<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mac | L. Collado-Torres</title>
    <link>/tags/mac/</link>
      <atom:link href=http://lcolladotor.github.io/tags/mac/index.xml rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Mac</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2011-2020. All thoughts and opinions here are my own. The icon was designed by [Mauricio Guzmán](https://www.linkedin.com/in/mauricio-guzman-6529b551/) and is inspired by [Huichol culture](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Huichol); it represents my community building interests</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu2b32c4ab415f12f472f73c7b0301b0d1_19400_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Mac</title>
      <link>/tags/mac/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alfred: a must for any Mac user</title>
      <link>/2013/02/15/alfred-a-must-for-any-mac-user/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2013/02/15/alfred-a-must-for-any-mac-user/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of the semester, I decided to go hunting for Mac apps that would help me be more organizing and/or enjoy my Mac even more. After all, I was using the basics –with multiple spaces– and had only customized my favorite editors. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out that &lt;a href=&#34;http://bit.ly/12w0M6m&#34;&gt;Alfred&lt;/a&gt; is an excellent app. The free version can get you a lot of mileage and save you lots of time by typing alt + space, then entering  the keyword you want to search in Google. Or alt + space, image, then the  query for Google Images. Or alt + space, find, the parts of the name of a file you want. Or alt + space, in, something you want to find inside a file. I love the alt + space, define, something I want to find in the dictionary. I know that dictionaries are just around the corner [a bookmark away!] but still, thanks to Alfred I now look up words WAY more frequently than what I did before. I mean, just not having to move my hands away from my keyboard and doing a ton of stuff is just great =)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are plenty of other default searches that come with Alfred&amp;#8217;s free version. Another thing that I love is using it to do system commands like lock the screen, or send my computer to sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try it out!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
