<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Family on L. Collado-Torres</title>
    <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/categories/family/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Family on L. Collado-Torres</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2011-2017 Leonardo Collado Torres under (CC) BY-NC-SA</copyright>
    <atom:link href="/categories/family/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>National Science and Arts 2011 awardee: Julio Collado Vides</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2011/11/19/National-Science-and-Arts-2011-awardee-Julio-Collado-Vides</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2011/11/19/National-Science-and-Arts-2011-awardee-Julio-Collado-Vides</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m very happy to announce that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ccg.unam.mx/en/personalInfo?idPersona=39&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Julio Collado Vides&lt;/a&gt;, my father, was &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sep.gob.mx/es/sep1/C1291111&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; yesterday as the recipient for this year&amp;#8217;s National Science and Arts 2011 award for the Physics, Mathematics and Natural Sciences fields by the SEP (Public Education Secretariat). Obviously, he is very happy and everyone in our extended family is proud of him, and celebrating with some Don Julio tequila! (that probably was only me :P)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why him? That&amp;#8217;s a question for the selection committee but I can try to answer a similar question: what are his major contributions? At least the way I see it, he is renowned as being one of the first bioinformaticians in Mexico. His &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ccg.unam.mx/en/ComputationalGenomics&#34;&gt;Computational Genomics&lt;/a&gt; group constructs and maintains the RegulonDB database which holds curated information (specially on regulation) for &lt;em&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/em&gt;. Back in the day, he has this crazy idea of building mathematical gramatics (something like that) which he then used to carry out promoter-binding site searches on the &lt;em&gt;E. coli &lt;/em&gt;genome. That&amp;#8217;s why he is one of the co-authors of the 1996 paper announcing the complete sequence of this famous bacteria. He has also being one of the promoters of Genomic sciences and was part of the founders of the undergraduate program for this field at UNAM: National Autonomous University of Mexico &amp;#8212; the best for science (and many other areas) in Mexico. He also has performed more administrative tasks like being the director of the Center for Genomic Sciences, but I don&amp;#8217;t think that counts much for the award. I think that it&amp;#8217;s significant that he is doing &lt;a href=&#34;http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=julio+collado+vides&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;btnG=Search&amp;amp;as_sdt=1%2C21&amp;amp;as_sdtp=on&#34;&gt;very good research&lt;/a&gt; in Mexico and is a leader in his field, which is why he is one of the few mexican scientists with an NIH (National Institute of Health in the US) grant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, this is an excellent news and join him in the celebrations :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
