<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Genomics | L. Collado-Torres</title>
    <link>/tags/genomics/</link>
      <atom:link href=http://lcolladotor.github.io/tags/genomics/index.xml rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Genomics</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2011-2020 Leonardo Collado Torres under (CC) BY-NC-SA 4.0. All thoughts and opinions here are my own. Icon is the [R logo](https://www.r-project.org/logo/) modified</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>Genomics</title>
      <link>/tags/genomics/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>SciLifeLab Prize: you still have time to participate! </title>
      <link>/2018/06/20/scilifelab-prize-you-still-have-time-to-participate/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2018/06/20/scilifelab-prize-you-still-have-time-to-participate/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-06-20-scilifelab-prize-you-still-have-time-to-participate_files/unnamed.jpg&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have recently been getting reminder emails from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencemag.org/science-scilifelab-prize-young-scientists&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt; &amp;amp; SciLifeLab Prize for Young Scientists&lt;/a&gt;. The application deadline is July 15th, 2018!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year I submitted an entry to this competition and I enjoyed the experience, even if it was a bit rushed. The process of joining the competition is relatively straight forward:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write an essay about your Ph.D. thesis work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get a recommendation letter from your Ph.D. advisor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write a short Ph.D. thesis abstract section, list your affiliation, education, academic and professional awards and professional experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Include references.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don’t need to pay for competing! You already did the very hard part of completing your Ph.D.!!! I also like competitions like this one that invite you to think about your thesis and how to explain it. You should note that you are only eligible to participate once in this competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can read about the 4 winners from 2017 at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencemag.org/prizes/SciLifeLab/2017&#34;&gt;www.sciencemag.org/prizes/SciLifeLab/2017&lt;/a&gt; and other years too to draw some inspiration from. I didn’t win, but I’m still going to share my entry in case it’s useful to others. I’m also sharing it to keep with the theme of also sharing your failures that I talked in my &lt;a href=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/06/11/mindfulness/#.WyrJbBJKjUI&#34;&gt;mindfulness post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t know exactly why my entry was not selected (you might have some ideas on how to improve it!). But I can tell you that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I knew the deadline was coming but I wrote it the week it was due.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I didn’t have time to ask for some more specific feedback from others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I forgot that a recommendation letter was needed, so I asked at the very last minute for one by &lt;a href=&#34;http://jtleek.com/&#34;&gt;Jeff Leek&lt;/a&gt;. I don’t know what magic he did (likely skipping a few hours of sleep, sorry!!!) but he managed to send it in time. Oops!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure if I should have emphasized more the impact of my Ph.D. thesis work or what else to do. However, I do know that this exercise was useful. First, just re-reading my essay makes me smile. Also, Figure 1 shown here became a figure in the &lt;code&gt;recount-workflow&lt;/code&gt; paper &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Collado-Torres_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://f1000research.com/articles/6-1558/v1&#39;&gt;Collado-Torres, Nellore, and Jaffe, 2017&lt;/a&gt;). Furthermore, when I was notified about the &lt;a href=&#34;https://bioinformatics-peer-prize-iii.thinkable.org/&#34;&gt;Thinkable Bioinformatics Peer Prize III&lt;/a&gt; I didn’t have to think twice about joining that competition. Finally, since I wrote it in an Rmd file, it was easy to modify for this blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like I’ve said, you have nothing to lose by joining this competition. Yes, you have to invest a bit of time. But it can be helpful and morale boosting! Plus, you have a chance to win it!!! Just remember that the deadline is July 15th, 2018 (and to give your advisor enough time to write their recommendation letter for you)!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case you are curious, here are my full &lt;a href=&#34;https://gist.github.com/lcolladotor/657aaae9d16aff3ce468f44f8780a317&#34;&gt;entry files&lt;/a&gt; (the figure is here though).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Collado-Torres_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Collado-Torres_2017&#34;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt; L. Collado-Torres, A. Nellore and A. E. Jaffe. “recount workflow: Accessing over 70,000 human RNA-seq samples with Bioconductor [version 1; referees: 1 approved, 2 approved with reservations]”. In: &lt;em&gt;F1000Research&lt;/em&gt; (2017). DOI: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.12688/f1000research.12223.1&#34;&gt;10.12688/f1000research.12223.1&lt;/a&gt;. URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://f1000research.com/articles/6-1558/v1&#34;&gt;https://f1000research.com/articles/6-1558/v1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without further ado, here’s my full entry:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;usable-human-gene-expression-data-and-annotation-agnostic-methods&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Usable human gene expression data and annotation-agnostic methods&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the last decade RNA sequencing (RNA-seq) has become the predominant assay for measuring gene expression. RNA-seq allows us to measure all expressed genes, improve gene and transcript annotation, and measure expressed sequences that otherwise are excluded in microarray studies. Typical RNA-seq analysis starts with a matrix containing the number of RNA-seq reads overlapping each gene for each sample &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Love et al. 2016; Law et al. 2016)&lt;/span&gt;. To compute such a matrix, you first map the raw data to the genome with aligners such as &lt;em&gt;TopHat2&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;HISAT&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Kim et al. 2013; Kim, Langmead, and Salzberg 2015)&lt;/span&gt; and then use tools such as &lt;em&gt;Rsubread&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;HTSeq&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Y, GK, and W 2013; Anders, Pyl, and Huber 2014)&lt;/span&gt; to construct the read count matrix. After measuring enough samples, you can determine which genes are differentially expressed between two or more groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I started my graduate studies with Jeff Leek, the most commonly used methods for differential expression analysis were &lt;em&gt;DESeq&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Anders and Huber 2010)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;em&gt;edgeR&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Robinson, McCarthy, and Smyth 2010)&lt;/span&gt;. Leek and colleagues put together a set of gene count matrices in a project called &lt;em&gt;ReCount&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Frazee, Langmead, and Leek 2011)&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;em&gt;ReCount&lt;/em&gt; allowed researchers to access several datasets without having to run the whole processing pipeline. &lt;em&gt;ReCount&lt;/em&gt; then helped the development of new methods such as &lt;em&gt;DESeq2&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Love, Huber, and Anders 2014)&lt;/span&gt;. It was also Leek and colleagues that decided to look at RNA-seq data in a manner less dependent on potentially incomplete gene annotation. With the increase in size of RNA-seq projects, they thought it would be feasible to assess the differential expression signal at base pair resolution in an approach called differentially expressed regions (DER) finder &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Frazee et al. 2014)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was around then that I started to work with Andrew Jaffe, who had RNA-seq data from the human brain. Jaffe and colleagues hypothesized that the gene annotation for the human brain might be incomplete and were interested in applying the DER finder approach to their data. With them, I modified the DER finder approach to make it computationally feasible to analyze these human brain samples at base resolution &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Jaffe et al. 2015)&lt;/span&gt;. We indeed found that the human brain transcriptome was not fully annotated and identified intronic DERs that were present in other brain datasets, including from mouse, and showed these regions were enriched for genetic risk for brain disorders. Further computational improvements to the DER finder approach yielded the &lt;em&gt;derfinder&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Collado-Torres, Nellore, Frazee, et al. 2017)&lt;/span&gt; Bioconductor &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Huber et al. 2015)&lt;/span&gt; package, reducing computing time from days to hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I was working on &lt;em&gt;derfinder&lt;/em&gt;, Abhinav Nellore was developing &lt;em&gt;Rail-RNA&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Nellore, Collado-Torres, et al. 2016)&lt;/span&gt; with the goal of aligning large RNA-seq datasets. We determined that we only needed coverage data instead of alignments to use &lt;em&gt;derfinder&lt;/em&gt; and to perform gene level analyses. Coverage data files are much smaller than alignment files, which meant that we could greatly reduce our storage costs when using &lt;em&gt;Rail-RNA&lt;/em&gt; and allowed us to think as big as possible. Initially we looked at 21,504 human RNA-seq samples and explored the landscape of exon-exon junctions &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Nellore, Jaffe, et al. 2016)&lt;/span&gt;. The reads spanning exon-exon junctions provided by &lt;em&gt;Rail-RNA&lt;/em&gt; can be used for a second type of annotation-agnostic analysis as these reads provide information about exon skipping, alternative donor/acceptor sites and novel events. With a fairly conservative filter we determined that 18.6% of exon-exon junctions were missing in the annotation &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Nellore, Jaffe, et al. 2016)&lt;/span&gt;. This observation along with the fact that exon-exon junctions can be used to determine differential transcript usage gave strength to this second annotation-agnostic RNA-seq analysis method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Researchers around the world have shared their raw data via the Sequence Read Archive or via large consortiums such as the Genotype-Tissue Expression study (GTEx) and the Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA). However, it still is complicated to align and compute count matrices for these datasets. We thought that if the public data was uniformly processed that we could make this large body of human expression data more reusable. We were well positioned to carry out this project and just needed resources. Luckily, Jeff Leek, Ben Langmead and others got together and funded the implementation of &lt;em&gt;Rail-RNA&lt;/em&gt; to analyze all the human public RNA-seq data available at the time, over 70,000 samples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34; style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;
&lt;span id=&#34;fig:figure1&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-06-20-scilifelab-prize-you-still-have-time-to-participate_files/figure1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Overview of the data available in recount2. Reads aligned to the reference genome can be used to compute a base pair coverage curve, identify exon-exon junctions and compute gene and exon count matrices. The reads spanning exon-exon junctions (jx) are used to compute a third count matrix that includes un-annotated junctions (jx 3 and 4). Annotation-agnostic expressed regions can be determined from the coverage data.&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
Figure 1: Overview of the data available in recount2. Reads aligned to the reference genome can be used to compute a base pair coverage curve, identify exon-exon junctions and compute gene and exon count matrices. The reads spanning exon-exon junctions (jx) are used to compute a third count matrix that includes un-annotated junctions (jx 3 and 4). Annotation-agnostic expressed regions can be determined from the coverage data.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We computed gene count matrices for these 70,000 samples and made them available as the &lt;em&gt;recount2&lt;/em&gt; resource that can be accessed at &lt;a href=&#34;https://jhubiostatistics.shinyapps.io/recount/&#34;&gt;jhubiostatistics.shinyapps.io/recount/&lt;/a&gt; as well as through the &lt;em&gt;recount&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Collado-Torres, Nellore, Kammers, et al. 2017)&lt;/span&gt; Bioconductor package, thus representing a major improvement over &lt;em&gt;ReCount&lt;/em&gt;. To take advantage of the data as much as possible, we also released exon and exon-exon junction count matrices as well as the coverage data files required for the DER finder approach, thus enabling both annotation-agnostic methods we developed that complement traditional methods. Figure 1 illustrates the type of information that is available via &lt;em&gt;recount2&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My colleagues and I believe that &lt;em&gt;recount2&lt;/em&gt; will fuel the development of new analytical methods and greatly increase the usability of the public human gene expression data researchers have collected over the years. In the meantime, we are working hard on improving the data in &lt;em&gt;recount2&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Ellis, Collado-Torres, and Leek 2017; Wilks et al. 2017)&lt;/span&gt; and exploring how to leverage results from different RNA-seq analytical approaches &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Jaffe et al. 2017)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ph.d.thesis-abstract&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ph.D. thesis abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leonardo Collado-Torres’ thesis work is centered around the development of R software packages for analyzing RNA sequencing (RNA-seq) and ChIP sequencing (ChIP-seq) high throughput genomic data. The first chapter describes the &lt;em&gt;derfinder&lt;/em&gt; Bioconductor package which implements the DER Finder approach for identifying differentially expressed regions with RNA-seq data in an annotation-agnostic manner. The second chapter shows how &lt;em&gt;derfinder&lt;/em&gt; can be applied to ChIP-seq data to identify differentially bounded regions. The third chapter describes the &lt;em&gt;regionReport&lt;/em&gt; Bioconductor package for producing HTML or PDF reports from region-based genomic analyses, such as the &lt;em&gt;derfinder&lt;/em&gt; analyses described in the previous chapters. The last thesis project Leonardo Collado-Torres carried out was the development of the &lt;em&gt;recount2&lt;/em&gt; resource and accompanying &lt;em&gt;recount&lt;/em&gt; Bioconductor package using the &lt;em&gt;Rail-RNA&lt;/em&gt; results from processing all the public human RNA-seq data at the time, which spans over 70,000 samples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;affiliation&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Affiliation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lieber Institute for Brain Development, Johns Hopkins Medical Campus, Baltimore, Maryland, 21205, USA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;education&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Education&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2011-2016. Ph.D. in Biostatistics at Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health, Baltimore, US. Advised by Jeff Leek and Andrew Jaffe.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2005-2009. Bachelor in Genomic Sciences (LCG) at the National Autonomous University of Mexico (UNAM), Cuernavaca, MX.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2002-2005. High school at ITESM Campus Cuernavaca, Cuernavaca, MX.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;academic-and-professional-awards&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Academic and professional awards&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2011: Awarded CONACyT Mexico scholarship for PhD studies outside Mexico.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2009: &lt;em&gt;Summa Cum Laude&lt;/em&gt; for bachelor in Genomic Sciences studies at LCG-UNAM.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2005: Best high school average (&lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\sim\)&lt;/span&gt; 200 students): awarded ITESM system 90% scholarship for college studies, declined to join LCG-UNAM.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;professional-experience&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Professional experience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016-current. Data Scientist with Andrew Jaffe lab at LIBD, Baltimore. At LIBD, Dr. Collado-Torres is part of the Data Science team which goals include better understanding and characterizing genomics signatures in the human brain, including DNA methylation and gene expression. Leonardo helps mentor other team members, provides support for LIBD projects and is advancing his academic career as part of Andrew Jaffe’s lab.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2009-2011. Bioinformatician with Enrique Morett lab at IBT-UNAM, Cuernavaca, MX. Identified transcriptions start sites and transcription units in &lt;em&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Geobacter sulfurreducens&lt;/em&gt; with RNA-seq data. Developed the &lt;em&gt;BacterialTranscription&lt;/em&gt; R package.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2009-2011. Scientific executive at Winter Genomics in Cuernavaca, MX. Responsible for recruiting and hiring new personnel, overseeing and supervising bioinformaticians, training new employees, writing research reports and presenting them to colleagues, and organizing all scientific projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2007-2009. Undergraduate research assistant at Guillermo Davila’s lab at CCG-UNAM, Cuernavaca, MX. Determined bacteriophage ecological groups by developing a method based on codon distribution of all phage sequenced genomes. Joint work with Sur Herrera Paredes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2006-2007. Undergraduate research assistant at Roberto Kolter’s lab at Harvard, Boston, US. Supervisor: Elizabeth Shank. Carried out screenings to identify bacteria that activate the production of exopolysaccharide through the activation of the gene tasA in &lt;em&gt;Bacillus subtilis&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;references&#34; class=&#34;section level2 unnumbered&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;refs&#34; class=&#34;references&#34;&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-anders2010&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anders, Simon, and Wolfgang Huber. 2010. “Differential Expression Analysis for Sequence Count Data.” &lt;em&gt;Genome Biology&lt;/em&gt; 11 (10): R106. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1186/gb-2010-11-10-r106&#34;&gt;10.1186/gb-2010-11-10-r106&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-anders2014htseq&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anders, Simon, Paul Theodor Pyl, and Wolfgang Huber. 2014. “HTSeq–A Python Framework to Work with High-Throughput Sequencing Data.” &lt;em&gt;bioRxiv&lt;/em&gt;. Cold Spring Harbor Labs Journals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-collado-torres-derfinder&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Collado-Torres, Leonardo, Abhinav Nellore, Alyssa C. Frazee, Christopher Wilks, Michael I. Love, Ben Langmead, Rafael A. Irizarry, Jeffrey T. Leek, and Andrew E. Jaffe. 2017. “Flexible Expressed Region Analysis for RNA-Seq with Derfinder.” &lt;em&gt;Nucleic Acids Research&lt;/em&gt; 45 (2): e9–e9. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkw852&#34;&gt;10.1093/nar/gkw852&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-collado-torres-recount2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Collado-Torres, Leonardo, Abhinav Nellore, Kai Kammers, Shannon E. Ellis, Margaret A. Taub, Kasper D. Hansen, Andrew E. Jaffe, Ben Langmead, and Jeffrey T. Leek. 2017. “Reproducible RNA-Seq Analysis Using Recount2.” &lt;em&gt;Nature Biotechnology&lt;/em&gt; 35 (4): 319–21. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/nbt.3838&#34;&gt;10.1038/nbt.3838&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-ellis2017&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ellis, Shannon E, Leonardo Collado-Torres, and Jeffrey Leek. 2017. “Improving the Value of Public Rna-Seq Expression Data by Phenotype Prediction.” &lt;em&gt;bioRxiv&lt;/em&gt;. Cold Spring Harbor Labs Journals. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1101/145656&#34;&gt;10.1101/145656&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-frazee2014&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frazee, Alyssa C, Sarven Sabunciyan, Kasper D Hansen, Rafael A Irizarry, and Jeffrey T Leek. 2014. “Differential Expression Analysis of RNA-seq Data at Single-Base Resolution.” &lt;em&gt;Biostatistics (Oxford, England)&lt;/em&gt;, January. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1093/biostatistics/kxt053&#34;&gt;10.1093/biostatistics/kxt053&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-frazee2011&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frazee, Alyssa C., Ben Langmead, and Jeffrey T. Leek. 2011. “ReCount: A Multi-Experiment Resource of Analysis-Ready RNA-Seq Gene Count Datasets.” &lt;em&gt;BMC Bioinformatics&lt;/em&gt; 12: 449. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2105-12-449&#34;&gt;10.1186/1471-2105-12-449&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-huber2015&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Huber, Wolfgang, Vincent J Carey, Robert Gentleman, Simon Anders, Marc Carlson, Benilton S Carvalho, Hector Corrada Bravo, et al. 2015. “Orchestrating High-Throughput Genomic Analysis with Bioconductor.” &lt;em&gt;Nature Methods&lt;/em&gt; 12 (2). Nature Publishing Group: 115–21. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/nmeth.3252&#34;&gt;10.1038/nmeth.3252&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-jaffe2015&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jaffe, Andrew E., Jooheon Shin, Leonardo Collado-Torres, Jeffrey T. Leek, Ran Tao, Chao Li, Yuan Gao, et al. 2015. “Developmental Regulation of Human Cortex Transcription and Its Clinical Relevance at Single Base Resolution.” &lt;em&gt;Nature Neuroscience&lt;/em&gt; 18 (1): 154–61. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/nn.3898&#34;&gt;10.1038/nn.3898&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-jaffe2017&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jaffe, Andrew E., Richard Straub, Joo Heon Shin, Ran Tao, Yuan Gao, Leonardo Collado-Torres, Tony Kam-Thong, et al. 2017. “Developmental and genetic regulation of the human cortex transcriptome in schizophrenia.” &lt;em&gt;bioRxiv&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-kim2015&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kim, Daehwan, Ben Langmead, and Steven L. Salzberg. 2015. “HISAT: A Fast Spliced Aligner with Low Memory Requirements.” &lt;em&gt;Nature Methods&lt;/em&gt; 12 (4): 357–60. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/nmeth.3317&#34;&gt;10.1038/nmeth.3317&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-kim2013&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kim, Daehwan, Geo Pertea, Cole Trapnell, Harold Pimentel, Ryan Kelley, and Steven L Salzberg. 2013. “TopHat2: Accurate Alignment of Transcriptomes in the Presence of Insertions, Deletions and Gene Fusions.” &lt;em&gt;Genome Biology&lt;/em&gt; 14 (4): R36. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1186/gb-2013-14-4-r36&#34;&gt;10.1186/gb-2013-14-4-r36&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-Law2016a&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Law, Charity W, Monther Alhamdoosh, Shian Su, Gordon K Smyth, and Matthew E Ritchie. 2016. “RNA-seq analysis is easy as 1-2-3 with limma, Glimma and edgeR.” &lt;em&gt;F1000Research&lt;/em&gt; 5 (May): 1408. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.12688/f1000research.9005.2&#34;&gt;10.12688/f1000research.9005.2&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-love2014&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Love, Michael I, Wolfgang Huber, and Simon Anders. 2014. “Moderated Estimation of Fold Change and Dispersion for Rna-Seq Data with Deseq2.” &lt;em&gt;Genome Biology&lt;/em&gt; 15 (12). Springer: 1–21.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-Love2016&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Love, Michael I., Simon Anders, Vladislav Kim, and Wolfgang Huber. 2016. “RNA-Seq workflow: gene-level exploratory analysis and differential expression.” &lt;em&gt;F1000Research&lt;/em&gt; 4 (May): 1070. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.12688/f1000research.7035.2&#34;&gt;10.12688/f1000research.7035.2&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-rail-rna&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nellore, Abhinav, Leonardo Collado-Torres, Andrew E. Jaffe, José Alquicira-Hernández, Christopher Wilks, Jacob Pritt, James Morton, Jeffrey T. Leek, and Ben Langmead. 2016. “Rail-RNA: Scalable Analysis of RNA-Seq Splicing and Coverage.” &lt;em&gt;Bioinformatics (Oxford, England)&lt;/em&gt;, September. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btw575&#34;&gt;10.1093/bioinformatics/btw575&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-nellore2016human&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nellore, Abhinav, Andrew E. Jaffe, Jean-Philippe Fortin, José Alquicira-Hernández, Leonardo Collado-Torres, Siruo Wang, Robert A. Phillips Iii, et al. 2016. “Human Splicing Diversity and the Extent of Unannotated Splice Junctions Across Human RNA-Seq Samples on the Sequence Read Archive.” &lt;em&gt;Genome Biology&lt;/em&gt; 17 (1): 266.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-robinson2010&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Robinson, Mark D, Davis J McCarthy, and Gordon K Smyth. 2010. “edgeR: a Bioconductor Package for Differential Expression Analysis of Digital Gene Expression Data.” &lt;em&gt;Bioinformatics (Oxford, England)&lt;/em&gt; 26 (1): 139–40. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btp616&#34;&gt;10.1093/bioinformatics/btp616&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-wilks2017&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wilks, Christopher, Phani Gaddipati, Abhinav Nellore, and Benjamin Langmead. 2017. “Snaptron: querying and visualizing splicing across tens of thousands of RNA-seq samples.” &lt;em&gt;bioRxiv&lt;/em&gt;. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1101/097881&#34;&gt;10.1101/097881&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-rsubread&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Y, Liao, Smyth GK, and Shi W. 2013. “The Subread Aligner: Fast, Accurate and Scalable Read Mapping by Seed-and-Vote.” &lt;em&gt;Nucleic Acids Research&lt;/em&gt; 41 (10): e108.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Keeping in touch (ENAR2014?) and philosophical questions regarding México&#39;s future in genomics</title>
      <link>/2013/06/12/keeping-in-touch-enar2014-and-philosophical/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2013/06/12/keeping-in-touch-enar2014-and-philosophical/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The following text is an email I sent to several of my friends from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/about&#34;&gt;LCG undergraduate program &lt;/a&gt;I studied. There I talk about keeping in touch, I invite them to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.enar.org/meetings.cfm&#34;&gt;ENAR 2014&lt;/a&gt;, and also talk about some philosophical questions regarding our future. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m posting it here because I don&amp;#8217;t mind sharing these thoughts and because I don&amp;#8217;t have the current email addresses of many former LCG students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Enjoy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hola a todos,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Les escribo por el gusto de mantener el contacto, por razones académicas, y también por un rollo filosófico / a futuro.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacto&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Como ya les dije, me da mucho gusto escribirles. Cuando lo hago sé que generalmente resulta en mails largos, así que intentando ser corto, siento que hoy termina el ciclo de personas que conocí en la LCG. Digo, hoy se gradua la 7ma generación y realmente no conozco las nuevas. Fueron años muy buenos los que viví con todos allá en Cuerna y ojalá podamos mantener cierto vínculo a través de los años. Sé que cuesta. Por ejemplo, no tengo los correos de algunos (o no los encontré vía google), otros los intenté adivinar vía &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/titulados&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/titulados&#34;&gt;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/titulados&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; y la regla de 8 caracteres, y solo pocos lo siguen teniendo en su página de Facebook (por rollos de seguridad). También soy bastante malo para escribir regularmente (ya sea vía email o mis blogs: &lt;a href=&#34;http://fellgernon.tumblr.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;académico&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;más personal&lt;/span&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Este año en especial he disfrutado (y seguiré disfrutando) mucho de ver a algunos aunque sea un par de horas =)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;También me gusta mucho cuando me piden ayuda sobre algo, aunque sea lento en contestar :P&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ENAR 2014&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;De lo académico, les quiero avisar que en 2014 van a organizar acá en Baltimore el congreso ENAR (Eastern North American Regional) en marzo del 2014. Es un congreso de bioestadística con una buena parte enfocada a la genómica. Y bueno, muchas cosas hechas en R. Mi jefe está organizando un par de las sesiones así que si tienen sugerencias de quienes invitar avísenme. Ustedes mismos ^_&lt;em&gt;^ &lt;/em&gt;(hay un buen número de pláticas por alumnos de posgrado &amp;amp; postdocs), sus jefes, etc. En fin, tal vez les interese el congreso.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;De 2014 no hay mucha info aún &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.enar.org/meetings.cfm&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.enar.org/meetings.cfm&#34;&gt;http://www.enar.org/meetings.cfm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, pero allí pueden ver lo que pasó en otros años.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rollos filosóficos&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;El rollo filosófico / a futuro tiene que ver con:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class=&#34;ol1&#34;&gt;&lt;li class=&#34;li1&#34;&gt;¿Qué condiciones piden para trabajar en México?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&#34;li1&#34;&gt;¿Cómo crear un vínculo más fuerte entre egresados LCG?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&#34;li1&#34;&gt;¿A qué dedicarse? ¿Academia? ¿Industria? ¿Otra cosa?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Del punto (1) lo he platicado con algunos pero creo que es un tema interesante y muy variado. Hay aspectos que tal vez están fuera de nuestro alcance como la seguridad, y hay otros como el ambiente de trabajo y de la ciencia. El rollo de plazas y los esfuerzos de algunos por crear espacios: CCG tiene algunas ahorita, Palacios &amp;amp; Dávila están haciendo un plan grande para repatriar ex-LCGs, el INMEGEN &amp;amp; el CINVESTAV han estado creciendo, o la idea de hacer un plan nosotros. Ojo, a penas me enteré que para tener plaza de investigador en la UNAM te piden tener un postdoc de 2 años: el chiste es que tengas publicaciones &amp;amp; hayas demostrado que la puedes hacer en la ciencia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;¿Sacrificas potencial académico trabajando en México? Dicho de otra forma, ¿cómo te afecta: el rollo del idioma, el de competir en condiciones que parecen ser más difíciles, o el de tener menos colaboradores cerca para crecer con su crítica &amp;amp; datos de última tecnología? O irse fuera de México (no hay por que ser mártir) y sentirse a gusto con esa decisión. Siempre hay formas de colaborar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Del punto (2) yo opino que puede ser a través de comentar artículos con gente ex-LCG involucrada (algo así &lt;a href=&#34;http://fellgernon.tumblr.com/post/45152484977/commenting-scientific-papers#.UbjBemTF1d8&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;describí aquí&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;), o tal vez vía &lt;a href=&#34;http://masciencia.org/&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;Más Ciencia por México&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (no los logré convencer en esto de comentar artículos). Digo, también ayudaría que &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/titulados&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/titulados&#34;&gt;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/titulados&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; tenga ligas a las páginas actuales de cada quien.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Del (3), en mi opinión cubre también todo el rollo de si queremos vivir con &amp;#8220;soft-money&amp;#8221; a través del ciclo de donativos (el pay-line es 10% en EUA ahorita por lo de sequester), de la libertad académica (¿es una realidad o una forma de cautivarnos?), y también depende del tipo de industria. Otra forma de ver este punto es ¿cual es el nivel de estrés con el que estamos dispuestos a vivir? ¿A qué aspiramos? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;En fin, dan ganas de organizar alguna reunión de ex-LCGs!! Mientras, a seguir con estudios &amp;amp; disfrutar la chamba (investigación o lo que estén haciendo).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Si me preguntan que busco con este correo, es simple:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;ul1&#34;&gt;&lt;li class=&#34;li1&#34;&gt;Mantener el contacto&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&#34;li1&#34;&gt;Invitarlos a ENAR 2014&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&#34;li1&#34;&gt;Promover discusión en estos temas filosóficos / a futuro&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saludos,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leo&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PD Perdón, terminó siendo un mail largo :P&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beware of mis-assembled genomes: still valid today!</title>
      <link>/2012/01/26/beware-of-mis-assembled-genomes-still-valid-today/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2012/01/26/beware-of-mis-assembled-genomes-still-valid-today/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been recently impressed by Steven Salzberg talk as &lt;a href=&#34;http://fellgernon.tumblr.com/post/16468048496/extensive-comments-and-review-about-the-recent-bake-off#.TyAz0OPOzIw&#34;&gt;you might have noticed&lt;/a&gt;, and browing &lt;a href=&#34;http://bioinformatics.igm.jhmi.edu/salzberg/&#34;&gt;his home page&lt;/a&gt; I stumbled upon his opinion piece (also by James Yorke): &lt;a href=&#34;http://cbcb.umd.edu/papers/Mis-assembledGenomesReprint.pdf&#34;&gt;Beware of mis-assembled genomes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s a short note published in 2005, but damn, can anyone deny that it fits perfectly for today&amp;#8217;s state of the art in the de &lt;em&gt;novo&lt;/em&gt; genome assembly field? I bet no one will. For instance, it&amp;#8217;s a solid statement to say:&lt;/p&gt;
&gt; The source of most mis-assemblies is, as it has always been, repeats.
&lt;p&gt;He didn&amp;#8217;t add a &amp;#8220;will always be&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;will be for at least 7 years more&amp;#8221; now that we are in 2012, but it feels like this will be the case until we can get accurate (and cheap) reads that span even the longest repeat. Well, maybe we don&amp;#8217;t need such huge reads as people have been able to find large genome duplications. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And as I said in my &lt;a href=&#34;http://fellgernon.tumblr.com/post/16468048496/extensive-comments-and-review-about-the-recent-bake-off#.TyAz0OPOzIw&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;#8217;m still surprised by how careless the human genome assembly was carried out as they didn&amp;#8217;t track their own steps. I was hoping that wasn&amp;#8217;t the case, but clearly it is:&lt;/p&gt;
&gt; Indeed, many of the original assemblies of parts of the human genome were done in the mid- and late-1990s, and are now lost.
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m also impressed by how accurate Steven and James&amp;#8217; prediction was when they forsaw that people were going to be misled in judging assembly quality by contigs size without taking into account mis-assemblies. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They also called upon the bioinformatics community to take action in evaluating genome assemblies. Due to the amount of data nowadays, it feels like a inhuman (well, incluster as infeasible by high power clusters :P, well, incomputable is the correct term) task. But with some funding, I bet Salzberg and colleagues could find a way to do so. At least partially. Yet, as with anything, you need motivation, and I&amp;#8217;m note sure they are motivated to clean up the mess. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Extensive comments and review about the recent bake-off of de novo genome assemblers &#34;GAGE&#34;</title>
      <link>/2012/01/25/extensive-comments-and-review-about-the-recent-bake-off/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2012/01/25/extensive-comments-and-review-about-the-recent-bake-off/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During this week&amp;#8217;s Genomics seminar at the Genome Cafe in the Biostats department, &lt;a href=&#34;http://scholar.google.com/citations?user=sUVeH-4AAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34;&gt;Steven Salzberg&lt;/a&gt; gave a talk on his team new published paper: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22147368&#34;&gt;GAGE: A critical evaluation of genome assemblies and assembly algorithms.&lt;/a&gt; I worked on a few assembly projects during my time at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wintergenomics.com/&#34;&gt;Winter Genomics&lt;/a&gt;, but that was not the main reason why I was immediately submerged into his talk. I think that it was due to his bold comments since comparing genome assemblers is a, hmm&amp;#8230;, delicate issue. I really like the confidence he has on his work and the way he projects it when he talks. It might be too preachy for some, but I like it. Plus it helps that I completely agreed on two key points that differentiate GAGE from it&amp;#8217;s competitors: &lt;a href=&#34;http://cnag.bsc.es/&#34;&gt;dnGASP&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://assemblathon.org/&#34;&gt;Assemblathon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, GAGE uses real data sets instead of simulated ones. I know that some might argue that a given data set can have specific properties that are not general or that it&amp;#8217;s biased to a certain assembler. It also feels a bit funny, because I started out assembling simulated data too. It certainly had its uses as I learnt a lot. But once you encounter a real data set you learn how complicated things can be, and it can be quite messy as no one gives you perfectly clean data. I haven&amp;#8217;t read much about GAGE&amp;#8217;s competitors, but regardless of how they simulate their data, I completely agree with Steven that GAGE has the advantage by using four real data sets. Plus, they were quite sensible when choosing the four data sets as they are Illumina data (the most common) with frequently used read sizes and library types. Note that even the bacterial genome have more than one replicon. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second key point is that the GAGE team made public all the data and assembly &lt;em&gt;recipes&lt;/em&gt; available through their &lt;a href=&#34;http://gage.cbcb.umd.edu/&#34;&gt;official site&lt;/a&gt; (which has a great summary in from of a FAQ explaining the project and key differences). They have certainly made an effort to guarantee the reproducibility of their results, which is hard to do and hasn&amp;#8217;t been done before. It&amp;#8217;s a sad feeling that it took so long for someone to focus on reproducibility. So it feels wrong that they have to stress out how unique this feature is on their paper, but they definitely had to. Hm&amp;#8230; can anyone reproduce the human genome assembly? I&amp;#8217;m not talking about someone reading the paper and doing it on their institution computers, but someone from the author team. I hope the changelog is saved at least in some kind of repository.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another important difference between GAGE and say Assemblaton, is that the for GAGE an in-house team ran the assemblers instead of asking the authors of each program to fine tune their results. If you had asked me a year ago, I would surely had supported the idea of asking the authors to run their programs. After all, even if you read all the documentation it&amp;#8217;s the authors who know the best tricks on how to use their assemblers (or should be very good users). Yet, I can see the point that in reality it&amp;#8217;s not the authors who run their code for each application. It&amp;#8217;s a person or team of bioinformaticians (or a biologist struggling to death with UNIX) that has read the manual &amp;amp; papers (hopefully) from a few tools and decided which is his favorite one. During this process they probably ran a few of the assemblers with a small parameter scan and compared the results. The GAGE pipeline is very similar and hence feels much real. They obviously did this process in a more rigorous way and made sure the conditions allowed comparing the assemblers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the steps common to all of their &lt;em&gt;recipes&lt;/em&gt; was to run &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21114842&#34;&gt;Quake: quality-aware detection and correction of sequencing errors.&lt;/a&gt; I didn&amp;#8217;t know about this specific tool before, but I did know about the idea. Basically, you plot the distribution of the k-mers multiplicity from your data and do something to those that are possible errors (those k-mers that are unique or have very low multiplicity compared to the expected value); most commonly you try to correct them and if you can&amp;#8217;t, you discard them. That&amp;#8217;s a very broad explanation and I&amp;#8217;m sure that interested readers will download the original paper. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, the point is that they cleaned the data sets prior to using any assembler. I couldn&amp;#8217;t agree more to the sentence:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High-quality data can produce dramatic differences in the results&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Running some kind of preprocessing cleaning tool should help, but you can&amp;#8217;t do miracles with crappy data. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is getting huge, so I&amp;#8217;ll jump to some points I&amp;#8217;d like to highlight though it&amp;#8217;ll still be very long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I&amp;#8217;m amazed by the simple concept that is &amp;#8220;N50 corrected&amp;#8221;. It does look complicated to calculate, but the idea of splitting contigs when an error (at least a 5 bp indel) is found (they have Sanger-sequence reference genomes for 3 of them) before calculating the N50 size is just great. It&amp;#8217;s simple and very effective. By using this statistic and comparing it to the original N50 size you can clearly detect &lt;em&gt;aggressive&lt;/em&gt; assemblers that don&amp;#8217;t mind adding errors vs highly conservative ones. Then, comparing &amp;#8220;N50 corrected&amp;#8221; vs the number of errors (as in figure 6) is VERY informative. I just love that figure!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result is a bit frustrating because the winner is ALLPATHS-LG. Don&amp;#8217;t get me wrong, I think that they are doing great work (they introduced new statistics for comparing assemblies, they are exploiting library preparation more than the rest, etc) but it&amp;#8217;s simply hard to come by a data set that meets ALLPATHS-LG&amp;#8217; requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, no matter which assembler you use, your result is going to contain lots of errors. There is no way around it, it&amp;#8217;s a fact! Hm&amp;#8230; unless you want tiny contigs (very conservative assemblers) which aren&amp;#8217;t really useful. I think that it&amp;#8217;ll be important to stress this out to consumers of the technology instead of fueling their wild dreams of high-quality finished (not draft) de novo assemblies. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, de &lt;em&gt;novo&lt;/em&gt; genome assembly (specially for large genomes) is still a complicated endeavor. You shouldn&amp;#8217;t take it lightly!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you might have noticed, I found this paper (and the talk) to be very stimulating and interesting. And as I forgot to do so during the talk, &lt;strong&gt;thank you Salzberg et al. for taking a huge step in the right direction&lt;/strong&gt;. It&amp;#8217;ll surely help those working on the field and that at some point asked themselves:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What will an assembly based on short reads look like?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which assembly software will produce the best results?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What parameters should be used when running the software?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple more notes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;It&amp;#8217;s sad, but &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ebi.ac.uk/~zerbino/velvet/&#34;&gt;Velvet&lt;/a&gt; didn&amp;#8217;t perform as well as I hoped. I had been convinced for a while that it is one of the best assemblers out there. Plus I&amp;#8217;m surprised that it couldn&amp;#8217;t run on a 256&amp;#160;GB machine for the bumble bee data set.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take a look at the E-size statistic on the methods section of the paper. It&amp;#8217;s interesting that it correlates well with N50 size. At times, I haven&amp;#8217;t been too eager to select a best assembly on N50 size as it might not be one of the longest assemblies and I felt like I was wasting data. But it is a very reasonable summary statistic for such a hard problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;#8217;m still curious on whether gap-closers like &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez/20388197?dopt=Abstract&amp;amp;holding=f1000,f1000m,isrctn&#34;&gt;IMAGE: Iterative Mapping and Assembly for Gap Elimination&lt;/a&gt; (I don&amp;#8217;t know why they didn&amp;#8217;t include the name on their paper title &amp;gt;.&amp;lt;) correctly increase scaffold/contig length by &lt;a href=&#34;http://genomebiology.com/2010/11/4/R41/figure/F1&#34;&gt;re-assembling local &lt;em&gt;border&lt;/em&gt; paired-reads&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check the websites of the competitors. GAGE looks more complete to me and I&amp;#8217;m quite surprised dnGASP doesn&amp;#8217;t include links to the other sites! The &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/#!/gagecompetition&#34;&gt;GAGE twitter&lt;/a&gt; might be a bit too much (plus it seems abandoned).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/news/2011/110323/full/471425a.html&#34;&gt;Here is a news commentary &lt;/a&gt;which talks about the three competitors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I found it funny when Salzberg declared a winner in the talk, but it&amp;#8217;s surely takes some guts to do so and I agree that it had to be done after such a rigorous comparison (or &amp;#8220;bake-off&amp;#8221; ^_^).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From the advice section in Genomics 2011 (&lt;a href=&#34;http://fellgernon.tumblr.com/post/16368703139/commenting-genomics-in-2011#.Tx922ePOzIw&#34;&gt;check my long post about it&lt;/a&gt;), &amp;#8220;Published is better than perfect&amp;#8221;. Results from a bake-off like GAGE are going to change quickly since new updates are released quickly, but they are very helpful!!!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Commenting: Genomics in 2011</title>
      <link>/2012/01/23/commenting-genomics-in-2011/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2012/01/23/commenting-genomics-in-2011/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today is my first day of classes and &lt;a href=&#34;http://scholar.google.com/citations?hl=en&amp;amp;user=8XOPyM4AAAAJ&amp;amp;oi=sra&#34;&gt;Kasper&lt;/a&gt; couldn&amp;#8217;t have had a better timing to share the link to &lt;a href=&#34;http://genomebiology.com/2011/12/12/137&#34;&gt;Genomics in 2011: challenges and opportunities&lt;/a&gt;. There, the Editorial Board members of Genome Biology gave their opinion on: important 2011 papers, influential people for their careers, advice to young scientists, top challenges in their field, and unlimited money projects. I felt identified several times and as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think one of the most important skills in research is the ability to communicate ideas. [&amp;#8230;] practicing both writing skills and oral presentation skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;here I am sharing my view on the paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall the paper is a good read and I enjoyed most of it, so I highly recommend reading it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The top papers section is quite broad and it felt to me like a huge abstract on many papers. Now I want to read the paper on &amp;#8220;phenologs&amp;#8221;, a concept that seems very simple and natural, and has helped understand a bit more what genes do (functional genomics).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The parts about influential people and unlimited money projects are not so interesting. I felt that it was too personal and I didn&amp;#8217;t feel that it related to me much. Regardless, I&amp;#8217;d like to highlight some parts of the text:&lt;/p&gt;
&gt; * [&amp;#8230;] showed me the fun of methodology development in computational biology
&gt; * [&amp;#8230;] emphasized establishing a solid foundation in computer science and statistics but also developed our skills to identify relevant and impactful biological questions
&gt; * His humble upbringing, ability to admit when he was wrong, and persistence for what was right has continued to inspire me.
&lt;p&gt;The advice section was very appealing to me and I felt reassured as some of the advice I gave even younger scientists (&lt;a href=&#34;http://fellgernon.tumblr.com/post/13739343319/introducing-biostatistics-to-first-year-lcg-students#.Tx3PlmPOz_g&#34;&gt;check my talk to LCG students&lt;/a&gt;) popped up. I surely learnt a few things too =)&lt;/p&gt;
&gt; * Surrounding yourself with people who are smarter than you also helps you raise your game.
&gt; * Published is better than perfect.
&gt; * Importance of communication
&gt; * you need to appreciate the biology as much as, if not more than, the statistical method or computer science
&gt; * The success of our field is ultimately measured by the impact we can have on our understanding of biology
&gt; * I would say it&amp;#8217;s the ability to understand both the experimental and the computational sciences. [&amp;#8230;] I would learn the key principles in computational biology or at the very least the linguistics, and vice versa.
&lt;p&gt;I hadn&amp;#8217;t taken consciousness of the fact that the amount of computing you can do (per dollar) is doubling every year while the size of genomic databases is going up by a factor of 10. I knew something was off and that we are getting more data, but I didn&amp;#8217;t know the ratio. Plus, I have to agree with the comment that cloud computing is not going to be the solution though I&amp;#8217;m not sure if:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only solution is to discover fundamentally better algorithms for processing these databases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure, we need better algorithms, but I think that it&amp;#8217;s fair to ask for cleaner and higher-quality data. This doesn&amp;#8217;t mean that the data format has to be simpler, as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Far too often, enough biological details are abstracted away so that the solution loses its biological relevance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sad, but true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do agree with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another challenge is to educate people about genomics and to tone down the natural hype of the genomics field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as with any discipline, it&amp;#8217;s not easy to explain your field to a random person and it&amp;#8217;s a harder job when someone exaggerates a set of results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The argument that RO1 NIH grants are not built for young genomics scientists is interesting and I do hope that it changes soon. Though I don&amp;#8217;t have a clue as to how the following is going to happen:&lt;/p&gt;
&gt; the last challenge is to transform the academic review system in our institutions&lt;/p&gt;
&gt; Understanding the systems-level ecological rules governing microbial community structure&lt;
&lt;p&gt;surely opened my eyes as it was one of my main interests a few years ago (and stills interests me ^^).&lt;/p&gt;
&gt; streamlining methods for turning next-generation data into actionable biology
&lt;p&gt;sounds very fancy!! It&amp;#8217;s as fancy, and important, as developing new ways to visualize networks that take into account time instead of viewing all the possibilities at once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To finish off the post, I agree completely with:&lt;/p&gt;
&gt;I believe the biggest bottleneck is the bioinformatics and the shortage of researchers in the field. There needs to be a big investment to address this shortage. 
&lt;p&gt;Note that I think that there are lots of bioinformatics-converts: people who recently joined the field to fill in the gap in their lab. As:&lt;/p&gt;
&gt;In my opinion, too many computational biology researchers are working in isolation on marginally relevant problems or making incremental improvements in areas that have already been well-populated by methods that are already adequate. 
&lt;p&gt;So, yes, we need more bioinformaticians as most labs have high-throughput experiments (with only one experiment you already need a bioinformatician), but I do hope that a good proportion of them are trained to develop methods and focus on important problems and new areas instead of marginally relevant ones on &amp;#8220;old&amp;#8221; areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s why I&amp;#8217;m studying a PhD in Biostatistics!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
