<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Genomics on L. Collado-Torres</title>
    <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/tags/genomics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Genomics on L. Collado-Torres</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2011-2018 Leonardo Collado Torres under (CC) BY-NC-SA</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://lcolladotor.github.io/tags/genomics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Keeping in touch (ENAR2014?) and philosophical questions regarding México&#39;s future in genomics</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/06/12/keeping-in-touch-enar2014-and-philosophical/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/06/12/keeping-in-touch-enar2014-and-philosophical/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The following text is an email I sent to several of my friends from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/about&#34;&gt;LCG undergraduate program &lt;/a&gt;I studied. There I talk about keeping in touch, I invite them to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.enar.org/meetings.cfm&#34;&gt;ENAR 2014&lt;/a&gt;, and also talk about some philosophical questions regarding our future. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m posting it here because I don&amp;#8217;t mind sharing these thoughts and because I don&amp;#8217;t have the current email addresses of many former LCG students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Enjoy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beware of mis-assembled genomes: still valid today!</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/01/26/Beware-of-mis-assembled-genomes-still-valid-today/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/01/26/Beware-of-mis-assembled-genomes-still-valid-today/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;#8217;ve been recently impressed by Steven Salzberg talk as you might have noticed, and browing his home page I stumbled upon his opinion piece (also by James Yorke): Beware of mis-assembled genomes.
It&amp;#8217;s a short note published in 2005, but damn, can anyone deny that it fits perfectly for today&amp;#8217;s state of the art in the de novo genome assembly field? I bet no one will. For instance, it&amp;#8217;s a solid statement to say:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Extensive comments and review about the recent bake-off of de novo genome assemblers &#34;GAGE&#34;</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/01/25/extensive-comments-and-review-about-the-recent-bake-off/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/01/25/extensive-comments-and-review-about-the-recent-bake-off/</guid>
      <description>During this week&amp;#8217;s Genomics seminar at the Genome Cafe in the Biostats department, Steven Salzberg gave a talk on his team new published paper: GAGE: A critical evaluation of genome assemblies and assembly algorithms. I worked on a few assembly projects during my time at Winter Genomics, but that was not the main reason why I was immediately submerged into his talk. I think that it was due to his bold comments since comparing genome assemblers is a, hmm&amp;#8230;, delicate issue.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Commenting: Genomics in 2011</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/01/23/Commenting-Genomics-in-2011/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/01/23/Commenting-Genomics-in-2011/</guid>
      <description>Today is my first day of classes and Kasper couldn&amp;#8217;t have had a better timing to share the link to Genomics in 2011: challenges and opportunities. There, the Editorial Board members of Genome Biology gave their opinion on: important 2011 papers, influential people for their careers, advice to young scientists, top challenges in their field, and unlimited money projects. I felt identified several times and as:
 I think one of the most important skills in research is the ability to communicate ideas.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>