<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Misc on L. Collado-Torres</title>
    <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/categories/Misc/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Misc on L. Collado-Torres</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2011-2018 Leonardo Collado Torres under (CC) BY-NC-SA 4.0. All thoughts and opinions here are my own.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://lcolladotor.github.io/categories/Misc/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Problems with an article from the Baltimore Sun covering Dr. Mahoney-Steel’s immigration issues</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/09/19/problems-with-an-article-from-the-baltimore-sun-covering-dr-mahoney-steel-s-immigration-issues/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/09/19/problems-with-an-article-from-the-baltimore-sun-covering-dr-mahoney-steel-s-immigration-issues/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, September 19th 2018, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.baltimoresun.com/balnews-dan-rodricks-20130507-staff.html&#34;&gt;Dan Rodricks&lt;/a&gt; (Twitter: &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/DanRodricks&#34;&gt;DanRodricks&lt;/a&gt;) published an article in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.baltimoresun.com&#34;&gt;Baltimore Sun&lt;/a&gt;. The article was shared to me with the title &lt;em&gt;I only thought this happened to Mexicans&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and is currently titled&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.baltimoresun.com/news/maryland/dan-rodricks-blog/bs-md-rodricks-0919-story.html&#34;&gt;“Rodricks: Hopkins library specialist hit by immigration crackdown after being blindsided by visa denial”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-09-19-problems-with-an-article-from-the-baltimore-sun-covering-dr-mahoney-steel-s-immigration-issues_files/Screen%20Shot%202018-09-19%20at%2011.43.50%20PM.png&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn’t like the title at all nor did I feel right when reading the article. I shared it with about 50 other Mexicans in Baltimore&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, talked about it over dinner, discussed a bit with Hopkins colleagues, and now thanks to all of them I have a clearer idea of what my problems with this article are. And there are many of them, but we can group them into:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the reporting by Dan Rodricks,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;em&gt;portrayed&lt;/em&gt; handling of Dr. Mahoney-Steel’s case by Johns Hopkins University,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and the &lt;em&gt;portrayed&lt;/em&gt; lack of attention by Dr. Mahoney-Steel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I get into all of it, there is a petition online in support of Dr. Mahoney-Steel that you can read and sign &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.change.org/p/johns-hopkins-university-support-dr-tamsyn-mahoney-steel-and-all-displaced-workers&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; if you want: nearly 2,000 people have already signed it. You can also &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.change.org/p/johns-hopkins-university-support-dr-tamsyn-mahoney-steel-and-all-displaced-workers/c?source_location=petition_show&#34;&gt;read other’s reasons&lt;/a&gt; for signing the petition. Right now I do not feel comfortable signing this petition, but maybe you are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;the-reporting-by-dan-rodricks&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The reporting by Dan Rodricks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article starts by framing Dr. Mahoney-Steel’s story around the fact that she had to return to England due to issues with her immigration paperwork and that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the reaction of several friends and colleagues was uncannily the same: “I thought this only happened to Mexicans.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was no need at all to grab attention to Dr. Mahoney-Steel’s story by mentioning Mexicans or any other Spanish-speaking immigrants. Dan Rodricks is trying to get the reader to think that &lt;em&gt;Mexicans are illegal immigrants&lt;/em&gt; (which many politicians have said), and thus that &lt;em&gt;they aren’t welcome&lt;/em&gt;, and then &lt;em&gt;ohh, others aren’t welcome either&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I’m glad that the title has been changed at the Baltimore Sun’s website, the first paragraph and last paragraph of the story still mention this quote that is attributed to friends and colleagues of Dr. Mahoney-Steel. They might have said this, but Dan Rodricks could have simply ignored their quote and framed his story along the lines of the updated title: a library specialist that is suffering because of the current immigration policies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My second problem with the reporting is that there is a lack of information that is important in this context. There are many ways to become a permanent resident in the US and thus get a &lt;em&gt;green card&lt;/em&gt;. Some of these ways involve getting sponsored by your employer. Some don’t. Basically, in some situations it would be the employer’s responsibility (Johns Hopkins University in this case) to be involved in and be supportive and in others I think that they are not obliged to help financially. You can have very different reactions to this story based on what mechanism Dr. Mahoney-Steel was asking Johns Hopkins University to help her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;the-portrayed-handling-of-dr.mahoney-steels-case-by-hopkins&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The &lt;em&gt;portrayed&lt;/em&gt; handling of Dr. Mahoney-Steel’s case by Hopkins&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m using &lt;em&gt;portrayed&lt;/em&gt; here because we currently don’t know Hopkins’ side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What seems to be the main reason why Dr. Mahoney-Steel’s case became a story is because she submitted her documents to request a renewal of her H-1B (highly specialized worker) visa to Johns Hopkins University’s &lt;a href=&#34;http://ois.jhu.edu/&#34;&gt;Office of International Services&lt;/a&gt;. She didn’t hear back from them until she heard in August 21st that they decided not to send her documents to the US government and that she should leave the country by August 31st.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is hugely disturbing and would be enough to grab the attention of many readers. This is what caught the attention of several colleagues at Hopkins. We haven’t really heard the story from OIS’ perspective and I would definitely want to know more&lt;a href=&#34;#fn4&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to the lack of details in the article, we don’t know exactly which mechanism Dr. Mahoney-Steel was asking Hopkins to help her with. She might have been considering applying under &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.uscis.gov/green-card/employment-based&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;employed-based immigration&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; via &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.uscis.gov/working-united-states/permanent-workers/employment-based-immigration-first-preference-eb-1&#34;&gt;EB-1&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.uscis.gov/working-united-states/permanent-workers/employment-based-immigration-second-preference-eb-2&#34;&gt;EB-2&lt;/a&gt;. For the EB-1 I think that your employer has to help you quite a bit. But not all employers want to do so. Also these processes take a considerable amount of time, not 10 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, maybe Dr. Mahoney-Steel was asking Hopkins to help her pay for her green card &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.uscis.gov/greencard/immediate-relative-us-citizen&#34;&gt;application through family&lt;/a&gt; since she’s married to a US citizen and due to their &lt;em&gt;portrayed&lt;/em&gt; extremely poor communication on her H-1B visa renewal. I haven’t heard of any employer helping their employees with the green card fees in such cases. It’d be great if they did it, but I wouldn’t expect this to happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;the-portrayed-lack-of-attention-by-dr.mahoney-steel&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The &lt;em&gt;portrayed&lt;/em&gt; lack of attention by Dr. Mahoney-Steel&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, we don’t know how everything exactly happened. My issues here could be based on how Dan Rodricks used his notes from interviewing Dr. Mahoney-Steel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the Mexicans I shared the article with are not US citizens&lt;a href=&#34;#fn5&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and thus have different types of visas that allow us to study and/or work in the US. We learn fast, either through personal experience or stories from others, that you have to prioritize any visa paperwork you have to do. That involves lots of planning and attention to detail. For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Knowing when your visa expires.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning the types of visas you can apply to after your current one expires.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fees associated with the different visa applications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Requirements for the visa you want to get: timeline, documents that you have, documents that you need to get, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Communicating with all parties involved.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this information at hand you can make plans. &lt;a href=&#34;http://ois.jhu.edu/&#34;&gt;OIS&lt;/a&gt; is also pretty helpful, in my experience, as they provide seminars where they explain a lot of this information and you can also request to meet with one of their specialists. OIS also sends reminders that prompt you to get moving: get your documents ready and send them on time. Additionally, I have learned myself that if something says that it can take between 60 and 90 days, that I should think that it’ll take 90 days and be happy if it takes less than that. This doesn’t mean that our plans are the best or that they always work out. It just means that we try to be prepared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having said all that, as portrayed, I’m surprised by Dr. Mahoney-Steel because:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;She didn’t contact OIS a few days after sending her documents to follow up on her case. If she had, maybe she would have had more time to convince them to actually send her H-1B visa renewal documents to the US government, ask for help for her green card (EB-1, EB-2?, EB-2 NIW?), ask for her direct employer (Sheridan Libraries) to intervene, etc. Still, OIS should have immediately notified her that they weren’t going to send her H-1B documents to the US government!!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;She has been married to a US citizen for less than two years (but over one)… and didn’t get a green card via an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.uscis.gov/greencard/immediate-relative-us-citizen&#34;&gt;application through family&lt;/a&gt;. To my understanding, that’s one of the cheapest and fastest ways&lt;a href=&#34;#fn6&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref6&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to apply for a green card. If you can get a green card, then you can stop worrying about visas. Isn’t that something we all want? Yes, it’s not free. The I-485&lt;a href=&#34;#fn7&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref7&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; fee &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.uscis.gov/i-485&#34;&gt;is 1,225 USD for someone aged 14 to 78&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn8&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref8&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Say that you are applying via EB2-NIW and hiring some lawyers, then you are looking at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wegreened.com/Legal-Fees&#34;&gt;5,000 USD or more in lawyer fees alone plus another 700 USD for the government&lt;/a&gt;. Given the large advantages that you get from having a green card and her husband’s situation, I would hope that many would have helped Dr. Mahoney-Steel raise 1,225 USD. Luckily for Dr. Mahoney-Steel, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.uscis.gov/family/family-us-citizens/bringing-spouses-live-united-states-permanent-residents&#34;&gt;she can still apply for a green card through family even if she is living outside the US&lt;/a&gt;. I would hope that Johns Hopkins would be willing to hire her back then, or maybe even now and have her work remotely from the UK while the green card application is being processed (if Hopkins has a branch in Europe).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It does seem like Hopkins realized that they made a mistake (as portrayed in the article) because they covered her flight back to England.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m sorry to say this, but it ultimately looks to me that Dr. Mahoney-Steel felt entitled and never expected to face immigration problems. Though again, that’s the current lens I have, that is, Dan Rodricks’ article and the infamous quote from her friends and colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;closing-remarks&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Closing remarks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope that Dan Rodricks and/or the Baltimore Sun edits his article to remove any mentions about Mexicans, which as they stand currently are all negative and ultimately offensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also hope that we get some clarification from Johns Hopkins University Office of International Services. Depending on what happened, they might need to apologize to Dr. Mahoney-Steel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are an immigrant in the US, I encourage you to plan ahead as much as you can anything related to visa paperwork. The current administration will make it as hard as they can to legally immigrate to the US, read for example this article: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.propublica.org/article/authorities-can-now-deny-visa-and-green-card-applications-without-giving-applicants-a-chance-to-fix-errors&#34;&gt;“Authorities Can Now Deny Visa and Green Card Applications Without Giving Applicants a Chance to Fix Errors”&lt;/a&gt;. But you don’t need to make it harder on yourself by lack of planning. Take advantage of all the resources you have at your employer (OIS in this case) and ask your fellow immigrants to share their knowledge with you. If you are thinking about getting a green card, you can start by checking websites &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.visapro.com/green-cards/&#34;&gt;like this one that lists all the possible ways to get one&lt;/a&gt; and by checking the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.uscis.gov/greencard/eligibility-categories&#34;&gt;USCIS website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I’ll write a letter to the Baltimore Sun including a link to this post. But that’s for tomorrow September 20th 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;acknowledgements&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to thank those who I discussed this article with and corrected some of my facts. If you want me to name you let me know and I’ll edit this post. I didn’t because going the other way around (from named to anonymous) is challenging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I saw the article as a photo that was shared by Hopkins colleagues. Dan Rodrick’s Facebook page also shows the article with the original title.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 09/19/2018 at 10 pm ET.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many of us are students, alumni or even staff members at Hopkins and affiliated institutes (like myself).&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn4&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;If they ever can share their story due to privacy restrictions.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn5&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can be a dual citizen.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref5&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn6&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;It will still take months, say about 11 to 13 months from what I’ve heard.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref6&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn7&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The form you submit to get a green card.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref7&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn8&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;You might need to cover about another 400 USD in fees to get the documents that show that you have all the vaccines you need if you go to a place like &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.passporthealthusa.com/locations/md/baltimore/162/&#34;&gt;Passport Health&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref8&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Slack for Academic Departmental Communication</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/06/19/using-slack-for-academic-departmental-communication/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/06/19/using-slack-for-academic-departmental-communication/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a joint blog post between &lt;a href=&#34;http://stephaniehicks.com&#34;&gt;Stephanie Hicks&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/&#34;&gt;Leonardo Collado-Torres&lt;/a&gt;. We want to share with you our experience using Slack and why you should join us. This post is in an interview style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-06-19-using-slack-for-academic-departmental-communication_files/slack-logo.png&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;what-is-slack&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is Slack?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[SH]&lt;/code&gt; Slack is a communication tool for &lt;em&gt;teams&lt;/em&gt;. The main idea is you have individual chat rooms (referred to as &lt;em&gt;channels&lt;/em&gt; that always begin with the # symbol), which are organized by topics. Traditionally, if an email is sent to everyone on your team, each person must decide how tag or organize emails in their account. In contrast, Slack provides the structure and organization for all users on the team. Each user clicks on a specific topic, or channel, and all the messages related to that topic are already there, thereby reducing the organizational burden. In a slack team used by academic department, topics can be anything from announcements of #conferences, #workshops, #jobs, #seminars, #working_groups, #good_reads, #food_alerts, #payroll, and #IT_help. You can write public messages in the individual channels or send private direct messages to anyone on your team. Everything in Slack is searchable (e.g. files, conversations, people). Finally, Slack includes a lot of functionality and integration with other useful tools such as Google Drive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-06-19-using-slack-for-academic-departmental-communication_files/Screen%20Shot%202018-06-19%20at%204.00.33%20PM.png&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[LCT]&lt;/code&gt; Slack is a website that provides access to a group of message channels bundled together in what they call a workspace. These channels can have specific purposes and different sets of members. Slack also provides many integrations with other software that we commonly use, like integration with GitHub, todo lists, Google Calendar, Google Docs, etc. The idea of using Slack is to keep your communications with close colleagues organized and make them more fluid than email. You might use the &lt;em&gt;general&lt;/em&gt; channel for making broad announcements, such as an interesting talk from a guest. Then switch to a private channel with your 4 colleagues for that new secret project you are working on and discuss some ideas that would be useful to explore in more detail. And finally, switch to a one-on-one channel with your advisor and ask if you can meet for a few minutes that later today. Like many websites, Slack is also available as its own desktop and phone applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;how-do-you-use-slack&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How do you use Slack?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[SH]&lt;/code&gt; While I communicate with colleagues everyday on Slack, I think it’s important to distinguish between Slack and email. Both are important, I just use them for different purposes. I view communication on Slack to be for instant, real-time messaging and discussion to increase collaboration. These are usually short messages compassing a single idea. In contrast, I view email to be a slower, more deliberate medium. There is less expectation for immediate response. In both cases, you can always turn them off completely and enjoy some peace too!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-06-19-using-slack-for-academic-departmental-communication_files/Screen%20Shot%202018-06-19%20at%204.04.08%20PM.png&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;versus&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-06-19-using-slack-for-academic-departmental-communication_files/Screen%20Shot%202018-06-19%20at%204.04.18%20PM.png&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[LCT]&lt;/code&gt; I’m part of multiple Slack &lt;em&gt;workplaces&lt;/em&gt; (collections of channels and users) but I mostly use one with my genomics collaborators. There, we have a channel per project, some of which can be silent for weeks/months. But that’s ok, because I can always jump back to them and revise what we were talking about. We have a channel for R questions, one for the team that I’m a part of (Andrew Jaffe’s lab), one for organizing when and where to eat lunch, another one with the recount2 team, a diversity channel, one for our computing cluster JHPCE, among others. I also frequently ask and get asked questions on one-on-one channels with Andrew’s lab members and people elsewhere from our genomics workplace. I love using Twitter for networking in academia and keeping myself updated. So I also tend to share relevant news to specific channels I’m a part of. For the project specific channels I also use the integration with GitHub to keep everything in one place and reduce the chance of git merge issues :P&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;what-do-you-like-about-slack&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What do you like about Slack?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[SH]&lt;/code&gt; I recently transitioned from being a postdoctoral research fellow to an assistant professor. Many people warned me about the increase in the number of emails that I would receive. While that is certainly true, I would attribute Slack to being the biggest mitigator in reducing the number of emails that I have received. It reduces my email burden and increases communication between collaborators and colleagues. When an email sometimes seems too formal, Slack is &lt;em&gt;perfect&lt;/em&gt; for sending out quick messages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[LCT]&lt;/code&gt; It greatly reduces the amount of emails and email chains. Also, I like having the option of more communication with all my colleagues than would be typically allowed via email. Like no one would like an email about some interesting R package tweet or emails about lunch. Also, it was very useful this past year when I advised two students. I could get them involved in different projects, get them observe how we do some things, but also provide them a space to ask me questions during the week outside of our weekly meeting slot. Ultimately, I like to be organized and Slack helps me stay organized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;any-more-tips&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Any more tips?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[SH]&lt;/code&gt; I have found that the more I engage and write messages in channels on a Slack team, the more I get in return. As conversations flow in a given channel on a particular topic, I may or may not have anything useful to contribute. If it’s the former, I try to pass along links, advice, knowledge or whatever is appropriate. If it’s the latter, I still gain knowledge by being able to read other people’s responses and learning how others would have approached or solved a problem. Either way it’s a win-win!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[LCT]&lt;/code&gt; Regardless of what channel you use, it’s important to keep your messages polite. Basically, following a code of conduct similar to &lt;a href=&#34;http://research.libd.org/rstatsclub/#coc&#34;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;. This is not the anonymous internet, here you are interacting with your colleagues and you have to be aware of biases you might have, otherwise you might perpetrate some problems &lt;a href=&#34;https://work.qz.com/1128150/your-companys-slack-is-probably-sexist/&#34;&gt;like sexism&lt;/a&gt;. Remember, you share the responsibility of making sure that your Slack workspace is a welcoming environment where anyone is allowed to ask questions. I also think that it’s very important to keep your boundaries clear between work and home. I highly recommend going to your &lt;em&gt;preferences&lt;/em&gt; and automatically disabling notifications outside work hours as shown below. That’s something you can’t do with Google Chat: yes, I might be available after work hours, but I want to choose whether to respond or not and I don’t want others to expect an immediate answer if they see me online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-06-19-using-slack-for-academic-departmental-communication_files/Screen%20Shot%202018-06-18%20at%209.52.35%20AM.png&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want more, check &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1ji-3hLYPs3yIEu7wqyRdkGanxdON84ypuq8lyL5Yf-I/edit#slide=id.p&#34;&gt;this great presentation&lt;/a&gt; about Slack by Stephanie Hicks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;acknowledgements&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog post was made possible thanks to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=blogdown&#34;&gt;blogdown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Xie_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&#39;&gt;Xie, Hill, and Thomas, 2017&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&#34;&gt;devtools&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Wickham_2018&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&#39;&gt;Wickham, Hester, and Chang, 2018&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;references&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Wickham_2018&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Wickham_2018&#34;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt; H. Wickham, J. Hester and W. Chang. &lt;em&gt;devtools: Tools to Make Developing R Packages Easier&lt;/em&gt;. R package version 1.13.5. 2018. URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Xie_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Xie_2017&#34;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt; Y. Xie, A. P. Hill and A. Thomas. &lt;em&gt;blogdown: Creating Websites with R Markdown&lt;/em&gt;. ISBN 978-0815363729. Boca Raton, Florida: Chapman and Hall/CRC, 2017. URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&#34;&gt;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;reproducibility&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reproducibility&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Session info ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##  setting  value                       
##  version  R version 3.5.0 (2018-04-23)
##  system   x86_64, darwin15.6.0        
##  ui       X11                         
##  language (EN)                        
##  collate  en_US.UTF-8                 
##  tz       America/New_York            
##  date     2018-06-19&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Packages --------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##  package       * version date       source                            
##  backports       1.1.2   2017-12-13 cran (@1.1.2)                     
##  base          * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  bibtex          0.4.2   2017-06-30 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  BiocStyle     * 2.8.2   2018-05-30 Bioconductor                      
##  blogdown        0.6     2018-04-18 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  bookdown        0.7     2018-02-18 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  colorout      * 1.2-0   2018-05-03 Github (jalvesaq/colorout@c42088d)
##  compiler        3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  datasets      * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  devtools      * 1.13.5  2018-02-18 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  digest          0.6.15  2018-01-28 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  evaluate        0.10.1  2017-06-24 cran (@0.10.1)                    
##  graphics      * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  grDevices     * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  htmltools       0.3.6   2017-04-28 cran (@0.3.6)                     
##  httr            1.3.1   2017-08-20 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  jsonlite        1.5     2017-06-01 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  knitcitations * 1.0.8   2017-07-04 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  knitr           1.20    2018-02-20 cran (@1.20)                      
##  lubridate       1.7.4   2018-04-11 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  magrittr        1.5     2014-11-22 cran (@1.5)                       
##  memoise         1.1.0   2017-04-21 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  methods       * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  plyr            1.8.4   2016-06-08 cran (@1.8.4)                     
##  R6              2.2.2   2017-06-17 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  Rcpp            0.12.17 2018-05-18 cran (@0.12.17)                   
##  RefManageR      1.2.0   2018-04-25 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  rmarkdown       1.10    2018-06-11 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  rprojroot       1.3-2   2018-01-03 cran (@1.3-2)                     
##  stats         * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  stringi         1.2.3   2018-06-12 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  stringr         1.3.1   2018-05-10 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  tools           3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  utils         * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  withr           2.1.2   2018-03-15 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  xfun            0.2     2018-06-16 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  xml2            1.2.0   2018-01-24 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  yaml            2.1.19  2018-05-01 CRAN (R 3.5.0)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mindfulness</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/06/11/mindfulness/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/06/11/mindfulness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently participated for the first time in a silent retreat (6 hrs) as part of a &lt;em&gt;Mindfulness-Based Stress Reduction&lt;/em&gt; course. I’ve really been enjoying this course and the experience of learning new ways (for me) to live better and enjoy life more. If you haven’t heard of &lt;em&gt;mindfulness&lt;/em&gt; before (like me a few months ago), &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mindfulness&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; defines it as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Mindfulness is the psychological process of bringing one&amp;#39;s attention to
experiences occurring in the present moment, which can be developed
through the practice of meditation and other training.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In academia and science, but really anywhere, we can encounter many sources of stress (some examples below). We all deal with it in different ways and this MBSR course is just one that I’m liking right now and recommend. If there’s no course near you, check out the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00C4BA3UK&#34;&gt;Full Catastrophe Living&lt;/a&gt; book that my course is based on&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these tweets are threads, so you’ll have to open them to see them: click on the blue bird on the right side of each tweet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I won an NSF grant yesterday, with three weeks to go before applying to tenure. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A thread👇&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Dr. Bryony DuPont (@BryonyDuPont) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/BryonyDuPont/status/1005618536100683777?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 10, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Just another barrier that us scientists in &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/developing?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#developing&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/countries?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#countries&lt;/a&gt; need to find ways to overcome. Not only do we have less funding, but also generating data that for other countries is routine is more expensive. &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/latin?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#latin&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/american?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#american&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/scientists?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#scientists&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/plight?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#plight&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/Hln7N4x4iM&#34;&gt;https://t.co/Hln7N4x4iM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Daniela Robles (@daniela_oaks) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/daniela_oaks/status/1004798860835938305?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 7, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Thanks for sharing this Ted! &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/tladeras?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@tladeras&lt;/a&gt; As with anything, but particularly with mental health, I think it’s important to know you are not alone and that some things we feel have names: impostor syndrome, anxiety, depression, etc. Our minds are very powerful! &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/MentalHealthMatters?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#MentalHealthMatters&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/X1UIAznV8f&#34;&gt;https://t.co/X1UIAznV8f&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; 🇲🇽 Dr. Leonardo Collado-Torres (@fellgernon) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/fellgernon/status/1004478330257707008?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 6, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the exercises on our silent retreat was &lt;em&gt;mindful eating&lt;/em&gt;. That is, eating slowly and focusing on our senses while eating food. This involved smelling the food, seeing all the colors it has, feeling all the different textures, and focusing on its taste. Plus, not talking to anyone. I had bought a lunch before the retreat (so I wouldn’t have to break the silence during it) that I normally don’t find interesting: some fruit and a chicken curry wrap from CVS. But wow, it was amazing that day! I greatly enjoyed how it tasted and all the different sensations I felt. I couldn’t believe it was the same food I had eaten other times before without much excitement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lately I’ve been processing some strong feelings related to feeling unwelcome, homesickness and loneliness. I’m doing many things that I know help me, starting with talking about them with my family. I’ve also been keeping myself busy doing some sports outside, going to events, bars, having friends over, etc. But what motivated me to write this post today is that after lunch I left really bad today. I had to go outside and try to calm myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-06-11-mindfulness_files/2018-06-11_13.25.34.jpg&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought I did, returned to work, and nah, I couldn’t do it today. So I went home, rested in my room in the dark, and I find myself finishing this post about 2 hours later. I’m not sure it’s related to the MSBR course, but I’m wondering if the mindfulness practice is also opening my mind’s ears and eyes to my inner feelings way more than normal&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I don’t think it’s bad. It’s just that it’s way harder to enjoy this process than it was eating a lunch. I’m trying to feel happy because I have feelings and I’m recognizing them. My family is also happy because they view it as a part of maturing and that I’m getting ready for taking another step in my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just some things are taking me way more time than normal. For example, it took me 2 days to process what I wanted to reply to a tweet and how to word it: it turned out well because I think we all heard each other ^^.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Thanks for the link &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/apreshill?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@apreshill&lt;/a&gt;! I agree that the blog post was aweful! You can’t blame X for the fact that X is marginalized. However, I disagree with the notion that Z can’t talk about X (challenging). I’m in favor of inclusion. Otherwise that line of thought leads to xenophobia&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; 🇲🇽 Dr. Leonardo Collado-Torres (@fellgernon) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/fellgernon/status/1006207918813958145?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 11, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also discovered that the silent retreat reminded me of vacations where I turn off my phone/email and spend a few days thinking about what’s next. I used to go to Mexico every 6 months or so during my PhD to recharge. I want to do it again, but I can’t. That lead me to my strong feelings of homesickness I had today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just to close, I’m OK. I appreciate all the support I have and I recommend others to learn about mindfulness. You might be missing out some super tasty lunches and/or an exploration trip towards your inner self.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also want to add that I know some of you might see this post as over-sharing (yes, it might be). One reply is that I think that leaders also have to show their vulnerable sides. This has been debated a lot in academic twitter accounts in the context of showing your failures too, not just your successes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;acknowledgements&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog post was made possible thanks to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=blogdown&#34;&gt;blogdown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Xie_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&#39;&gt;Xie, Hill, and Thomas, 2017&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&#34;&gt;devtools&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Wickham_2018&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&#39;&gt;Wickham, Hester, and Chang, 2018&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;references&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Wickham_2018&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Wickham_2018&#34;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt; H. Wickham, J. Hester and W. Chang. &lt;em&gt;devtools: Tools to Make Developing R Packages Easier&lt;/em&gt;. R package version 1.13.5. 2018. URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Xie_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Xie_2017&#34;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt; Y. Xie, A. P. Hill and A. Thomas. &lt;em&gt;blogdown: Creating Websites with R Markdown&lt;/em&gt;. ISBN 978-0815363729. Boca Raton, Florida: Chapman and Hall/CRC, 2017. URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&#34;&gt;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;reproducibility&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reproducibility&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Session info ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##  setting  value                       
##  version  R version 3.5.0 (2018-04-23)
##  system   x86_64, darwin15.6.0        
##  ui       X11                         
##  language (EN)                        
##  collate  en_US.UTF-8                 
##  tz       America/New_York            
##  date     2018-06-11&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Packages --------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##  package       * version date       source                            
##  backports       1.1.2   2017-12-13 cran (@1.1.2)                     
##  base          * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  bibtex          0.4.2   2017-06-30 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  BiocStyle     * 2.8.1   2018-05-17 Bioconductor                      
##  blogdown        0.6     2018-04-18 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  bookdown        0.7     2018-02-18 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  colorout      * 1.2-0   2018-05-03 Github (jalvesaq/colorout@c42088d)
##  compiler        3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  datasets      * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  devtools      * 1.13.5  2018-02-18 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  digest          0.6.15  2018-01-28 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  evaluate        0.10.1  2017-06-24 cran (@0.10.1)                    
##  graphics      * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  grDevices     * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  htmltools       0.3.6   2017-04-28 cran (@0.3.6)                     
##  httr            1.3.1   2017-08-20 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  jsonlite        1.5     2017-06-01 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  knitcitations * 1.0.8   2017-07-04 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  knitr           1.20    2018-02-20 cran (@1.20)                      
##  lubridate       1.7.4   2018-04-11 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  magrittr        1.5     2014-11-22 cran (@1.5)                       
##  memoise         1.1.0   2017-04-21 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  methods       * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  plyr            1.8.4   2016-06-08 cran (@1.8.4)                     
##  R6              2.2.2   2017-06-17 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  Rcpp            0.12.17 2018-05-18 cran (@0.12.17)                   
##  RefManageR      1.2.0   2018-04-25 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  rmarkdown       1.9     2018-03-01 cran (@1.9)                       
##  rprojroot       1.3-2   2018-01-03 cran (@1.3-2)                     
##  stats         * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  stringi         1.2.2   2018-05-02 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  stringr         1.3.1   2018-05-10 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  tools           3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  utils         * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  withr           2.1.2   2018-03-15 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  xfun            0.1     2018-01-22 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  xml2            1.2.0   2018-01-24 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  yaml            2.1.19  2018-05-01 CRAN (R 3.5.0)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Baltimore friends, I have a paper copy if you want to borrow it for a while.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;It could be a coincidence with other events in my life.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>End of the summer blogger challenge</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2014/10/03/kiva/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2014/10/03/kiva/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;This summer a few of us at &lt;a href=&#34;http://bmorebiostat.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Bmore Biostats&lt;/a&gt; agreed to a summer iron blogger challenge. We either had to blog every week or every two weeks. The penalty of not publishing a post in our chosen timeframe was to donate 5 or 10 USD (respectively) to our charity of choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I liked the idea of the blogging challenge and thought it would help me keep motivated to keep my blog active during the summer. However, I totally failed and only posted twice during the 16 week summer. That is, I have to donate 14 * 5 = 70 USD. I think that most of us blogged a lot less than what we were hoping to and potentially owe a charity some money. But well, there is no real obligation to donate and I don&#39;t expect others to do so. However, I want to do it. Doing so will help me take a iron blogger challenge more seriously next time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;kiva&#34;&gt;Kiva&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a charity of my choice, I ended up choosing &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kiva.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Kiva&lt;/a&gt;. Through them you can loan 25 USD to an individual or group that needs the money to improve their business, home, etc. And in general, you get your money back. Alternatively, you can donate your money from the get go or keep re-loaning it instead of withdrawing it back to your bank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;900&#34; height=&#34;506&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/lSN2WdqXwfc?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is my first time doing something like this, so I am going to ask for the money back and then re-loan it as I see fit. So, because strictly speaking I am not donating it, I decided to increase my entry to 100 USD. That is, 4 Kiva loans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kiva recommends lending to different individuals, Kiva partners, and countries to diversify your risk. Being born in Mexico, I wanted to specifically help people from there. If you &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kiva.org/lend#/?perPage=20&amp;amp;countries%5B%5D=MX&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;restrict the search to Mexico&lt;/a&gt;, currently there are 13 open loans. From them, I chose:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kiva.org/lend/773040&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Aurea&lt;/a&gt; administered by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kiva.org/partners/301&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Eblock International&lt;/a&gt;. She wants to install a floor in her room. It seems like she has used other Kiva loans to slowly build her house.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kiva.org/lend/775645&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Sonia&lt;/a&gt; administered by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kiva.org/partners/294&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Kubo Financiero&lt;/a&gt;. She wants to buy recycling materials for her business.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kiva.org/lend/774187&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Mujeres Mazahuas Group&lt;/a&gt; who are re-stocking their grocery business. The loan is administered by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kiva.org/partners/130&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;VisionFund Mexico&lt;/a&gt; who have gotten loans for over 6 million since 2009. That&#39;s a large chunk of the 16 million that Kiva has sent to Mexico.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kiva.org/lend/774355&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Gabino&lt;/a&gt; administered by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kiva.org/partners/226&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Sistema Biobolsa&lt;/a&gt;. He wants a biodigester which will help him in his agriculture business.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully the loans will be used properly! But like my friend who has experience in micro-banks in Mexico tells me, it is very hard to know that. We&#39;ll see what happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the meantime, here is my receipt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/figs/2014-10-03-kiva/receipt.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/figs/2014-10-03-kiva/receipt.png&#34; alt=&#34;Workflow&#34; style=&#34;width: 631px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;join-kiva&#34;&gt;Join Kiva&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For whatever&#39;s worth, here is my Kiva invitation link: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kiva.org/invitedby/fellgernon&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;kiva.org/invitedby/fellgernon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;want-more&#34;&gt;Want more?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check other &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jhubiostat&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;@jhubiostat&lt;/a&gt; student blogs at &lt;a href=&#34;http://bmorebiostat.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Bmore Biostats&lt;/a&gt; as well as topics on &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/search?q=%23rstats&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;#rstats&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;I am a writer&#34; exercise</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/21/I-am-a-writer-exercise/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/21/I-am-a-writer-exercise/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I do not have a clear memory of when I started to write or in which language it was. My first written words might have been in English since I lived in Boston (USA) three years during my early childhood. By age five I was back in Mexico and that is where I am sure I wrote my first full homeworks. During elementary school, I changed languages once more—this time to French. By middle school, I started to be interested in two new types of languages. One was mathematics which I liked, but which I didn&amp;#8217;t consider till much later. The other was related to computers as I learnt the very basics of HTML—that&amp;#8217;s all I know so far. In college—having reverted back to Spanish and English—and in my current stage in graduate school, I am a writer because I write—I mainly typeset using &lt;code&gt;LaTeX&lt;/code&gt;—my homeworks, code in &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt;, and summarize findings in reports. For the past year, I have been using &lt;a href=&#34;http://fellgernon.tumblr.com/&#34;&gt;Fellgernon Bit&lt;/a&gt; to practice writing and hopefully improve my skills. Furthermore, for me the process of writing helps me clarify my thoughts and organize them before attempting to communicate them. Sometimes it works, others it doesn&amp;#8217;t. Finally, I am a writer because it is crucial in the academic environment to be able to communicate through the printed word. This is tricky because sometimes you want to be very short, direct but not leave anything important out, like when emailing a professor. Other times, you have to be very precise and clear yet tell an interesting story such as when writing a scientific report.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, I consider myself a writer in training and would like to improve. But as with everything, practice is key. That&amp;#8217;s a big part of why I blog and why I&amp;#8217;m enrolled in this course.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>And so begins English Composition I</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/21/And-so-begins-English-Composition-I/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/21/And-so-begins-English-Composition-I/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week started the English Composition I: Achieving Expertise course (&lt;span class=&#34;showtooltip&#34; title=&#34;(2013). Coursera.  https://www.coursera.org/ [Online.  last-accessed: 2013-03-21 03:47:13].   https://www.coursera.org/course/composition.&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/course/composition&#34;&gt;Comer, 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;) that I have been looking forward to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not sure yet how long I will last, but I hope to enjoy it as much as I can. Plus, it should help me with my posting and other writing areas. While I last in the course, I plan to publish my writings in the blog too. So you will hopefully see me be more active here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it is important to cite when writing, I have also figured out how to do so automatically in Rmd files. For that I learnt how to use &lt;strong&gt;knitcitations&lt;/strong&gt; from the GitHub instructions (&lt;span class=&#34;showtooltip&#34; title=&#34;cboettig (2013). knitcitations.   https://github.com/cboettig/knitcitations [Online. last-accessed:  2013-03-21 03:19:44].   https://github.com/cboettig/knitcitations.&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cboettig/knitcitations&#34;&gt;knitcitations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;) and a explanatory post (&lt;span class=&#34;showtooltip&#34; title=&#34;Boettiger C (2013). knitcitations.   http://www.carlboettiger.info/2012/05/30/knitcitations.html  [Online. last-accessed: 2013-03-21 02:15:41].   http://www.carlboettiger.info/2012/05/30/knitcitations.html.&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.carlboettiger.info/2012/05/30/knitcitations.html&#34;&gt;Boettiger, 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;knitcitations&lt;/strong&gt; is great, but it kind of struggles with some pages. That is why I modified my template in &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/lcolladotor/FBit&#34;&gt;FBit&lt;/a&gt; by writing my own citing function for pages where &lt;code&gt;citep&lt;/code&gt; fails. Here is the code:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;## I made my own citing function since citep() doesn&#39;t work like I want to with
## urls that are not really pages themselve like part of a GitHub repo.
mycitep &amp;lt;- function(x, short, year=substr(date(), 21, 24), tooltip=TRUE) {
	tmp &amp;lt;- citep(x)
	res &amp;lt;- gsub(&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;quot;, paste0(&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;quot;, short, &amp;quot;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;quot;), tmp)
	if(tooltip) {
		res &amp;lt;- gsub(&amp;quot;\\?\\?\\?\\?&amp;quot;, year, res)
	}
	res
}

## You already saw an inline working example in the post itself.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Carl Boettiger, (2013) knitcitations. &lt;em&gt;Lab Notebook&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.carlboettiger.info/2012/05/30/knitcitations.html&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.carlboettiger.info/2012/05/30/knitcitations.html&#34;&gt;http://www.carlboettiger.info/2012/05/30/knitcitations.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cboettig, knitcitations. &lt;em&gt;GitHub&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cboettig/knitcitations&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cboettig/knitcitations&#34;&gt;https://github.com/cboettig/knitcitations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Coursera. &lt;em&gt;Coursera&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/course/composition&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/course/composition&#34;&gt;https://www.coursera.org/course/composition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
