<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Misc on L. Collado-Torres</title>
    <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/categories/Misc/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Misc on L. Collado-Torres</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2011-2018 Leonardo Collado Torres under (CC) BY-NC-SA 4.0. All thoughts and opinions here are my own.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://lcolladotor.github.io/categories/Misc/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>End of the summer blogger challenge</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2014/10/03/kiva/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2014/10/03/kiva/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;This summer a few of us at &lt;a href=&#34;http://bmorebiostat.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Bmore Biostats&lt;/a&gt; agreed to a summer iron blogger challenge. We either had to blog every week or every two weeks. The penalty of not publishing a post in our chosen timeframe was to donate 5 or 10 USD (respectively) to our charity of choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I liked the idea of the blogging challenge and thought it would help me keep motivated to keep my blog active during the summer. However, I totally failed and only posted twice during the 16 week summer. That is, I have to donate 14 * 5 = 70 USD. I think that most of us blogged a lot less than what we were hoping to and potentially owe a charity some money. But well, there is no real obligation to donate and I don&#39;t expect others to do so. However, I want to do it. Doing so will help me take a iron blogger challenge more seriously next time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;kiva&#34;&gt;Kiva&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a charity of my choice, I ended up choosing &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kiva.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Kiva&lt;/a&gt;. Through them you can loan 25 USD to an individual or group that needs the money to improve their business, home, etc. And in general, you get your money back. Alternatively, you can donate your money from the get go or keep re-loaning it instead of withdrawing it back to your bank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;900&#34; height=&#34;506&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/lSN2WdqXwfc?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is my first time doing something like this, so I am going to ask for the money back and then re-loan it as I see fit. So, because strictly speaking I am not donating it, I decided to increase my entry to 100 USD. That is, 4 Kiva loans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kiva recommends lending to different individuals, Kiva partners, and countries to diversify your risk. Being born in Mexico, I wanted to specifically help people from there. If you &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kiva.org/lend#/?perPage=20&amp;amp;countries%5B%5D=MX&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;restrict the search to Mexico&lt;/a&gt;, currently there are 13 open loans. From them, I chose:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kiva.org/lend/773040&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Aurea&lt;/a&gt; administered by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kiva.org/partners/301&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Eblock International&lt;/a&gt;. She wants to install a floor in her room. It seems like she has used other Kiva loans to slowly build her house.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kiva.org/lend/775645&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Sonia&lt;/a&gt; administered by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kiva.org/partners/294&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Kubo Financiero&lt;/a&gt;. She wants to buy recycling materials for her business.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kiva.org/lend/774187&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Mujeres Mazahuas Group&lt;/a&gt; who are re-stocking their grocery business. The loan is administered by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kiva.org/partners/130&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;VisionFund Mexico&lt;/a&gt; who have gotten loans for over 6 million since 2009. That&#39;s a large chunk of the 16 million that Kiva has sent to Mexico.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kiva.org/lend/774355&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Gabino&lt;/a&gt; administered by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kiva.org/partners/226&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Sistema Biobolsa&lt;/a&gt;. He wants a biodigester which will help him in his agriculture business.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully the loans will be used properly! But like my friend who has experience in micro-banks in Mexico tells me, it is very hard to know that. We&#39;ll see what happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the meantime, here is my receipt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/figs/2014-10-03-kiva/receipt.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/figs/2014-10-03-kiva/receipt.png&#34; alt=&#34;Workflow&#34; style=&#34;width: 631px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;join-kiva&#34;&gt;Join Kiva&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For whatever&#39;s worth, here is my Kiva invitation link: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kiva.org/invitedby/fellgernon&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;kiva.org/invitedby/fellgernon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;want-more&#34;&gt;Want more?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check other &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jhubiostat&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;@jhubiostat&lt;/a&gt; student blogs at &lt;a href=&#34;http://bmorebiostat.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Bmore Biostats&lt;/a&gt; as well as topics on &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/search?q=%23rstats&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;#rstats&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;I am a writer&#34; exercise</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/21/I-am-a-writer-exercise/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/21/I-am-a-writer-exercise/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I do not have a clear memory of when I started to write or in which language it was. My first written words might have been in English since I lived in Boston (USA) three years during my early childhood. By age five I was back in Mexico and that is where I am sure I wrote my first full homeworks. During elementary school, I changed languages once more—this time to French. By middle school, I started to be interested in two new types of languages. One was mathematics which I liked, but which I didn&amp;#8217;t consider till much later. The other was related to computers as I learnt the very basics of HTML—that&amp;#8217;s all I know so far. In college—having reverted back to Spanish and English—and in my current stage in graduate school, I am a writer because I write—I mainly typeset using &lt;code&gt;LaTeX&lt;/code&gt;—my homeworks, code in &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt;, and summarize findings in reports. For the past year, I have been using &lt;a href=&#34;http://fellgernon.tumblr.com/&#34;&gt;Fellgernon Bit&lt;/a&gt; to practice writing and hopefully improve my skills. Furthermore, for me the process of writing helps me clarify my thoughts and organize them before attempting to communicate them. Sometimes it works, others it doesn&amp;#8217;t. Finally, I am a writer because it is crucial in the academic environment to be able to communicate through the printed word. This is tricky because sometimes you want to be very short, direct but not leave anything important out, like when emailing a professor. Other times, you have to be very precise and clear yet tell an interesting story such as when writing a scientific report.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, I consider myself a writer in training and would like to improve. But as with everything, practice is key. That&amp;#8217;s a big part of why I blog and why I&amp;#8217;m enrolled in this course.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>And so begins English Composition I</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/21/And-so-begins-English-Composition-I/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/21/And-so-begins-English-Composition-I/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week started the English Composition I: Achieving Expertise course (&lt;span class=&#34;showtooltip&#34; title=&#34;(2013). Coursera.  https://www.coursera.org/ [Online.  last-accessed: 2013-03-21 03:47:13].   https://www.coursera.org/course/composition.&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/course/composition&#34;&gt;Comer, 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;) that I have been looking forward to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not sure yet how long I will last, but I hope to enjoy it as much as I can. Plus, it should help me with my posting and other writing areas. While I last in the course, I plan to publish my writings in the blog too. So you will hopefully see me be more active here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it is important to cite when writing, I have also figured out how to do so automatically in Rmd files. For that I learnt how to use &lt;strong&gt;knitcitations&lt;/strong&gt; from the GitHub instructions (&lt;span class=&#34;showtooltip&#34; title=&#34;cboettig (2013). knitcitations.   https://github.com/cboettig/knitcitations [Online. last-accessed:  2013-03-21 03:19:44].   https://github.com/cboettig/knitcitations.&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cboettig/knitcitations&#34;&gt;knitcitations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;) and a explanatory post (&lt;span class=&#34;showtooltip&#34; title=&#34;Boettiger C (2013). knitcitations.   http://www.carlboettiger.info/2012/05/30/knitcitations.html  [Online. last-accessed: 2013-03-21 02:15:41].   http://www.carlboettiger.info/2012/05/30/knitcitations.html.&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.carlboettiger.info/2012/05/30/knitcitations.html&#34;&gt;Boettiger, 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;knitcitations&lt;/strong&gt; is great, but it kind of struggles with some pages. That is why I modified my template in &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/lcolladotor/FBit&#34;&gt;FBit&lt;/a&gt; by writing my own citing function for pages where &lt;code&gt;citep&lt;/code&gt; fails. Here is the code:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;## I made my own citing function since citep() doesn&#39;t work like I want to with
## urls that are not really pages themselve like part of a GitHub repo.
mycitep &amp;lt;- function(x, short, year=substr(date(), 21, 24), tooltip=TRUE) {
	tmp &amp;lt;- citep(x)
	res &amp;lt;- gsub(&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;quot;, paste0(&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;quot;, short, &amp;quot;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;quot;), tmp)
	if(tooltip) {
		res &amp;lt;- gsub(&amp;quot;\\?\\?\\?\\?&amp;quot;, year, res)
	}
	res
}

## You already saw an inline working example in the post itself.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Carl Boettiger, (2013) knitcitations. &lt;em&gt;Lab Notebook&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.carlboettiger.info/2012/05/30/knitcitations.html&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.carlboettiger.info/2012/05/30/knitcitations.html&#34;&gt;http://www.carlboettiger.info/2012/05/30/knitcitations.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cboettig, knitcitations. &lt;em&gt;GitHub&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cboettig/knitcitations&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cboettig/knitcitations&#34;&gt;https://github.com/cboettig/knitcitations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Coursera. &lt;em&gt;Coursera&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/course/composition&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/course/composition&#34;&gt;https://www.coursera.org/course/composition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
