<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Misc on L. Collado-Torres</title>
    <link>/categories/Misc/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Misc on L. Collado-Torres</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2011-2018 Leonardo Collado Torres under (CC) BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/Misc/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>End of the summer blogger challenge</title>
      <link>/2014/10/03/kiva/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/10/03/kiva/</guid>
      <description>This summer a few of us at Bmore Biostats agreed to a summer iron blogger challenge. We either had to blog every week or every two weeks. The penalty of not publishing a post in our chosen timeframe was to donate 5 or 10 USD (respectively) to our charity of choice.
I liked the idea of the blogging challenge and thought it would help me keep motivated to keep my blog active during the summer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;I am a writer&#34; exercise</title>
      <link>/2013/03/21/I-am-a-writer-exercise/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/03/21/I-am-a-writer-exercise/</guid>
      <description>I do not have a clear memory of when I started to write or in which language it was. My first written words might have been in English since I lived in Boston (USA) three years during my early childhood. By age five I was back in Mexico and that is where I am sure I wrote my first full homeworks. During elementary school, I changed languages once more—this time to French.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>And so begins English Composition I</title>
      <link>/2013/03/21/And-so-begins-English-Composition-I/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/03/21/And-so-begins-English-Composition-I/</guid>
      <description>This week started the English Composition I: Achieving Expertise course (Comer, 2013) that I have been looking forward to.
I am not sure yet how long I will last, but I hope to enjoy it as much as I can. Plus, it should help me with my posting and other writing areas. While I last in the course, I plan to publish my writings in the blog too. So you will hopefully see me be more active here.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>