<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>LCG | L. Collado-Torres</title>
    <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/tag/lcg/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://lcolladotor.github.io/tag/lcg/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>LCG</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://lcolladotor.github.io/media/icon_hu2b32c4ab415f12f472f73c7b0301b0d1_19400_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>LCG</title>
      <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/tag/lcg/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>A knot of threads: from CSHL to LCG-UNAM to Aldo Barrientos to diversity scholarship opportunities</title>
      <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/11/06/a-knot-of-threads-from-cshl-to-lcg-unam-to-aldo-barrientos-to-diversity-scholarship-opportunities/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/11/06/a-knot-of-threads-from-cshl-to-lcg-unam-to-aldo-barrientos-to-diversity-scholarship-opportunities/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;I can’t tell you how many times I’ve started to write this post in my mind since May 2018. Today I’m finally typing it on the computer. This will be a rather long post that ties in several threads. I’ll talk about Cold Spring Harbor’s Biology of Genomes conference and its relationship to my undergrad in Mexico. I’ll also introduce you to Aldo Barrientos (1987-2011) who was was my undergrad classmate. Then I’ll tell you about myself and how regardless of your situation, privileged or not, you should ask for help and get to know the people around you. Finally, I want to highlight that many other Mexican researchers are doing great work and would love to be invited to talk about their work. Or simply, the opportunity to compete for scholarships and grants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;cshl-and-lcg-unam&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;CSHL and LCG-UNAM&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This past May I was selected to give a talk at &lt;a href=&#34;http://meetings.cshl.edu/Genome18&#34;&gt;Biology of Genomes 2018&lt;/a&gt; (BOG) at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cshl.edu/&#34;&gt;Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory&lt;/a&gt; (CSHL). This was my first time being there and I had plenty of time to reflect before my talk&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. For me, attending BOG was like a dream come true so I was blown away when I was selected to present at BOG.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first heard about the BOG conference when I was studying my undergrad in Mexico at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/es/about&#34;&gt;LCG-UNAM&lt;/a&gt;. My class has a history with the conference too. Basically, part of the class was meeting to discuss what optional courses to create for our fourth year, and well, some miscommunication happened among us. This created a rift in the group and was one of my motivations for focusing on communication as well as giving back. The former lead to me being elected as class president and the latter lead to me volunteering to teach R courses later on my undergrad&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As BOG18 went underway, some of my fellow junior presenters started their talks by mentioning why CSHL was special to them. Following their cue, I wrote some notes just before my presentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-11-06-a-knot-of-threads-from-cshl-to-lcg-unam-to-aldo-barrientos-to-diversity-scholarship-opportunities_files/2018-11-06%2021.21.51.jpg&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really wanted to give a shoutout to all my LCG-UNAM classmates. I also thought of Aldo Barrientos and how it could have been him at BOG. This got me nervous, but I really wanted to do it. I also wanted this to be short and professional. You can see how it turned out for yourself&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/SRGkibDQgIc&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;aldo-barrientos&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Aldo Barrientos&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s time for me to tell you more about Aldo Barrientos, my LCG-UNAM classmate. I won’t attempt to tell you his whole story since I think that others could write a much more detailed one that myself. I hope they do and if they are made public, I’ll share them from this blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aldo came from a low income family in Mexico: I believe that his father was a construction worker&lt;a href=&#34;#fn4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. He was smart and advanced through school successfully. He took the entry exam for LCG-UNAM like many people did in 2005. Eventually only around 10-15 percent of the applicants were admitted to this undergrad program. The school was free (25 Mexican cents per year), but it involved relocating to a new city. UNAM has some scholarship programs, but they are not enough. Aldo found a way like he always did. For example, he sold candy and juice to his classmates during lunch break. For reasons that I don’t remember, Aldo didn’t complete his undergrad in 2009 but was about to in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember Aldo as a very joyful person who was always smiling and joking with the rest of us. He had the &lt;em&gt;best&lt;/em&gt; dancing skills of anyone at my undergrad. He proved them time and time again, for example winning a dance contest at a party in my house and wearing the Pumas UNAM puma costume in our graduation party and dancing with everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-11-06-a-knot-of-threads-from-cshl-to-lcg-unam-to-aldo-barrientos-to-diversity-scholarship-opportunities_files/goyo.jpg&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://sk.pinterest.com/pin/170714642102216698/&#34;&gt;Image source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His path was cut abruptly in 2011. He was stabbed multiple times while waiting for someone. We all knew about this. It’s still unclear to me how everything happened in the following months. But I remember being told that he tried seeing a doctor before going back to his home. One day in 2011, we all started to learn about how grave his situation had turned. I didn’t know what to do&lt;a href=&#34;#fn5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and I talked to David Romero, director (dean?) of CCG-UNAM back then. He guided me and others and we were trying to coordinate ways to help Aldo, but by the time we got to his home it was too late. I regret that we weren’t able to help Aldo earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still have some emails from 2011 when we were talking about doing something to honour him. We never did as a class, though LCG-UNAM did acknowledge him. Maybe one day we will do an event to remember him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aldo faced more challenges that myself and other classmates. Yet I believe that he would have kept solving them one by one; he would have gotten his undergrad degree and had he chosen to stay in academia, then present his research findings at conferences like BOG.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;privileged-yes-entitled-no&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Privileged yes, entitled no&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thinking about Aldo made reflect also on who has been around in my own path, who has helped me and how grateful I am to them. Undoubtedly I’ve had an easier path than others including Aldo. That is, I’ve been privileged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, even with my privileged position it has been a hard fought battle to get to where I am now. I think that a mistake others do is that they assume that they are entitled to something given their privilege instead of working for that thing. This can apply to visas and the like where you still &lt;a href=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/09/19/problems-with-an-article-from-the-baltimore-sun-covering-dr-mahoney-steel-s-immigration-issues/&#34;&gt;have to apply for them in time&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along my way I have hesitated many times what to do and have sought guidance from others. Also along my way, I’ve tried to get to know others in my surroundings. Now that I look back I realize that many people were at my position or in junior positions have kept working towards their career goals and advanced in them. So, if you can, get to know others and learn from them. They could be the future Full Professors with Tenure, future Senior Software Engineers or other titles you look up to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s an incomplete version of my timeline (&lt;a href=&#34;https://lcolladotor.github.io/misc/timeline.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF version&lt;/a&gt;). I think that it’s pretty hard to list everyone who has helped you along the way. For example, I’m not mentioning my Ph.D. classmates from whom I learned many things. But it will give you a more detailed picture of the amount of people that have helped me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-11-06-a-knot-of-threads-from-cshl-to-lcg-unam-to-aldo-barrientos-to-diversity-scholarship-opportunities_files/timeline.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;invite-lcg-unam-alumni&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Invite LCG-UNAM alumni&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like I said at the beginning of my BOG18 talk, I’m not sure if I’m the first LCG-UNAM alumni to present at BOG but I know for sure that I won’t be the last one. That’s because I’m really proud of my classmates and all the great work they are doing. It’s also easy to go beyond my class to other LCG-UNAM alumni and then even go beyond and extend this to Mexican researchers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taken from my timeline, here are a few that I mentioned there (links are to their Twitter profiles):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mariaGTAC&#34;&gt;Maria Gutierrez-Arcelus&lt;/a&gt;: LCG-UNAM; Ph.D. at University of Geneva Medical School; Postdoc Harvard University&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mgschiavon&#34;&gt;Mariana Gómez-Schiavon&lt;/a&gt;: Ph.D. Duke University; postdoc UCSF&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/sur_hp&#34;&gt;Sur Herrera-Paredes&lt;/a&gt;: Ph.D. University of North Carolina; postdoc Standford&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/malacopa_genome&#34;&gt;Fernando Rabanal Mor&lt;/a&gt;: Ph.D. Gregor Mendel Institute; postdoc MPI for Developmental Biology&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/caralvar88&#34;&gt;Carlos Vargas&lt;/a&gt;: Winter Genomics, MS and Ph.D. Universitat de Valencia&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/RanitaRed&#34;&gt;Mariana Reyes&lt;/a&gt;: MS and Ph.D. Universitat de Valencia&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kazenojigoku&#34;&gt;Atahualpa Castillo&lt;/a&gt;: Ph.D. and postdoc University of Bath&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jimena Mónzon (Ph.D. Univeristy of Bath; Oxford’s Parkinson Disease Centre Career Development Fellow)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/licloona1487&#34;&gt;Alejandra Zayas&lt;/a&gt;: Ph.D. IBT-UNAM&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/AV_GonzalezS&#34;&gt;Adriana Verenisse Gonzalez Sandoval&lt;/a&gt;: Ph.D. University of Bath; postdoc Stanford&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/daniela_oaks&#34;&gt;Daniela Robles&lt;/a&gt;: Ph.D. Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute; Faculty LIIGH-UNAM&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/lbolanos68&#34;&gt;Luis Bolaños&lt;/a&gt;: Ph.D. CCG-UNAM; postdoc Oregon State University&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rodrigo García: MS and Ph.D. Universitat de Valencia&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Renan Escalante-Chong: Ph.D. Harvard postdoc MIT; Immuneering Corporation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gianella Garcia Hughes: Ph.D. UT Southwestern&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/garbanyo&#34;&gt;Adrian Cantú&lt;/a&gt;: LCG-UNAM; MS IBT-UNAM; INMEGEN; Ph.D. San Diego State University&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/yinayiyi&#34;&gt;Ana Georgina (Yina) Cobian&lt;/a&gt;: MS IBT-UNAM, Ph.D. San Diego State University&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/fa7gen&#34;&gt;Fernando Riveros-McKay Aguilera&lt;/a&gt;: Winter Genomics, Ph.D. Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/tatinhawk&#34;&gt;Martín Del Castillo Velasco Herrera&lt;/a&gt;: Winter Genomics, Ph.D. Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/AleMedinaRivera&#34;&gt;Alejandra Medina-Rivera&lt;/a&gt;: LCG-UNAM; Ph.D. CCG-UNAM; postdoc SickKids Toronto; Faculty LIIGH-UNAM&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/areyesq&#34;&gt;Alejandro Reyes&lt;/a&gt;: LCG-UNAM; Ph.D. EMBL; postdoc Harvard&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Víctor Moreno Mayar: LCG-UNAM; Ph.D. and postdoc Natural History Museum of Denmark&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;José Reyes: LCG-UNAM, Ph.D. Harvard&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the full list of LCG-UNAM alumni, check &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/es/titulados&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/es/titulados&lt;/a&gt;. There are 257 listed as of October 25, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone has their own story of breaking barriers and overcoming challenges. All of them would love the opportunity to present their work and to compete for funds to travel to conferences and do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;It is and for example Mexican grants cannot be used for paying memberships so we cannot easily get the discounts.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Alejandra Medina-Rivera (@AleMedinaRivera) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/AleMedinaRivera/status/1052349309818232832?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;October 17, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To close off, here are some inspiring or thought provoking tweets:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&amp;quot;Along with a healthy dose of luck, the key attributes needed to produce a worthy PhD thesis are a readiness to accept failure; resilience; persistence; ...and a willingness to commit to very hard work — together with curiosity and a passion for research.&amp;quot; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/o62DODM3iZ&#34;&gt;https://t.co/o62DODM3iZ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Mariana Gómez-Schiavon (@mgschiavon) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mgschiavon/status/1056571008662949888?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;October 28, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;When you&amp;#39;re early-stage in your career, reading stories of people who have been successful is invaluable. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;My &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/rstats?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#rstats&lt;/a&gt; hero is &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/JennyBryan?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@JennyBryan&lt;/a&gt;, and she&amp;#39;s shared her story in 2 interviews:&lt;br&gt;-&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/rOpenSci?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@rOpenSci&lt;/a&gt; profile by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kellrstats?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@kellrstats&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/bz9Jj4UJqG&#34;&gt;https://t.co/bz9Jj4UJqG&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br&gt;-&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/statschat?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@statschat&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/UFWfgIg2qa&#34;&gt;https://t.co/UFWfgIg2qa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; We are R-Ladies (@WeAreRLadies) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/WeAreRLadies/status/1055124381876260865?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;October 24, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I was told by a PhD thesis committee member that if I returned to Mexico after a postdoc I would &amp;quot;fade into mediocrity&amp;quot;. However, I did return to my home country, started my own lab, and are now well funded to investigate the genetics and genomics of cancer in Mexican patients. &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/9inVPvYkPj&#34;&gt;https://t.co/9inVPvYkPj&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Daniela Robles https://mas.to/@daniela_oaks (@daniela_oaks) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/daniela_oaks/status/1019597807395770368?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 18, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Got a bad news myself today but then I got an AWESOME one from my mom! She got a 9/10 in her chemistry class, her last class to complete her high school!!! I’m so proud of her &amp;amp; how resilient she’s been! My brother &amp;amp; I couldn’t be happier, prouder &amp;amp; dying to hug her! &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/nevergiveup?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#nevergiveup&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; 🇲🇽 Leonardo Collado-Torres (@lcolladotor) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/lcolladotor/status/1001985730904764417?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;May 31, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Mexico, Day of the Dead was just last week (November 2nd) and Aldo’s birthday would have been a few weeks ago on October 27th. It was time to finally write this blog post. I hope that you take something positive from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;acknowledgments&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Acknowledgments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog post was made possible thanks to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://bioconductor.org/packages/3.10/BiocStyle&#34;&gt;BiocStyle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Oles_2020&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://github.com/Bioconductor/BiocStyle&#39;&gt;Oleś, Morgan, and Huber, 2020&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=blogdown&#34;&gt;blogdown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Xie_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&#39;&gt;Xie, Hill, and Thomas, 2017&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&#34;&gt;knitcitations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Boettiger_2019&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&#39;&gt;Boettiger, 2019&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=sessioninfo&#34;&gt;sessioninfo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Csardi_2018&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=sessioninfo&#39;&gt;Csárdi, core, Wickham, Chang, et al., 2018&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;references&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Boettiger_2019&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Boettiger_2019&#34;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt;
C. Boettiger.
&lt;em&gt;knitcitations: Citations for ‘Knitr’ Markdown Files&lt;/em&gt;.
R package version 1.0.10.
2019.
URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Csardi_2018&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Csardi_2018&#34;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt;
G. Csárdi, R. core, H. Wickham, W. Chang, et al.
&lt;em&gt;sessioninfo: R Session Information&lt;/em&gt;.
R package version 1.1.1.
2018.
URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=sessioninfo&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=sessioninfo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Oles_2020&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Oles_2020&#34;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt;
A. Oleś, M. Morgan, and W. Huber.
&lt;em&gt;BiocStyle: Standard styles for vignettes and other Bioconductor documents&lt;/em&gt;.
R package version 2.14.4.
2020.
URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Bioconductor/BiocStyle&#34;&gt;https://github.com/Bioconductor/BiocStyle&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Xie_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Xie_2017&#34;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt;
Y. Xie, A. P. Hill, and A. Thomas.
&lt;em&gt;blogdown: Creating Websites with R Markdown&lt;/em&gt;.
ISBN 978-0815363729.
Boca Raton, Florida: Chapman and Hall/CRC, 2017.
URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&#34;&gt;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;reproducibility&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reproducibility&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code for the dates:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;## R code for making the dates.pdf file
## which I then imported into Adobe Illustrator for making
## the timeline.png
x &amp;lt;- paste0(1987:2018, &amp;#39;-&amp;#39;, c(paste0(&amp;#39;0&amp;#39;, 1:9), 10:12), &amp;#39;-01&amp;#39;)

plot(y = seq_len(length(x)), x = as.Date(x), las = 2, ylab = &amp;#39;&amp;#39;, xlab = &amp;#39;&amp;#39;, xaxt= &amp;#39;n&amp;#39;)
axis(1, at = as.Date(x), labels = months(as.Date(x)))


library(&amp;#39;ggplot2&amp;#39;)
library(&amp;#39;scales&amp;#39;)
df &amp;lt;- data.frame(y = 0, date = as.Date(x))


pdf(&amp;#39;dates.pdf&amp;#39;, height = 40,  useDingbats = FALSE)
ggplot(df, aes(y, date)) + 
  geom_line() + 
  scale_y_date(limits = c(as.Date(&amp;quot;1987-07-01&amp;quot;), as.Date(&amp;quot;2018-05-12&amp;quot;)), 
               breaks = date_breaks(&amp;#39;months&amp;#39;),
               date_labels = &amp;quot;%Y-%m&amp;quot;, expand=c(0,30)) +   theme(axis.text.y=element_text(angle=-180))
dev.off()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## ─ Session info ───────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────
##  setting  value                       
##  version  R version 3.6.2 (2019-12-12)
##  os       macOS Catalina 10.15.2      
##  system   x86_64, darwin15.6.0        
##  ui       X11                         
##  language (EN)                        
##  collate  en_US.UTF-8                 
##  ctype    en_US.UTF-8                 
##  tz       America/New_York            
##  date     2020-02-12                  
## 
## ─ Packages ───────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────
##  package       * version date       lib source                            
##  assertthat      0.2.1   2019-03-21 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  bibtex          0.4.2.2 2020-01-02 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  BiocManager     1.30.10 2019-11-16 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.1)                    
##  BiocStyle     * 2.14.4  2020-01-09 [1] Bioconductor                      
##  blogdown        0.17    2019-11-13 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.1)                    
##  bookdown        0.17    2020-01-11 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  cli             2.0.1   2020-01-08 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  colorout      * 1.2-1   2019-05-07 [1] Github (jalvesaq/colorout@7ea9440)
##  colorspace      1.4-1   2019-03-18 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  crayon          1.3.4   2017-09-16 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  digest          0.6.23  2019-11-23 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  dplyr           0.8.3   2019-07-04 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  evaluate        0.14    2019-05-28 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  fansi           0.4.1   2020-01-08 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  ggplot2       * 3.2.1   2019-08-10 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  glue            1.3.1   2019-03-12 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  gtable          0.3.0   2019-03-25 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  htmltools       0.4.0   2019-10-04 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  httr            1.4.1   2019-08-05 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  jsonlite        1.6     2018-12-07 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  knitcitations * 1.0.10  2019-09-15 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  knitr           1.27    2020-01-16 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  lazyeval        0.2.2   2019-03-15 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  lifecycle       0.1.0   2019-08-01 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  lubridate       1.7.4   2018-04-11 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  magrittr        1.5     2014-11-22 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  munsell         0.5.0   2018-06-12 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  pillar          1.4.3   2019-12-20 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  pkgconfig       2.0.3   2019-09-22 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.1)                    
##  plyr            1.8.5   2019-12-10 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  purrr           0.3.3   2019-10-18 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  R6              2.4.1   2019-11-12 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.1)                    
##  Rcpp            1.0.3   2019-11-08 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  RefManageR      1.2.12  2019-04-03 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  rlang           0.4.3   2020-01-24 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.2)                    
##  rmarkdown       2.1     2020-01-20 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  scales        * 1.1.0   2019-11-18 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.1)                    
##  sessioninfo   * 1.1.1   2018-11-05 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  stringi         1.4.5   2020-01-11 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  stringr         1.4.0   2019-02-10 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  tibble          2.1.3   2019-06-06 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  tidyselect      0.2.5   2018-10-11 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  withr           2.1.2   2018-03-15 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  xfun            0.12    2020-01-13 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  xml2            1.2.2   2019-08-09 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  yaml            2.2.0   2018-07-25 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
## 
## [1] /Library/Frameworks/R.framework/Versions/3.6/Resources/library&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;reactions-to-the-blog-post&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reactions to the blog post&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;My good old friend Leo sharing very interesting experiences of his path through academic life, public university system in &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/Mexico?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#Mexico&lt;/a&gt;, and remembering a very special person who taught us a ton of life lessons. &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/nHAiob30jn&#34;&gt;https://t.co/nHAiob30jn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Luis Bolaños (@lbolanos68) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/lbolanos68/status/1060038817774657536?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;November 7, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I&amp;#39;m reading this with tears in my eyes and joy in my heart. I&amp;#39;m so grateful and proud of my friend Leo. I&amp;#39;m so proud of all my classmates! Love you all! Love you Aldo &amp;lt;3 &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/ifOK9ASPmy&#34;&gt;https://t.co/ifOK9ASPmy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Mariana ReyesPrieto. (@mreyespri) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mreyespri/status/1060116424415436800?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;November 7, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Beautiful and inspiring!! Thanks Leo for writing this, for honoring Aldo and being the voice of many (including myself) who feel lucky and grateful for being a LCG alumni! &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/hDyKKThj8B&#34;&gt;https://t.co/hDyKKThj8B&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; paleogenomics (@paleogenomics) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/paleogenomics/status/1060355174546505729?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;November 8, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mine was the very last one of the conference.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Which then lead to my current career. See more at my &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/lcolladotor/status/1023665229882961922&#34;&gt;keynote&lt;/a&gt; for the “Latin American R/BioConductor Developers Workshop 2018”.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;My scientific talk was about the BrainSeq Phase II project by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.libd.org/&#34;&gt;Lieber Institute for Brain Development&lt;/a&gt;. It’s now available as a bioRxiv pre-print: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2018/09/26/426213&#34;&gt;426213&lt;/a&gt;. It took a while to finish this project, which contributed to my delay in making this blog post.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn4&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previous versions of my post incorrectly said that he was a farmer.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn5&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I believe that others asked me since I was or had been the class representative.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From learning to using to teaching to developing R</title>
      <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/talk/cdsb2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jul 2018 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lcolladotor.github.io/talk/cdsb2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;script async class=&#34;speakerdeck-embed&#34; data-slide=&#34;1&#34; data-id=&#34;711408b758884ca2bf0bb950ce0ba0ed&#34; data-ratio=&#34;1.77777777777778&#34; src=&#34;//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reproducible RNA-seq analysis with recount2 and recount-brain</title>
      <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/talk/lcg2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 May 2018 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lcolladotor.github.io/talk/lcg2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;script async class=&#34;speakerdeck-embed&#34; data-id=&#34;c6fe30adcbac4761a8808deb8d0ebeef&#34; data-ratio=&#34;1.77777777777778&#34; src=&#34;//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Federico Sánchez Rodríguez 1950-2016</title>
      <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2016/04/04/FedericoSanchez/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2016/04/04/FedericoSanchez/</guid>
      <description>&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#39;http://www.imagechef.com/ic/ribbon/&#39;&gt;&lt;img alt = &#39;Federico Sanchez Ribbon&#39; height=&#39;300&#39; src=&#39;http://lcolladotor.github.io/figs/2016-04-04-FedericoSanchez/Fede-Ribbon.jpg&#39; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.unam.mx/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UNAM&lt;/a&gt; community at large mourns the passing of Federico Sánchez Rodríguez. He got his bachelor&amp;rsquo;s degree from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.quimica.unam.mx/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;School of Chemistry - UNAM&lt;/a&gt;, masters and PhD degrees from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biomedicas.unam.mx/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Biomedicas - UNAM&lt;/a&gt;, postdoc from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucsf.edu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UCSF&lt;/a&gt;, was a member of CIFN-UNAM now called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ccg.unam.mx/en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CCG-UNAM&lt;/a&gt; (it&amp;rsquo;s his affiliation in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jbc.org/content/258/20/12618.full.pdf&amp;#43;html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; 1983 paper), and worked most of his career at &lt;a href=&#34;http://ibt.unam.mx/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;IBT-UNAM&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#39;http://www.ibt.unam.mx/server/PRG.base?tipo:doc,dir:PRG.curriculum,par:federico&#39;&gt;&lt;img alt = &#39;Federico Sanchez homepage&#39; height=&#39;227&#39; src=&#39;http://www.ibt.unam.mx/img/fot/federico.gif&#39; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m sure that he made many friends, trained many students at all levels, and had a highly productive academic career as evidenced on his &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ibt.unam.mx/server/PRG.base?tipo:doc,dir:PRG.curriculum,par:federico&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;homepage&lt;/a&gt; where he lists many papers, patents, etc. A &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/?term=S%C3%A1nchez%20F%5BAuthor%5D&amp;amp;cauthor=true&amp;amp;cauthor_uid=26911872&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PubMed author search&lt;/a&gt; includes his papers but be careful to not confuse him with other authors that shared his name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll remember Federico fondly for the time we shared at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/es/about&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;LCG-UNAM&lt;/a&gt;. He was a great teacher and motivated me to ask as many questions as I could think of. My background in biology was weaker than my classmates, and I loved to ask questions of the sort: if X biolgical process is possible, could Y happen in the cell? He let my imagination run wild. Federico was very supportive of an elective class a few of us organized in our 4th year. You could always tell that he fed off the energy of enthusiastic students. He was always there if you needed some advice. At the end of my time at LCG-UNAM, he enjoyed how I argued against other members of the LCG academic committee. He always supported me in my non-traditional choices. Federico knew many things about plants, but also about the best food, the best drinks, and was always eager to share his knowledge with you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one of my last interactions with him at &lt;em&gt;FedeFest&lt;/em&gt; in August 2014, I asked him a question in the style that I used to during class. I asked him how would he evaluate results from single-cell sequencing and verify that the results were indeed biogical and not technical. A month later, I sent him &lt;a href=&#34;http://genomebiology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13059-014-0452-9&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this paper&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fede, I will always remember you fondly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Best,
Leonardo&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LCG-UNAM 2005-2009&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>LCG-UNAM 11 years ago</title>
      <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2016/03/10/LCGUNAM/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2016/03/10/LCGUNAM/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This has been a busy week. I just flew in last night from &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/enar2016&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;#ENAR2016&lt;/a&gt; and I&amp;rsquo;m getting ready for a postdoc interview tomorrow, which means that I&amp;rsquo;m also flying today. On the flight back from &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/enar2016&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;#ENAR2016&lt;/a&gt; I started reading a book my friend &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/StrictlyStat&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;John Muschelli&lt;/a&gt; bought for me. It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;strong&gt;The Happiness Advantage&lt;/strong&gt; by Shawn Anchor and so far I&amp;rsquo;m loving it. There are several things that it talks about that I&amp;rsquo;ve done in the past, but maybe not in the past year. Anyhow, I&amp;rsquo;ll probably talk about it in a separate blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#39;http://www.amazon.com/Happiness-Advantage-Principles-Performance-Paperback/dp/B00BR9RW4U/ref=sr_1_2?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1457631904&amp;sr=8-2&amp;keywords=the+happiness+advantage&#39;&gt;&lt;img alt = &#39;Happiness Advantage&#39; height=&#39;346&#39; src=&#39;http://ecx.images-amazon.com/images/I/41g4uexkAfL._SY344_BO1,204,203,200_.jpg&#39; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But coincidentally, a friend of mine from undergrad just shared with me the following YouTube video. Watching it made me very happy! We definitely had a blast during undergrad. The person that talks about Boston is &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frederick_Bieber&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Frederick Bieber&lt;/a&gt; (he&amp;rsquo;s kinda hard to google due to his last name) who at the time worked with 5 of my classmates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;853&#34; height=&#34;480&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/joIyVyIbRuk&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My undergrad class from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/es/about&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;LCG-UNAM&lt;/a&gt; (link is in English) was the 3rd one (yup, still guinea pigs) and the only one to start off with 40 students. Some left to study other degrees, most of us continue to work in academia getting our master&amp;rsquo;s, PhDs, postdocs done; others have chosen different career paths, and sadly one of us already passed away. But I bet we can all say that 2005-2009 were good and &lt;em&gt;happy&lt;/em&gt; years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;want-more&#34;&gt;Want more?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check other &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jhubiostat&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;@jhubiostat&lt;/a&gt; student blogs at &lt;a href=&#34;http://bmorebiostat.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Bmore Biostats&lt;/a&gt; as well as topics on &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/search?q=%23rstats&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;#rstats&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fast differential expression analysis annotation-agnostic across groups with biological replicates</title>
      <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/talk/lcg2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lcolladotor.github.io/talk/lcg2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;script async class=&#34;speakerdeck-embed&#34; data-id=&#34;86e4159fb96e409a8842f73ab4c7d820&#34; data-ratio=&#34;1.33333333333333&#34; src=&#34;//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Keeping in touch (ENAR2014?) and philosophical questions regarding México&#39;s future in genomics</title>
      <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/06/12/keeping-in-touch-enar2014-and-philosophical/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/06/12/keeping-in-touch-enar2014-and-philosophical/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The following text is an email I sent to several of my friends from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/about&#34;&gt;LCG undergraduate program &lt;/a&gt;I studied. There I talk about keeping in touch, I invite them to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.enar.org/meetings.cfm&#34;&gt;ENAR 2014&lt;/a&gt;, and also talk about some philosophical questions regarding our future. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m posting it here because I don&amp;#8217;t mind sharing these thoughts and because I don&amp;#8217;t have the current email addresses of many former LCG students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Enjoy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hola a todos,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Les escribo por el gusto de mantener el contacto, por razones académicas, y también por un rollo filosófico / a futuro.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacto&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Como ya les dije, me da mucho gusto escribirles. Cuando lo hago sé que generalmente resulta en mails largos, así que intentando ser corto, siento que hoy termina el ciclo de personas que conocí en la LCG. Digo, hoy se gradua la 7ma generación y realmente no conozco las nuevas. Fueron años muy buenos los que viví con todos allá en Cuerna y ojalá podamos mantener cierto vínculo a través de los años. Sé que cuesta. Por ejemplo, no tengo los correos de algunos (o no los encontré vía google), otros los intenté adivinar vía &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/titulados&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/titulados&#34;&gt;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/titulados&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; y la regla de 8 caracteres, y solo pocos lo siguen teniendo en su página de Facebook (por rollos de seguridad). También soy bastante malo para escribir regularmente (ya sea vía email o mis blogs: &lt;a href=&#34;http://fellgernon.tumblr.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;académico&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;más personal&lt;/span&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Este año en especial he disfrutado (y seguiré disfrutando) mucho de ver a algunos aunque sea un par de horas =)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;También me gusta mucho cuando me piden ayuda sobre algo, aunque sea lento en contestar :P&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ENAR 2014&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;De lo académico, les quiero avisar que en 2014 van a organizar acá en Baltimore el congreso ENAR (Eastern North American Regional) en marzo del 2014. Es un congreso de bioestadística con una buena parte enfocada a la genómica. Y bueno, muchas cosas hechas en R. Mi jefe está organizando un par de las sesiones así que si tienen sugerencias de quienes invitar avísenme. Ustedes mismos ^_&lt;em&gt;^ &lt;/em&gt;(hay un buen número de pláticas por alumnos de posgrado &amp;amp; postdocs), sus jefes, etc. En fin, tal vez les interese el congreso.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;De 2014 no hay mucha info aún &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.enar.org/meetings.cfm&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.enar.org/meetings.cfm&#34;&gt;http://www.enar.org/meetings.cfm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, pero allí pueden ver lo que pasó en otros años.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rollos filosóficos&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;El rollo filosófico / a futuro tiene que ver con:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class=&#34;ol1&#34;&gt;&lt;li class=&#34;li1&#34;&gt;¿Qué condiciones piden para trabajar en México?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&#34;li1&#34;&gt;¿Cómo crear un vínculo más fuerte entre egresados LCG?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&#34;li1&#34;&gt;¿A qué dedicarse? ¿Academia? ¿Industria? ¿Otra cosa?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Del punto (1) lo he platicado con algunos pero creo que es un tema interesante y muy variado. Hay aspectos que tal vez están fuera de nuestro alcance como la seguridad, y hay otros como el ambiente de trabajo y de la ciencia. El rollo de plazas y los esfuerzos de algunos por crear espacios: CCG tiene algunas ahorita, Palacios &amp;amp; Dávila están haciendo un plan grande para repatriar ex-LCGs, el INMEGEN &amp;amp; el CINVESTAV han estado creciendo, o la idea de hacer un plan nosotros. Ojo, a penas me enteré que para tener plaza de investigador en la UNAM te piden tener un postdoc de 2 años: el chiste es que tengas publicaciones &amp;amp; hayas demostrado que la puedes hacer en la ciencia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;¿Sacrificas potencial académico trabajando en México? Dicho de otra forma, ¿cómo te afecta: el rollo del idioma, el de competir en condiciones que parecen ser más difíciles, o el de tener menos colaboradores cerca para crecer con su crítica &amp;amp; datos de última tecnología? O irse fuera de México (no hay por que ser mártir) y sentirse a gusto con esa decisión. Siempre hay formas de colaborar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Del punto (2) yo opino que puede ser a través de comentar artículos con gente ex-LCG involucrada (algo así &lt;a href=&#34;http://fellgernon.tumblr.com/post/45152484977/commenting-scientific-papers#.UbjBemTF1d8&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;describí aquí&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;), o tal vez vía &lt;a href=&#34;http://masciencia.org/&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;Más Ciencia por México&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (no los logré convencer en esto de comentar artículos). Digo, también ayudaría que &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/titulados&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/titulados&#34;&gt;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/titulados&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; tenga ligas a las páginas actuales de cada quien.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Del (3), en mi opinión cubre también todo el rollo de si queremos vivir con &amp;#8220;soft-money&amp;#8221; a través del ciclo de donativos (el pay-line es 10% en EUA ahorita por lo de sequester), de la libertad académica (¿es una realidad o una forma de cautivarnos?), y también depende del tipo de industria. Otra forma de ver este punto es ¿cual es el nivel de estrés con el que estamos dispuestos a vivir? ¿A qué aspiramos? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;En fin, dan ganas de organizar alguna reunión de ex-LCGs!! Mientras, a seguir con estudios &amp;amp; disfrutar la chamba (investigación o lo que estén haciendo).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Si me preguntan que busco con este correo, es simple:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;ul1&#34;&gt;&lt;li class=&#34;li1&#34;&gt;Mantener el contacto&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&#34;li1&#34;&gt;Invitarlos a ENAR 2014&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&#34;li1&#34;&gt;Promover discusión en estos temas filosóficos / a futuro&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saludos,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leo&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PD Perdón, terminó siendo un mail largo :P&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Commenting scientific papers</title>
      <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/11/Commenting-scientific-papers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/11/Commenting-scientific-papers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been thinking about commenting papers in blog posts. I did a &lt;a href=&#34;http://fellgernon.tumblr.com/tagged/Paper%20comments#.UT534NHF0W8&#34;&gt;few some long time ago&lt;/a&gt;, but now I&amp;#8217;m thinking of doing this activity more systematically. There are several reasons why I&amp;#8217;m thinking of doing this, say for 1 paper a week. It has the obvious advantage of forcing me to read a paper in depth per week. At the same time, I want to learn more from others. See what I like in other papers and maybe avoid some mistakes. There are two main lines of papers that I would be posting about. Anything that is somewhat close to my research (genomics, RNA-seq, biostatistics, bioconductor, visualization) and anything done by my undergrad peers from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/&#34;&gt;LCG-UNAM&lt;/a&gt;. I don&amp;#8217;t think that there is a compilation of papers from LCG students despite many of us doing research all over the globe —Mexico, US, Canada, Denmark, France, England, Germany, Switzerland, Austria, Australia to name a few countries. Maybe compiling a list of papers with contributions from LCG students is a task for &lt;a href=&#34;http://masciencia.org/&#34;&gt;Más Ciencia por México&lt;/a&gt; which seeks to promote science in Mexico. But I would be happy to learn what others are doing and in a way keep in touch academically. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another reason in favor is that blogging helps me practice my English. And writing helps me organize my ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, the question remains, if you systematically comment papers, what would you comment on?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that I should state my opinion of the paper in different areas. Kind of like doing a review. First, try to summarize the paper. Next, was the scientific objective clear? They did answer the main question? Then, given the nature of my Ph.D. program, &lt;span&gt;I think that I should try to comment on any statistics used in the papers. This certainly includes the plots and reproducibility. If they included tools (software), I could take a quick look at it. Then, I can end with stating the main things I liked. Maybe I could come up with some scoring mechanism to rate the paper.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;You can think of other aspects to talk about of a paper. For example, in what way did it help it&amp;#8217;s field? But, I don&amp;#8217;t think that I can answer this for many papers outside my research area. It would all be speculation. I guess that I could use Google Scholar to see who cited the paper and maybe comment on it&amp;#8217;s impact that way. For the LCG papers, I could point out how the LCG students contributed. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;Or maybe I could take the more educational route. But that&amp;#8217;s very time consuming as I can see from &lt;a href=&#34;http://cienciaexplicada.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;La Ciencia explicada&lt;/a&gt;&#39;s highly detailed posts.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;Anyhow, if I have something clear in mind is how I would implement it. I&amp;#8217;m thinking of making a GitHub repository and writing my comments using Rmd and knitr. Then posting them here using Markdown. It should be easy to then have a template post and fill in the gaps after reading the paper.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;The risk of using a template is that the comments will start to look boring. That&amp;#8217;s why I might add a more free section, or change things up a bit.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;If you have any ideas, let me know!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to R and Biostatistics (2012 version)</title>
      <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/talk/introbiostats2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Nov 2012 16:29:18 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lcolladotor.github.io/talk/introbiostats2012/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/11/12/introduction-to-r-and-biostatistics-2012-version/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Blog post describing this talk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to R and Biostatistics (2012 version): presentation</title>
      <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/11/12/Introduction-to-R-and-Biostatistics-2012-version/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/11/12/Introduction-to-R-and-Biostatistics-2012-version/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;To follow my &lt;a href=&#34;http://fellgernon.tumblr.com/post/34677935591/introducing-r-and-biostatistics-to-first-year-lcg#.UKFlW-Oe918&#34;&gt;Introducing R and Biostatistics to first year LCG students (2012 version)&lt;/a&gt; post,  you can now find the presentation online from my site either in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu/~lcollado/lcg/introR2012/intro_R_Biostat_LCG_2012_slides.html&#34;&gt;presentation format&lt;/a&gt;, in a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu/~lcollado/lcg/introR2012/intro_R_Biostat_LCG_2012.html&#34;&gt;single webpage format&lt;/a&gt;, or the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu/~lcollado/lcg/introR2012/intro_R_Biostat_LCG_2012.Rmd&#34;&gt;raw Rmd file&lt;/a&gt;. To prove the point that publishing to &lt;a href=&#34;http://rpubs.com/&#34;&gt;RPubs&lt;/a&gt; is super easy, you can also find the &lt;a href=&#34;http://rpubs.com/lcollado/2618&#34;&gt;single webpage format over there&lt;/a&gt;. I also like how you can comment and share in RPubs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the challenges of giving a presentation to first year students is finding the balance between introducing them to cool things you are doing in your work and actually giving a talk that they can follow. I thought about this and ended dropping anything related to my work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My presentation was split pretty much in two parts. First, I wanted to promote some philosophical discussion about what is statistics. Second, I gave a brief overview of what you can do with R. Or more exactly, what they should be able to learn to do even if they become &lt;em&gt;wet &lt;/em&gt;biologists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While planning this presentation, I knew that I wanted to give the new students a flavor of the three different currents in statistics. I aimed to improve &lt;a href=&#34;http://fellgernon.tumblr.com/post/13739343319/introducing-biostatistics-to-first-year-lcg-students#.UKFl6uOe918&#34;&gt;my 2011 explanations&lt;/a&gt; now that I&amp;#8217;m taking the Foundations of Statistical Inference course. I&amp;#8217;m happy with the result and I think this is greatly due to Royall&amp;#8217;s diagnostic test example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another key point that I wanted to emphasize was that RStudio is the way to go if you are new to R. It is very straightforward to use, plus it is nicely interegrated with &lt;a href=&#34;http://yihui.name/knitr/&#34;&gt;knitr&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to use R Markdown (Rmd) for the first time, after seeing how easy &lt;a href=&#34;http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/&#34;&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt; really is compared to using LaTeX and Beamer. However, when it got to doing the presentation I have to say that I was a bit dissapointed by how some things just break when using the R Markdown to Markdown to HTML presentation pipeline —using &lt;a href=&#34;http://johnmacfarlane.net/pandoc/&#34;&gt;pandoc&lt;/a&gt; for the last step. For example, the math breaks when using mathml or mathjax at times (like after adding an iframe for a youtube video), so I had to use webtex which doesn&amp;#8217;t look as nice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in the commands, I used the &amp;#8220;Knit HTML&amp;#8221; button in R Studio [equivalent to running from R: &lt;em&gt;library(knitr); knit(&amp;#8220;filename.Rmd&amp;#8221;)&lt;/em&gt;] and then ran the following command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;pandoc -s -S &amp;#8212;webtex -i -t dzslides intro_R_Biostat_LCG_2012.md -o intro_R_Biostat_LCG_2012_slides.html &amp;amp; open intro_R_Biostat_LCG_2012_slides.html&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was originally aiming to have a single Rmd file to produce an HTML presentation and a Beamer presentation. However, controlling the pictures in the Beamer output proved to be challenging. While I had a work around, the final problem was the math part. By the time I realized this it was too late —I just dropped the Beamer presentation. Googling, even the author of knitr acknowledges that the best input for PDF output is still LaTeX.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, I&amp;#8217;m happy that I got the HTML presentation done using R Markdown and briefly introduced it to the first year students. The basics of knitr are very easy to learn and I&amp;#8217;m hoping that it got some of them curious enough to try it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next thing in line: prepare 5 questions for the students.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing R and Biostatistics to first year LCG students (2012 version)</title>
      <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/10/30/introducing-r-and-biostatistics-to-first-year-lcg/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/10/30/introducing-r-and-biostatistics-to-first-year-lcg/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On Friday November 9th I&amp;#8217;ll be giving a talk to the first year students from the Undergraduate Program on Genomic Sciences (LCG in Spanish) during their &amp;#8220;Seminar 1: Introduction to Bioinformatics&amp;#8221; course. It&amp;#8217;s just like I did a year ago as I documented in my post &lt;a href=&#34;http://fellgernon.tumblr.com/post/13739343319/introducing-biostatistics-to-first-year-lcg-students#.UJBq6Wl25FQ&#34;&gt;Introducing Biostatistics to first year LCG students&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, this time I&amp;#8217;ll change things a bit. I&amp;#8217;m allowed to require the students to read 2-3 papers before my talk to introduce them to my field. I&amp;#8217;ll do so, but in a more peculiar way by requiring them to listen in to a few videos I selected. So, without further ado here are the three required &amp;#8220;papers&amp;#8221;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is &amp;#8220;&lt;strong&gt;paper 1&lt;/strong&gt;&#34; (~30 minutes). The goal is to introduce you to the basic workings of R and also to great sources of R videos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, learn to install R (watch it in full screen).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder=&#34;0&#34; height=&#34;305&#34; src=&#34;http://www.screenr.com/embed/kzT8&#34; width=&#34;500&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or you can also watch any of the two following videos:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder=&#34;0&#34; height=&#34;281&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/Icawuhf0Yqo&#34; width=&#34;500&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder=&#34;0&#34; height=&#34;281&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/mfGFv-iB724&#34; width=&#34;500&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next learn about RStudio and why it&amp;#8217;s a great place to start (watch it on hd and fullscreen).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder=&#34;0&#34; height=&#34;281&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/JbTMvQ-SbvQ&#34; width=&#34;500&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you are ready to learn how to create a variable in R. Use RStudio instead of the R GUI to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder=&#34;0&#34; height=&#34;305&#34; src=&#34;http://www.screenr.com/embed/qyT8&#34; width=&#34;500&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, learn the super basics about the basic R plot system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder=&#34;0&#34; height=&#34;305&#34; src=&#34;http://www.screenr.com/embed/XeS8&#34; width=&#34;500&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you are ready to learn about how to use the combine function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder=&#34;0&#34; height=&#34;305&#34; src=&#34;http://www.screenr.com/embed/jyT8&#34; width=&#34;500&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, learn about data.frame type of objects&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder=&#34;0&#34; height=&#34;305&#34; src=&#34;http://www.screenr.com/embed/fCs8&#34; width=&#34;500&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and how to add new variables to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder=&#34;0&#34; height=&#34;305&#34; src=&#34;http://www.screenr.com/embed/ge28&#34; width=&#34;500&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next up is learning how to find help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder=&#34;0&#34; height=&#34;305&#34; src=&#34;http://www.screenr.com/embed/Pps8&#34; width=&#34;500&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost there. Now check how to change your current working directory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder=&#34;0&#34; height=&#34;281&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/8xT3hmJQskU&#34; width=&#34;500&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, learn how to install and load a package in R.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder=&#34;0&#34; height=&#34;396&#34; src=&#34;http://www.screenr.com/embed/Fps8&#34; width=&#34;500&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are more curious regarding the origins of R check the next video (not part of &amp;#8220;paper 1&amp;#8221;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder=&#34;0&#34; height=&#34;281&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/kzxHxFHW6hs&#34; width=&#34;500&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, &amp;#8220;&lt;strong&gt;paper 2&lt;/strong&gt;&#34; (~39 minutes). The goal here is to get a feeling of how you can use R to create plots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First start with this demonstration of the basic R plotting tools (called &amp;#8220;base graphics&amp;#8221;). It does in enough level of detail of how the basic plotting system works and how you can customize the colors, layout, etc. For the purpose of getting used to the tool, I recommend that you follow this video using RStudio. Also, you&amp;#8217;ll want to watch it in 720p.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder=&#34;0&#34; height=&#34;281&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/4KLfzsj-qkE&#34; width=&#34;500&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now check the demo for plotting with the &lt;em&gt;lattice&lt;/em&gt; package. This is more advanced, but it should also be more illustrative of the power you have with R. Plus it shows how we can expand the functionality of R by using packages contributed to the community and freely available for us to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder=&#34;0&#34; height=&#34;281&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/6VP5JBq1g7g&#34; width=&#34;500&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, &amp;#8220;&lt;strong&gt;paper 3&lt;/strong&gt;&#34; (~28 minutes). This is the first lecture from a course by Brian Caffo in which he goes over the definition and overall motivation behind Biostatistics. It should be much more fun to watch than reading a review paper in the area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder=&#34;0&#34; height=&#34;281&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/jkUqDVtpKs4&#34; width=&#34;500&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, for those motivated to learn more, I recommend some of my own posts summarizing  information that can be useful to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://fellgernon.tumblr.com/post/32688589475/jhsph-biostat-through-coursera#.UJBzBml25FQ&#34;&gt;JHSPH-Biostat through Coursera&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://fellgernon.tumblr.com/post/33114381084/an-online-bioinformatics-curriculum#.UJBy92l25FQ&#34;&gt;An Online Bioinformatics Curriculum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://fellgernon.tumblr.com/post/30077689805/setting-up-your-computer-for#.UJBzO2l25FQ&#34;&gt;Setting up your computer for bioinformatics/biostatistics and a compedium of resources&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://fellgernon.tumblr.com/post/30970426274/i-consider-myself-a-fan-of-using-version-control#.UJBzKml25FQ&#34;&gt;Motivation behind using a version control system&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://fellgernon.tumblr.com/post/32198487580/introducing-git-while-making-your-academic-webpage#.UJBzIGl25FQ&#34;&gt;Introducing Git while making your academic webpage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://fellgernon.tumblr.com/post/33162495473/why-arent-all-of-our-graphs-interactive#.UJBy8ml25FQ&#34;&gt;Why aren’t all of our graphs interactive?&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://fellgernon.tumblr.com/post/33908652237/visualizing-colors#.UJBy6Gl25FQ&#34;&gt;Visualizing colors()&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://fellgernon.tumblr.com/post/16763819010/p-values-and-statistics-phylosophy#.UJB0j2l25FQ&#34;&gt;P-values and Statistics phylosophy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://fellgernon.tumblr.com/post/13830203652/the-new-visualization-package-for-genome-data-in#.UJB04Wl25FQ&#34;&gt;The new visualization package for genome data in Bioconductor: ggbio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.twotorials.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.twotorials.com/&#34;&gt;http://www.twotorials.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kaiseredu.org/tutorials-and-presentations/bios/anthony-damico.aspx&#34;&gt;Anthony Damico&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/user/rdpeng?feature=results_main&#34;&gt;Youtube videos&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu/~rpeng/&#34;&gt;Roger Peng&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/user/bcaffo?feature=results_main&#34;&gt;Youtube videos&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bcaffo.com/&#34;&gt;Brian Caffo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing Biostatistics to first year LCG students</title>
      <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2011/12/04/Introducing-Biostatistics-to-first-year-LCG-students/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Dec 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2011/12/04/Introducing-Biostatistics-to-first-year-LCG-students/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Around two weeks ago I gave a talk via skype to the first year students from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/about&#34;&gt;Undergraduate Program on Genomic Sciences&lt;/a&gt; (LCG in Spanish) from the National Autonomous University of Mexico (UNAM in Spanish). The talk was under the context of the &lt;em&gt;Introduction to Bioinformatics Seminar Series&lt;/em&gt; whose goal is to familiarize the new students with the bioinformatics world. It used to be a course heavy on exploring database websites, some basic theory, and lots of new concepts and algorithm names. Like, what is BLAST? This year, the course involved several talks from former students (like myself) on their experience and current job (most of us are in graduate school).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my case, I was invited to talk about Biostatistics and R as I was one of the first LCG students to learn and teach R to other students (including PhD students ^^): &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/~lcollado/R/&#34;&gt;12 hour intro to R and Bioconductor&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/~lcollado/E/&#34;&gt;R in an intro to statistics course&lt;/a&gt;, a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/~lcollado/B/&#34;&gt;full course on Bioconductor&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a lot of fun preparing my talk as I tried to portray the three main currents in Biostatistics in a way that would be understandable, basic concepts such as a P-value, some basic R code (the students knew the super basics only), and doing so in a way that I would also pass how I see things. A key part for any bioinformatician, as I see it, is to have a good basic toolset. That&amp;#8217;s why I tried to pass on many tips to these young students. Also, I do like to go back to the philosophy of science and whether we need hypothesis nowadays or just models based on the data. I definitely had to cover the topic of communication as I strongly believe that any researcher has to be able to communicate with a biostastician if they want their help in analyzing their data. Also, a biostatistician is not a stastistician, meaning that they have to understand the underlying biological question. I tried emphasizing this point with the students and I attempted to motivate them to take a basic stastistics and probability course (2 preferably). After all, biostatistics is key nowadays in science since biology has gone high-throughput.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Giving the talk through skype was definitely a new experience for me. The best is to be in the classroom as you miss a lot of the interaction with the students. For instance, I didn&amp;#8217;t always know who as asking the question and frequently I had to ask them to repeat it louder. Plus, I chose to share my desktop with them instead of having them watch at my face all the time. I guess it wasn&amp;#8217;t easy for them to just watch a screen with a background voice for 2 hours :P But well, I hoped they liked it as much as I liked preparing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in the talk, I uploaded the &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/open?id=0B-mxZfuflcuONmY1MGI3ZjEtN2JjNy00MDNiLTk0NmMtYjdiNDAwNTZmNGNj&#34;&gt;PDF file&lt;/a&gt;, the associated &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/open?id=0B-mxZfuflcuOZTkxMDUzY2ItNmMzYi00ZDcyLTgyMTQtMWI5YzJmN2IzZjUw&#34;&gt;R file&lt;/a&gt; and the master &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/open?id=0B-mxZfuflcuOYTY3OTQ4NjUtZTFkOC00MGQ5LThiMzgtNDQ2ZjY2NmZlY2Zi&#34;&gt;Rnw file&lt;/a&gt; to Google Docs. The Rnw file can be useful if you are learning how to write Beamer presentations using Sweave and LaTeX.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I was asked to prepare two short questions so that the teachers can evaluate the students. As a bonus for any of them reading my blog ^^ (I did portray blogs as an excellent way to update yourself) here they are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Argue why you need to learn (at least basic) Biostatistics and why it&amp;#8217;s useful nowadays to analyze biological data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Based on the data from your recent experiment, you construct a 95% confidence interval (frequentist approach) for the mean of your variable of interest. What is the probability that the true mean of the distribution is contained in the confidence interval.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bonus: list 5 basic R plotting functions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Answers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;You need to learn the basics (at least) of Biostatistics in order to be able to communicate with your biostatistician collaborator, and to analyze your own data specially by performing exploratory data analyses (EDA). Also, biological experiments nowadays generate a lot of data as biology has gone high-throughput. Biostatistics is specially useful in order to analyze all this data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;0 or 1 and you cannot know which is the case for your specific dataset.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I mentioned: plot, hist, boxplot, qqplot, qqnorm, lines, points, abline, legend&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to R and Biostatistics</title>
      <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/talk/introbiostats2011/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Nov 2011 16:29:18 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lcolladotor.github.io/talk/introbiostats2011/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/2011/12/04/introducing-biostatistics-to-first-year-lcg-students/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Blog post describing this talk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script async class=&#34;speakerdeck-embed&#34; data-id=&#34;464d2cce929a4682adddccf1d4560ce8&#34; data-ratio=&#34;1.33333333333333&#34; src=&#34;//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interspecies interactions that result in Bacillus subtilis forming biofilms are mediated mainly by members of its own genus</title>
      <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/publication/2011-11_bsubtilis/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2011 17:13:40 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lcolladotor.github.io/publication/2011-11_bsubtilis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- More detail can easily be written here using *Markdown* and $\rm \LaTeX$ math code. --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to using Bioconductor for High Throughput Sequencing Analysis</title>
      <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/talk/nnb2010/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Aug 2010 16:01:25 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lcolladotor.github.io/talk/nnb2010/</guid>
      <description>&lt;script async class=&#34;speakerdeck-embed&#34; data-id=&#34;40788fe5d7554eb593cc6d1d938d7781&#34; data-ratio=&#34;1.33333333333333&#34; src=&#34;//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bacteriófagos: analizando su diversidad</title>
      <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/talk/fagos2008/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lcolladotor.github.io/talk/fagos2008/</guid>
      <description>&lt;script async class=&#34;speakerdeck-embed&#34; data-id=&#34;732afb05a0e24a33948734b33816d4f8&#34; data-ratio=&#34;1.33333333333333&#34; src=&#34;//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
