<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rstats on L. Collado-Torres</title>
    <link>/tags/rstats/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Rstats on L. Collado-Torres</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2011-2018 Leonardo Collado Torres under (CC) BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/rstats/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>blogdown archetype (template)</title>
      <link>/2018/03/08/blogdown-archetype-template/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/03/08/blogdown-archetype-template/</guid>
      <description>In a recent blog post I wrote about having a template for blogdown posts. I wanted to know if it was possible to do this and make my life (and others hopefully) easier for writing new blog posts that are ready to go with the features I frequently re-use.
In my case, I like using BiocStyle (Oleś, Morgan, and Huber, 2017) for functions such as CRANpkg(), Biocpkg() and Githubpkg(). I also like using knitcitations (Boettiger, 2017) for citing with citep() packages or papers; I use citation() and bib_metadata() to get the necessary information, respectively.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>blogdown Insert Image addin</title>
      <link>/2018/03/07/blogdown-insert-image-addin/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/03/07/blogdown-insert-image-addin/</guid>
      <description>Have you ever tried inserting an image into a blogdown post? Maybe you have, or maybe you tried and gave up. Lets first review the hard way before getting to the solution I contributed.
The hard way The process involves copying the target image to the static directory that corresponds to the blogdown post. Lets say that your post is called 2018-03-07-my-new-post.Rmd and lives at content/post/, so it’s full path is content/post/2018-03-07-my-new-post.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R markdown blog template</title>
      <link>/2018/02/17/r-markdown-blog-template/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/02/17/r-markdown-blog-template/</guid>
      <description>This blog post is mostly for myself but maybe it’s useful to others. It contains my current R markdown blog template. I initially posted this as a question at StackOverflow. Then I read how much a burden we put in Yihui Xie and decided that my current setup (copy-pasting) works just fine. In any case using blogdown with the RStudio IDE is much simpler than what I used to do in the past with jekyll or with even my prior setup with blogdown.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>JHSPH-Biostat through Coursera</title>
      <link>/2012/10/01/JHSPH-Biostat-through-Coursera/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/10/01/JHSPH-Biostat-through-Coursera/</guid>
      <description>Have you heard of online education? If you are in the US or Mexico I&amp;#8217;m sure that you have seen some ads about online universities. Well, that&amp;#8217;s not the type of education I&amp;#8217;m talking about. I&amp;#8217;m talking about free high-quality education. For some years, the top option has been the Open Courseware (OCW) organized under the Open Courseware Consortium (OCWC). Back in 2009 I was pushed my undergrad (LCG-UNAM) to design and teach OCW-compliant courses.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>