<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Science on L. Collado-Torres</title>
    <link>/categories/Science/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Science on L. Collado-Torres</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2011-2018 Leonardo Collado Torres under (CC) BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/Science/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Keeping in touch (ENAR2014?) and philosophical questions regarding México&#39;s future in genomics</title>
      <link>/2013/06/12/keeping-in-touch-enar2014-and-philosophical/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/06/12/keeping-in-touch-enar2014-and-philosophical/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The following text is an email I sent to several of my friends from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/about&#34;&gt;LCG undergraduate program &lt;/a&gt;I studied. There I talk about keeping in touch, I invite them to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.enar.org/meetings.cfm&#34;&gt;ENAR 2014&lt;/a&gt;, and also talk about some philosophical questions regarding our future. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m posting it here because I don&amp;#8217;t mind sharing these thoughts and because I don&amp;#8217;t have the current email addresses of many former LCG students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Enjoy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Have you been &#39;relative stupid&#39;?</title>
      <link>/2013/03/31/Have-you-been-relative-stupid/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/03/31/Have-you-been-relative-stupid/</guid>
      <description>I enjoyed reading &amp;#8220;The importance of stupidity in scientific research&#34; by Martin A. Schwartz which I learned existed through @hmason and @simplystats. I found the point of how it&amp;#8217;s normal to feel stupid in academia and specially in Ph.D. programs to be illuminating. But Schwartz clarifies that there are other kinds of stupid:
 we don&amp;#8217;t do a good enough job of teaching our students how to be productively stupid – that is, if we don&amp;#8217;t feel stupid it means we&amp;#8217;re not really trying.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Great commentary on sequestration&#39;s impact on research! National media should talk about this and YOU should read it!!!</title>
      <link>/2013/03/28/great-commentary-on-sequestrations-impact-on-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/03/28/great-commentary-on-sequestrations-impact-on-research/</guid>
      <description>Today Jeffrey T. Leek and Steven L. Salzberg published a paper commentary in Genome Biology today titled “Sequestration: inadvertently killing biomedical research to score political points” (Leek &amp;amp; Salzberg, 2013) which I think is a must read for anyone. Seriously!
I do not mean anyone involved in research, or all scientists. I mean, this commentary should be in the national media. Why?
Well, let me approach the technical side first. You might think that anything that appears in a scientific journal—despite any efforts to make it accessible to the general public—will rely on words whose meaning is mostly only understood by scientists.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Got acknowledged in a paper ^^</title>
      <link>/2012/10/31/got-acknowledged-in-a-paper-s4/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/10/31/got-acknowledged-in-a-paper-s4/</guid>
      <description>During the weekend while I was talking with a friend and former colleague, I realized that my name was mentioned in the acknowledgements section of a paper :) I haven&amp;#8217;t been much in touch with what&amp;#8217;s been happening back home, so this was a nice surprise.
The paper is: Genetic changes during a laboratory adaptive evolution process that allowed fast growth in glucose to an Escherichia coli strain lacking the major glucose transport system by Aguilar et al.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Online Bioinformatics Curriculum</title>
      <link>/2012/10/07/an-online-bioinformatics-curriculum/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/10/07/an-online-bioinformatics-curriculum/</guid>
      <description>Last week I talked about online courses in my JHSPH-Biostat through Coursera post. Now I&amp;#8217;m back to comment on An Online Bioinformatics Curriculum by David B. Searls. Sur Herrera pointed out this paper to me, and I have to say that if you are considering learning bioinformatics online it will be very useful to you. David Searls first goes through a history recap of online (free) courses. Notably, in the last year Coursera and other startups offered their first courses.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning about social networks through an interactive presentation</title>
      <link>/2012/09/28/learning-about-social-networks-through-an-interactive/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/09/28/learning-about-social-networks-through-an-interactive/</guid>
      <description>During this week&amp;#8217;s journal club meeting Hilary Parker (homepage, blog) led the session on &amp;#8220;Identifying influential and susceptible members of social networks&amp;#8221;. Were there some speakers or why did she &amp;#8220;lead the session&amp;#8221;? By this I mean that Hilary tried a very different (and interesting) format this time. Instead of giving a talk, not a formal one like at seminars, she prepared a short presentation (publicly available here) that begins showing a 20 minute video.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is science cool?</title>
      <link>/2012/08/27/Is-science-cool/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/08/27/Is-science-cool/</guid>
      <description>Adam Ruben shares his answer to whether science is cool or not. Since &amp;#8220;cool&amp;#8221; depends on the current trends, this question is set on the recent landing of Curiosity. It&amp;#8217;s the landrover that recently landed on Mars and has been sending some pictures back. Anyhow, check his answer here. I liked this part:
 If the Mars landing draws students to science, it won’t be because they witnessed science doing something cool.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pollination video</title>
      <link>/2012/03/01/great-video-thank-you-aunt-for-sending-it-to-me/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/03/01/great-video-thank-you-aunt-for-sending-it-to-me/</guid>
      <description>Great video! Thank you aunt for sending it to me =)</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>