<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rstats on L. Collado-Torres</title>
    <link>/categories/rstats/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Rstats on L. Collado-Torres</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2011-2018 Leonardo Collado Torres under (CC) BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/rstats/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>R markdown blog template</title>
      <link>/2018/02/17/r-markdown-blog-template/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/02/17/r-markdown-blog-template/</guid>
      <description>This blog post is mostly for myself but maybe it’s useful to others. It contains my current R markdown blog template. I initially posted this as a question at StackOverflow. Then I read how much a burden we put in Yihui Xie and decided that my current setup (copy-pasting) works just fine. In any case using blogdown with the RStudio IDE is much simpler than what I used to do in the past with jekyll or with even my prior setup with blogdown.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Updating R</title>
      <link>/2017/05/04/Updating-R/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/05/04/Updating-R/</guid>
      <description>As you might know by now, the latest R version was recently released (R 3.4.0). That means that you are highly encouraged to update your R installation. There are several ways to do this some of which are documented in these other blog posts: Tal Galili, 2013, Kris Eberwein, 2015. You would think that it&#39;s just a matter of downloading the latest R installer for your OS, installing it, and continuing your analysis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to ask for help for Bioconductor packages</title>
      <link>/2017/03/06/How-to-ask-for-help-for-Bioconductor-packages/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/06/How-to-ask-for-help-for-Bioconductor-packages/</guid>
      <description>tl;dr Please post your question at the Bioconductor support website https://support.bioconductor.org/ and check the posting guide http://www.bioconductor.org/help/support/posting-guide/. It&#39;s important that you provide reproducible code and information about your R session.
 Recently I have been getting more questions about several packages I maintain. It&#39;s great to see more interest from users, but at the same time most questions lack the information I need to help the users. I have also gotten most of the questions via email, which is why I am writing this post.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Easily explore a table with shinycsv</title>
      <link>/2017/01/20/Easily-explore-a-table-with-shinycsv/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/01/20/Easily-explore-a-table-with-shinycsv/</guid>
      <description>Have you ever had to explore a table with data? I believe the answer is yes for most people that work at a computer or even just use it for communicating with their friends and family. Tables of data pop up everywhere, for example in personal finance. Websites like Mint.com allow you to download your transactions in a CSV file called transactions.csv. CSV is one of the many formats for storing tables and most likely when you try to open the transactions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finding possible class schedules</title>
      <link>/2016/08/02/materias/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/08/02/materias/</guid>
      <description>Over the weekend my brother wanted to figure out his class schedule for the next semester. He is a veterinary medicine and zootechnology student at UNAM. For this upcoming semester there is a set of classes he has to take and each has 8 or so instructor options. The website where he finds the class times lists about 8 pre-constructed class schedules. So he normally finds one he likes quite a bit, and then manually starts checking if he can change X instructor for Y for a given class.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Are you doing parallel computations in R? Then use BiocParallel</title>
      <link>/2016/03/07/BiocParallel/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/03/07/BiocParallel/</guid>
      <description>It&#39;s the morning of the first day of oral conferences at #ENAR2016. I feel like I have a spidey sense since I woke up 3 min after an email from Jeff Leek; just a funny coincidence. Anyhow, I promised Valerie Obenchain at #Bioc2014 that I would write a post about one of my favorite Bioconductor packages: BiocParallel (Morgan, Obenchain, Lang, and Thompson, 2016). By now it&#39;s on the top 5% of downloaded Bioconductor packages, so many people know about it or are unaware that their favorite package uses it behind the scenes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching a short topic to beginner R users</title>
      <link>/2015/07/07/rmarkdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/07/07/rmarkdown/</guid>
      <description>A couple weeks ago I was given the opportunity to teach a 1 hr 30 min slot of an introduction to R course. In the past, I&#39;ve taught lectures for similar courses, and I ended up asking myself what would be the best short topic to teach and how to teach it.
Best short topic There are two ways to answer the first question, one boring and one more interesting.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Use hidden advanced arguments for user-friendly functions</title>
      <link>/2014/12/11/dots/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/12/11/dots/</guid>
      <description>As a user Imagine that you are starting to learn how to use a specific R package, lets call it foo. You will look at the vignette (if there is one), use help(package = foo), or look at the reference manual (for example, devtools&#39; ref man). Eventually, you will open the help page for the function(s) you are interested in using.
?function_I_want_to_use  In many packages, there is a main use case that is addressed by the package.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An xpd-tion into R plot margins</title>
      <link>/2014/11/21/add-logo-in-R/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/11/21/add-logo-in-R/</guid>
      <description>This is a guest post by Prasad Patil that answers the question: how to put a shape in the margin of an R plot?
The help page for R&#39;s par() function is a somewhat impenetrable list of abbreviations that allow you to manipulate anything and everything in the plotting device. You may have used this function in the past to create an array of plots (using mfrow or mfcol) or to set margins (mar or mai).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Where do I start using Bioconductor?</title>
      <link>/2014/10/16/startBioC/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/10/16/startBioC/</guid>
      <description>I was recently asked where do I get started with Bioconductor? and thought this would be a good short post.
What is BioC? Briefly, Bioconductor (Gentleman, Carey, Bates, and others, 2004) is an open source project that hosts a wide range of tools for analyzing biological data with R (R Core Team, 2014). These analysis tools are bundled into packages which are designed to answer specific questions or to provide key infrastructure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Concerns that can deter potential orders for developing Shiny apps</title>
      <link>/2014/06/10/shiny-orders/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/06/10/shiny-orders/</guid>
      <description>A few weeks ago I was invited to a meeting where a group was interested in exploring options for replacing their contract with a propriety software. They invited me because they saw some resemblances between a Shiny application I made and the features they need. It is a relatively small project and it seemed feasible to implement, but well, some details could have been tricky to code. During the meeting I explained what Shiny is, showcased some of the Shiny apps I&#39;ve made, and proposed some options including a simple site password.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simple mortgage calculator</title>
      <link>/2014/04/22/mortgage-calculator-flexible-payments/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/04/22/mortgage-calculator-flexible-payments/</guid>
      <description>Have you ever thought of borrowing some money? A common case is when you have to borrow money for buying a house, which is called a mortgage. Wikipedia (&#39;Mortgage loan&#39; entry) goes into much more detail about the definition than what I&#39;ll cover.
One of the aspects you have to evaluate when considering a loan such as a mortgage is how much interest you will be charged and how long the loan will be.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>rMaps Mexico map</title>
      <link>/2014/02/26/excited-by-willingness-to-help-get-things-done/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/02/26/excited-by-willingness-to-help-get-things-done/</guid>
      <description>It&#39;s exciting when great people help each other get things done This is a simple networking story, which might not be surprising to some but I was happily surprised by it. This is how the story goes:
Two weeks ago rMaps (Vaidyanathan, 2014) was released. After making a blog post about it I thought about using it to make a map of the homicide rate in Mexico over the recent years.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Automatically coloring your R output in the terminal using colorout</title>
      <link>/2014/02/17/colorout/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/02/17/colorout/</guid>
      <description>Thanks to Alyssa Frazee I just learned about the colorout package (Aquino, 2013). It modifies R so that the output is in different colors, making it much more pleasant to use R in the terminal.
Do note that colorout is not available from CRAN, but you can easily install by following the instructions on the colorout site (Official site) reproduced below:
download.file(&amp;quot;http://www.lepem.ufc.br/jaa/colorout_1.0-2.tar.gz&amp;quot;, destfile = &amp;quot;colorout_1.0-2.tar.gz&amp;quot;) install.packages(&amp;quot;colorout_1.0-2.tar.gz&amp;quot;, type = &amp;quot;source&amp;quot;, repos = NULL)  The next step is to then load colorout automatically when I start R.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>rMaps released</title>
      <link>/2014/02/10/rMaps-released/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/02/10/rMaps-released/</guid>
      <description>Ramnath Vaidyanathan just released his new R interactive package, rMaps (Vaidyanathan, 2014). The packages relies on the development version of his widely known rCharts package (Vaidyanathan, 2013) as well as javascript libraries that specialize in maps. If you don&#39;t know Ramnath, he is one of the most active R developers out there!! You can see that from his GitHub profile.
The package is very new and still under development, but I bet that Ramnath released it to get us users excited and maybe find some helpful hands to document it and further develop it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to upload files to Dropbox and Google Docs from R</title>
      <link>/2014/02/05/DropboxAndGoogleDocsFromR/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/02/05/DropboxAndGoogleDocsFromR/</guid>
      <description>Have you ever wondered whether you can upload files from R to Dropbox and/or Google Docs? I recently asked myself this question while making my most recent Shiny app (more later).
The answer is yes, you can upload files from R to these cloud services!
Dropbox As far as I know, the best R package for uploading files to Dropbox is rDrop (Ram &amp;amp; Temple Lang, 2012). The whole setup is very well explained in it&#39;s GitHub repository (Karthik).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating awesome reports for multiple audiences using knitrBootstrap</title>
      <link>/2013/12/10/knitrBootstrap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/12/10/knitrBootstrap/</guid>
      <description>As a biostatistics student, I use R very frequently when analyzing data. At the same time, I interact with other researchers, some who know how to use R (R crowd) and some who don&#39;t (yet!): no-R crowd. This means that I have to be able to communicate my results to two crowds. It is important that I can quickly provide the code in case that the R savvy want to look at it: maybe they find a bug and report it ^^.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trying to reduce the memory overhead when using mclapply</title>
      <link>/2013/11/14/Reducing-memory-overhead-when-using-mclapply/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/11/14/Reducing-memory-overhead-when-using-mclapply/</guid>
      <description>I am currently trying to understand how to reduce the memory used by mclapply. This function is rather complicated and others have explained the differences versus parLapply (A_Skelton73, 2013; lockedoff, 2012 ) and also made it clear that in mclapply each job does not know if the others are running out of memory and thus cannot trigger gc (Urbanek, 2012).
While I still struggle to understand all the details of mclapply, I can successfully use it to reduce computation time at the expense of a very high memory load.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating your Jekyll-Bootstrap powered blog for R blogging</title>
      <link>/2013/11/09/new-Fellgernon-Bit-setup-in-Github/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/11/09/new-Fellgernon-Bit-setup-in-Github/</guid>
      <description>As you might have noticed, I recently decided to move Fellgernon Bit from Tumblr to GitHub. There are a couple of reasons why I made this change.
 I wanted a more professional-looking blog.  There are not many R blogs on Tumblr, and well, long text posts are not really meant for Tumblr.  Better code highlighting.  I had enabled R code highlighting using the highlighting instructions from Jeffrey Horner (Horner, Part I).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ggplot Tutorial</title>
      <link>/2013/06/21/ggplot-Tutorial/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/06/21/ggplot-Tutorial/</guid>
      <description>ggplot TutorialI liked the following ggplot2 tutorial which is featured in Gabriela de Queiroz&amp;#8217;s blog called unbiasedestimator. The tutorial looks very neatly presented and I&amp;#8217;m sure that it will be very helpful to anyone just getting started with ggplot2 before they jump into ggplot2: Elegant Graphics for Data Analysis by Hadley Wickham or R Graphics Cookbook by Winston Chang.
The tutorial is very nicely formatted with code in bold highlighting parts that change something in the plot.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>userR2013 data analysis contest: data exploration</title>
      <link>/2013/06/12/userR2013-data-analysis-contest-data-exploration/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/06/12/userR2013-data-analysis-contest-data-exploration/</guid>
      <description>Description The useR2013 conference is organizing a data analysis contest, check the rules here.
They have a package called useR2013DAC with two data sets: one from La Liga and the other one from the Formula 1. Once you download and install the package (available here), you can quickly explore the data using the following R commands:
Data exploration ## Load the package library(useR2013DAC) ## Explore laliga data data(laliga) head(laliga)  ## Season Week HomeTeam AwayTeam ## 1 2008/09 1 Athletic Club Bilbao Union Deportiva Almeria ## 2 2008/09 1 Atlético Madrid Málaga CF ## 3 2008/09 1 Betis Sevilla Real Club Recreativo Huelva ## 4 2008/09 1 CA Osasuna Villarreal CF ## 5 2008/09 1 CD Numancia FC Barcelona ## 6 2008/09 1 Deportivo de La Coruña Real Madrid CF ## HomeGoals AwayGoals ## 1 1 3 ## 2 4 0 ## 3 0 1 ## 4 1 1 ## 5 1 0 ## 6 2 1  summary(laliga)  ## Season Week HomeTeam AwayTeam ## Length:1900 Min.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reading an R file from GitHub</title>
      <link>/2013/05/09/Reading-an-R-file-from-GitHub/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/05/09/Reading-an-R-file-from-GitHub/</guid>
      <description>Lets say that I want to read in this R file from GitHub into R.
The first thing you have to do is locate the raw file. You can do so by clicking on the Raw button in GitHub. In this case it&amp;#8217;s https://raw.github.com/lcolladotor/ballgownR-devel/master/ballgownR/R/infoGene.R
One would think that using source() would work, but it doesn&amp;#8217;t as shown below:
source(&amp;quot;https://raw.github.com/lcolladotor/ballgownR-devel/master/ballgownR/R/infoGene.R&amp;quot;)  ## Warning: unsupported URL scheme  ## Error: cannot open the connection  However, thanks again to Hadley Wickham you can do so by using the devtools (Wickham &amp;amp; Chang, 2013 ) package.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using plyr and doMC for quick and easy apply-family functions</title>
      <link>/2013/04/26/using-plyr-and-domc-for-quick-and-easy-apply-family/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/04/26/using-plyr-and-domc-for-quick-and-easy-apply-family/</guid>
      <description>A few weeks back I dedicated a short amount of time to actually read what plyr (Wickham, 2011) is about and I was surprised. The whole idea behind plyr is very simple: expand the apply() family to do things easy. plyr has many functions whose name ends with ply which is short of apply. Then, the functions are identified by two letters before ply which are abbreviations for the input (first letter) and output (second one).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predicting who will win a NFL match at half time</title>
      <link>/2013/03/23/Predicting-who-will-win-a-NFL-match-at-half-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/03/23/Predicting-who-will-win-a-NFL-match-at-half-time/</guid>
      <description>It was great to have a little break, Spring break, although the weather didn&amp;#8217;t feel like spring at all! During the early part of the break I worked on my final project for Jeff Leek&amp;#8217;s data analysis class, which we call 140.753 here. Continuing my previous posts on the topic, this time I&amp;#8217;ll share the results of my final project.
At the beginning of the course, we had to submit a project plan (more like a proposal) and in mine I announced my interest to look into some sports data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>And so begins English Composition I</title>
      <link>/2013/03/21/And-so-begins-English-Composition-I/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/03/21/And-so-begins-English-Composition-I/</guid>
      <description>This week started the English Composition I: Achieving Expertise course (Comer, 2013) that I have been looking forward to.
I am not sure yet how long I will last, but I hope to enjoy it as much as I can. Plus, it should help me with my posting and other writing areas. While I last in the course, I plan to publish my writings in the blog too. So you will hopefully see me be more active here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analyzing SimplyStatistics visits info</title>
      <link>/2013/03/09/Analyzing-SimplyStatistics-visits-info/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/03/09/Analyzing-SimplyStatistics-visits-info/</guid>
      <description>Recently we had to analyze the data of the number of visits per day to SimplyStatistics.org. There were two goals:
Estimate the fraction of visitors retained after a spike in the number of visitors Identify (if any) any factors that influence the fraction estimated in 1. For me it was a fun project in part because I like SimplyStatistics but also because I think that finding the answers to the questions would be interesting and help understand the readers of that blog.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sharing my work for &#34;Advanced Methods III&#34;</title>
      <link>/2013/02/13/Sharing-my-work-for-Advanced-Methods-III/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/02/13/Sharing-my-work-for-Advanced-Methods-III/</guid>
      <description>This semester I&amp;#8217;m taking the live version of the Data Analysis class by Jeff Leek. His more popular version of the course is available through Coursera. One of the things that Jeff promotes is reproducibility and sharing code. I share that tendency and thus created a Git repository for my homework and code for the class: lcollado753. I&amp;#8217;m hosting it with GitHub to try it out since I started with Mercurial via Bitbucket.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to R and Biostatistics (2012 version): presentation</title>
      <link>/2012/11/12/Introduction-to-R-and-Biostatistics-2012-version/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/11/12/Introduction-to-R-and-Biostatistics-2012-version/</guid>
      <description>To follow my Introducing R and Biostatistics to first year LCG students (2012 version) post, you can now find the presentation online from my site either in presentation format, in a single webpage format, or the raw Rmd file. To prove the point that publishing to RPubs is super easy, you can also find the single webpage format over there. I also like how you can comment and share in RPubs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing R and Biostatistics to first year LCG students (2012 version)</title>
      <link>/2012/10/30/introducing-r-and-biostatistics-to-first-year-lcg/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/10/30/introducing-r-and-biostatistics-to-first-year-lcg/</guid>
      <description>On Friday November 9th I&amp;#8217;ll be giving a talk to the first year students from the Undergraduate Program on Genomic Sciences (LCG in Spanish) during their &amp;#8220;Seminar 1: Introduction to Bioinformatics&amp;#8221; course. It&amp;#8217;s just like I did a year ago as I documented in my post Introducing Biostatistics to first year LCG students.
Well, this time I&amp;#8217;ll change things a bit. I&amp;#8217;m allowed to require the students to read 2-3 papers before my talk to introduce them to my field.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visualizing colors()</title>
      <link>/2012/10/19/Visualizing-colors/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/10/19/Visualizing-colors/</guid>
      <description>The other day I learnt about the existance of the colors() vector in R which specifies all the character-based colors like &amp;#8220;light blue&amp;#8221;, &amp;#8220;black&amp;#8221;, etc. So I made a simple plot to visualize them all. Here&amp;#8217;s the code:
mat &amp;lt;- matrix(1:length(colors()), ncol = 9, byrow= TRUE) df &amp;lt;- data.frame(col = colors(), x = as.integer(cut(1:length(colors()), 9)), y = rep(1:73, 9), stringsAsFactors=FALSE) plot(y ~ jitter(x), data = df, col = df$col, pch=16, main = &amp;quot;Visualizing colors() split in 9 groups&amp;quot;, xlab = &amp;quot;Group&amp;quot;, ylab = &amp;quot;Element of the group (min = 1, max = 73)&amp;quot;, sub = &amp;quot;x = 3, y = 1 means that it&#39;s the 2 * 73 + 1 = 147th color&amp;quot;)  And the plot:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting up your computer for bioinformatics/biostatistics and a compedium of resources</title>
      <link>/2012/08/23/setting-up-your-computer-for/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/08/23/setting-up-your-computer-for/</guid>
      <description>Jumping on the train set by Hilary Parker &amp;#8220;The Setup (Part 1)&#34; and Alyssa Frazee &amp;#8220;my software/hardware setup&amp;#8221;, I&amp;#8217;m going to share my setup and hopefully add something new. They both did a great job already, so make sure you read their posts!
I have some experience with all three main OS: Windows, Linux and Mac. That being said, I know some of the basic stuff for each but I surely use Google very frequently to get help.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The new visualization package for genome data in Bioconductor: ggbio</title>
      <link>/2011/12/06/the-new-visualization-package-for-genome-data-in/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/12/06/the-new-visualization-package-for-genome-data-in/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;#8217;s been a while since I&amp;#8217;ve been waiting for the release of a visualization package in Bioconductor. Back in 2008 I was really impressed by the power ofGenomeGraphs and I have used it in multiple occasions. Yet from both the Bioconductor Developer Meeting in Heidelberg 2010 and BioC2011 I&amp;#8217;ve been waiting for the release of the visualization tools developed by Michael Lawrence and Tengfei Yin at Genentech. So, after a long hiatus where I didn&amp;#8217;t browse the biocviews in Bioconductor, I found out that Lawrence and Yin released ggbio and biovizBase (it&amp;#8217;s more of an infrastructure package for ggbio) .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing Biostatistics to first year LCG students</title>
      <link>/2011/12/04/Introducing-Biostatistics-to-first-year-LCG-students/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Dec 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/12/04/Introducing-Biostatistics-to-first-year-LCG-students/</guid>
      <description>Around two weeks ago I gave a talk via skype to the first year students from the Undergraduate Program on Genomic Sciences (LCG in Spanish) from the National Autonomous University of Mexico (UNAM in Spanish). The talk was under the context of the Introduction to Bioinformatics Seminar Series whose goal is to familiarize the new students with the bioinformatics world. It used to be a course heavy on exploring database websites, some basic theory, and lots of new concepts and algorithm names.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>