<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Research on L. Collado-Torres</title>
    <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/tags/Research/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Research on L. Collado-Torres</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2011-2018 Leonardo Collado Torres under (CC) BY-NC-SA</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://lcolladotor.github.io/tags/Research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>LIBD video</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/07/17/starting-this-week-ill-be-doing-my-research-with/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/07/17/starting-this-week-ill-be-doing-my-research-with/</guid>
      <description>Starting this week, I&amp;#8217;ll be doing my research with the Lieber Institute for Brain Development (LIBD) as Andrew Jaffe&#39;s first Ph.D. student there. My main advisor will continue to be Jeff Leek which is great for me. I&amp;#8217;ll have access to massive data sets at Lieber and will face the challenge of integrative genomics. That will be fun, exciting and challenging!Here&amp;#8217;s a short video explaining what the LIBD is about and why Baltimore is a growing city.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Great commentary on sequestration&#39;s impact on research! National media should talk about this and YOU should read it!!!</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/28/great-commentary-on-sequestrations-impact-on-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/28/great-commentary-on-sequestrations-impact-on-research/</guid>
      <description>Today Jeffrey T. Leek and Steven L. Salzberg published a paper commentary in Genome Biology today titled “Sequestration: inadvertently killing biomedical research to score political points” (Leek &amp;amp; Salzberg, 2013) which I think is a must read for anyone. Seriously!
I do not mean anyone involved in research, or all scientists. I mean, this commentary should be in the national media. Why?
Well, let me approach the technical side first. You might think that anything that appears in a scientific journal—despite any efforts to make it accessible to the general public—will rely on words whose meaning is mostly only understood by scientists.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Got acknowledged in a paper ^^</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/10/31/got-acknowledged-in-a-paper-s4/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/10/31/got-acknowledged-in-a-paper-s4/</guid>
      <description>During the weekend while I was talking with a friend and former colleague, I realized that my name was mentioned in the acknowledgements section of a paper :) I haven&amp;#8217;t been much in touch with what&amp;#8217;s been happening back home, so this was a nice surprise.
The paper is: Genetic changes during a laboratory adaptive evolution process that allowed fast growth in glucose to an Escherichia coli strain lacking the major glucose transport system by Aguilar et al.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>