<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Academia on L. Collado-Torres</title>
    <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/tags/Academia/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Academia on L. Collado-Torres</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2011-2018 Leonardo Collado Torres under (CC) BY-NC-SA 4.0. All thoughts and opinions here are my own.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://lcolladotor.github.io/tags/Academia/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Slack for Academic Departmental Communication</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/06/19/using-slack-for-academic-departmental-communication/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/06/19/using-slack-for-academic-departmental-communication/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a joint blog post between &lt;a href=&#34;http://stephaniehicks.com&#34;&gt;Stephanie Hicks&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/&#34;&gt;Leonardo Collado-Torres&lt;/a&gt;. We want to share with you our experience using Slack and why you should join us. This post is in an interview style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-06-19-using-slack-for-academic-departmental-communication_files/slack-logo.png&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;what-is-slack&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is Slack?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[SH]&lt;/code&gt; Slack is a communication tool for &lt;em&gt;teams&lt;/em&gt;. The main idea is you have individual chat rooms (referred to as &lt;em&gt;channels&lt;/em&gt; that always begin with the # symbol), which are organized by topics. Traditionally, if an email is sent to everyone on your team, each person must decide how tag or organize emails in their account. In contrast, Slack provides the structure and organization for all users on the team. Each user clicks on a specific topic, or channel, and all the messages related to that topic are already there, thereby reducing the organizational burden. In a slack team used by academic department, topics can be anything from announcements of #conferences, #workshops, #jobs, #seminars, #working_groups, #good_reads, #food_alerts, #payroll, and #IT_help. You can write public messages in the individual channels or send private direct messages to anyone on your team. Everything in Slack is searchable (e.g. files, conversations, people). Finally, Slack includes a lot of functionality and integration with other useful tools such as Google Drive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-06-19-using-slack-for-academic-departmental-communication_files/Screen%20Shot%202018-06-19%20at%204.00.33%20PM.png&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[LCT]&lt;/code&gt; Slack is a website that provides access to a group of message channels bundled together in what they call a workspace. These channels can have specific purposes and different sets of members. Slack also provides many integrations with other software that we commonly use, like integration with GitHub, todo lists, Google Calendar, Google Docs, etc. The idea of using Slack is to keep your communications with close colleagues organized and make them more fluid than email. You might use the &lt;em&gt;general&lt;/em&gt; channel for making broad announcements, such as an interesting talk from a guest. Then switch to a private channel with your 4 colleagues for that new secret project you are working on and discuss some ideas that would be useful to explore in more detail. And finally, switch to a one-on-one channel with your advisor and ask if you can meet for a few minutes that later today. Like many websites, Slack is also available as its own desktop and phone applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;how-do-you-use-slack&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How do you use Slack?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[SH]&lt;/code&gt; While I communicate with colleagues everyday on Slack, I think it’s important to distinguish between Slack and email. Both are important, I just use them for different purposes. I view communication on Slack to be for instant, real-time messaging and discussion to increase collaboration. These are usually short messages compassing a single idea. In contrast, I view email to be a slower, more deliberate medium. There is less expectation for immediate response. In both cases, you can always turn them off completely and enjoy some peace too!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-06-19-using-slack-for-academic-departmental-communication_files/Screen%20Shot%202018-06-19%20at%204.04.08%20PM.png&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;versus&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-06-19-using-slack-for-academic-departmental-communication_files/Screen%20Shot%202018-06-19%20at%204.04.18%20PM.png&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[LCT]&lt;/code&gt; I’m part of multiple Slack &lt;em&gt;workplaces&lt;/em&gt; (collections of channels and users) but I mostly use one with my genomics collaborators. There, we have a channel per project, some of which can be silent for weeks/months. But that’s ok, because I can always jump back to them and revise what we were talking about. We have a channel for R questions, one for the team that I’m a part of (Andrew Jaffe’s lab), one for organizing when and where to eat lunch, another one with the recount2 team, a diversity channel, one for our computing cluster JHPCE, among others. I also frequently ask and get asked questions on one-on-one channels with Andrew’s lab members and people elsewhere from our genomics workplace. I love using Twitter for networking in academia and keeping myself updated. So I also tend to share relevant news to specific channels I’m a part of. For the project specific channels I also use the integration with GitHub to keep everything in one place and reduce the chance of git merge issues :P&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;what-do-you-like-about-slack&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What do you like about Slack?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[SH]&lt;/code&gt; I recently transitioned from being a postdoctoral research fellow to an assistant professor. Many people warned me about the increase in the number of emails that I would receive. While that is certainly true, I would attribute Slack to being the biggest mitigator in reducing the number of emails that I have received. It reduces my email burden and increases communication between collaborators and colleagues. When an email sometimes seems too formal, Slack is &lt;em&gt;perfect&lt;/em&gt; for sending out quick messages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[LCT]&lt;/code&gt; It greatly reduces the amount of emails and email chains. Also, I like having the option of more communication with all my colleagues than would be typically allowed via email. Like no one would like an email about some interesting R package tweet or emails about lunch. Also, it was very useful this past year when I advised two students. I could get them involved in different projects, get them observe how we do some things, but also provide them a space to ask me questions during the week outside of our weekly meeting slot. Ultimately, I like to be organized and Slack helps me stay organized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;any-more-tips&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Any more tips?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[SH]&lt;/code&gt; I have found that the more I engage and write messages in channels on a Slack team, the more I get in return. As conversations flow in a given channel on a particular topic, I may or may not have anything useful to contribute. If it’s the former, I try to pass along links, advice, knowledge or whatever is appropriate. If it’s the latter, I still gain knowledge by being able to read other people’s responses and learning how others would have approached or solved a problem. Either way it’s a win-win!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[LCT]&lt;/code&gt; Regardless of what channel you use, it’s important to keep your messages polite. Basically, following a code of conduct similar to &lt;a href=&#34;http://research.libd.org/rstatsclub/#coc&#34;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;. This is not the anonymous internet, here you are interacting with your colleagues and you have to be aware of biases you might have, otherwise you might perpetrate some problems &lt;a href=&#34;https://work.qz.com/1128150/your-companys-slack-is-probably-sexist/&#34;&gt;like sexism&lt;/a&gt;. Remember, you share the responsibility of making sure that your Slack workspace is a welcoming environment where anyone is allowed to ask questions. I also think that it’s very important to keep your boundaries clear between work and home. I highly recommend going to your &lt;em&gt;preferences&lt;/em&gt; and automatically disabling notifications outside work hours as shown below. That’s something you can’t do with Google Chat: yes, I might be available after work hours, but I want to choose whether to respond or not and I don’t want others to expect an immediate answer if they see me online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-06-19-using-slack-for-academic-departmental-communication_files/Screen%20Shot%202018-06-18%20at%209.52.35%20AM.png&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want more, check &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1ji-3hLYPs3yIEu7wqyRdkGanxdON84ypuq8lyL5Yf-I/edit#slide=id.p&#34;&gt;this great presentation&lt;/a&gt; about Slack by Stephanie Hicks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;acknowledgements&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog post was made possible thanks to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=blogdown&#34;&gt;blogdown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Xie_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&#39;&gt;Xie, Hill, and Thomas, 2017&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&#34;&gt;devtools&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Wickham_2018&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&#39;&gt;Wickham, Hester, and Chang, 2018&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;references&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Wickham_2018&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Wickham_2018&#34;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt; H. Wickham, J. Hester and W. Chang. &lt;em&gt;devtools: Tools to Make Developing R Packages Easier&lt;/em&gt;. R package version 1.13.5. 2018. URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Xie_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Xie_2017&#34;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt; Y. Xie, A. P. Hill and A. Thomas. &lt;em&gt;blogdown: Creating Websites with R Markdown&lt;/em&gt;. ISBN 978-0815363729. Boca Raton, Florida: Chapman and Hall/CRC, 2017. URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&#34;&gt;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;reproducibility&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reproducibility&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Session info ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##  setting  value                       
##  version  R version 3.5.0 (2018-04-23)
##  system   x86_64, darwin15.6.0        
##  ui       X11                         
##  language (EN)                        
##  collate  en_US.UTF-8                 
##  tz       America/New_York            
##  date     2018-06-19&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Packages --------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##  package       * version date       source                            
##  backports       1.1.2   2017-12-13 cran (@1.1.2)                     
##  base          * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  bibtex          0.4.2   2017-06-30 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  BiocStyle     * 2.8.2   2018-05-30 Bioconductor                      
##  blogdown        0.6     2018-04-18 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  bookdown        0.7     2018-02-18 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  colorout      * 1.2-0   2018-05-03 Github (jalvesaq/colorout@c42088d)
##  compiler        3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  datasets      * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  devtools      * 1.13.5  2018-02-18 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  digest          0.6.15  2018-01-28 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  evaluate        0.10.1  2017-06-24 cran (@0.10.1)                    
##  graphics      * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  grDevices     * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  htmltools       0.3.6   2017-04-28 cran (@0.3.6)                     
##  httr            1.3.1   2017-08-20 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  jsonlite        1.5     2017-06-01 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  knitcitations * 1.0.8   2017-07-04 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  knitr           1.20    2018-02-20 cran (@1.20)                      
##  lubridate       1.7.4   2018-04-11 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  magrittr        1.5     2014-11-22 cran (@1.5)                       
##  memoise         1.1.0   2017-04-21 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  methods       * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  plyr            1.8.4   2016-06-08 cran (@1.8.4)                     
##  R6              2.2.2   2017-06-17 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  Rcpp            0.12.17 2018-05-18 cran (@0.12.17)                   
##  RefManageR      1.2.0   2018-04-25 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  rmarkdown       1.10    2018-06-11 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  rprojroot       1.3-2   2018-01-03 cran (@1.3-2)                     
##  stats         * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  stringi         1.2.3   2018-06-12 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  stringr         1.3.1   2018-05-10 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  tools           3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  utils         * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  withr           2.1.2   2018-03-15 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  xfun            0.2     2018-06-16 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  xml2            1.2.0   2018-01-24 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  yaml            2.1.19  2018-05-01 CRAN (R 3.5.0)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mindfulness</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/06/11/mindfulness/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/06/11/mindfulness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently participated for the first time in a silent retreat (6 hrs) as part of a &lt;em&gt;Mindfulness-Based Stress Reduction&lt;/em&gt; course. I’ve really been enjoying this course and the experience of learning new ways (for me) to live better and enjoy life more. If you haven’t heard of &lt;em&gt;mindfulness&lt;/em&gt; before (like me a few months ago), &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mindfulness&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; defines it as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Mindfulness is the psychological process of bringing one&amp;#39;s attention to
experiences occurring in the present moment, which can be developed
through the practice of meditation and other training.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In academia and science, but really anywhere, we can encounter many sources of stress (some examples below). We all deal with it in different ways and this MBSR course is just one that I’m liking right now and recommend. If there’s no course near you, check out the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00C4BA3UK&#34;&gt;Full Catastrophe Living&lt;/a&gt; book that my course is based on&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these tweets are threads, so you’ll have to open them to see them: click on the blue bird on the right side of each tweet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I won an NSF grant yesterday, with three weeks to go before applying to tenure. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A thread👇&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Dr. Bryony DuPont (@BryonyDuPont) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/BryonyDuPont/status/1005618536100683777?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 10, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Just another barrier that us scientists in &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/developing?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#developing&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/countries?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#countries&lt;/a&gt; need to find ways to overcome. Not only do we have less funding, but also generating data that for other countries is routine is more expensive. &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/latin?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#latin&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/american?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#american&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/scientists?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#scientists&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/plight?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#plight&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/Hln7N4x4iM&#34;&gt;https://t.co/Hln7N4x4iM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Daniela Robles (@daniela_oaks) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/daniela_oaks/status/1004798860835938305?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 7, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Thanks for sharing this Ted! &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/tladeras?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@tladeras&lt;/a&gt; As with anything, but particularly with mental health, I think it’s important to know you are not alone and that some things we feel have names: impostor syndrome, anxiety, depression, etc. Our minds are very powerful! &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/MentalHealthMatters?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#MentalHealthMatters&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/X1UIAznV8f&#34;&gt;https://t.co/X1UIAznV8f&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; L. Collado-Torres (@fellgernon) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/fellgernon/status/1004478330257707008?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 6, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the exercises on our silent retreat was &lt;em&gt;mindful eating&lt;/em&gt;. That is, eating slowly and focusing on our senses while eating food. This involved smelling the food, seeing all the colors it has, feeling all the different textures, and focusing on its taste. Plus, not talking to anyone. I had bought a lunch before the retreat (so I wouldn’t have to break the silence during it) that I normally don’t find interesting: some fruit and a chicken curry wrap from CVS. But wow, it was amazing that day! I greatly enjoyed how it tasted and all the different sensations I felt. I couldn’t believe it was the same food I had eaten other times before without much excitement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lately I’ve been processing some strong feelings related to feeling unwelcome, homesickness and loneliness. I’m doing many things that I know help me, starting with talking about them with my family. I’ve also been keeping myself busy doing some sports outside, going to events, bars, having friends over, etc. But what motivated me to write this post today is that after lunch I left really bad today. I had to go outside and try to calm myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-06-11-mindfulness_files/2018-06-11_13.25.34.jpg&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought I did, returned to work, and nah, I couldn’t do it today. So I went home, rested in my room in the dark, and I find myself finishing this post about 2 hours later. I’m not sure it’s related to the MSBR course, but I’m wondering if the mindfulness practice is also opening my mind’s ears and eyes to my inner feelings way more than normal&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I don’t think it’s bad. It’s just that it’s way harder to enjoy this process than it was eating a lunch. I’m trying to feel happy because I have feelings and I’m recognizing them. My family is also happy because they view it as a part of maturing and that I’m getting ready for taking another step in my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just some things are taking me way more time than normal. For example, it took me 2 days to process what I wanted to reply to a tweet and how to word it: it turned out well because I think we all heard each other ^^.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Thanks for the link &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/apreshill?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@apreshill&lt;/a&gt;! I agree that the blog post was aweful! You can’t blame X for the fact that X is marginalized. However, I disagree with the notion that Z can’t talk about X (challenging). I’m in favor of inclusion. Otherwise that line of thought leads to xenophobia&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; L. Collado-Torres (@fellgernon) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/fellgernon/status/1006207918813958145?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 11, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also discovered that the silent retreat reminded me of vacations where I turn off my phone/email and spend a few days thinking about what’s next. I used to go to Mexico every 6 months or so during my PhD to recharge. I want to do it again, but I can’t. That lead me to my strong feelings of homesickness I had today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just to close, I’m OK. I appreciate all the support I have and I recommend others to learn about mindfulness. You might be missing out some super tasty lunches and/or an exploration trip towards your inner self.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also want to add that I know some of you might see this post as over-sharing (yes, it might be). One reply is that I think that leaders also have to show their vulnerable sides. This has been debated a lot in academic twitter accounts in the context of showing your failures too, not just your successes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;acknowledgements&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog post was made possible thanks to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=blogdown&#34;&gt;blogdown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Xie_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&#39;&gt;Xie, Hill, and Thomas, 2017&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&#34;&gt;devtools&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Wickham_2018&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&#39;&gt;Wickham, Hester, and Chang, 2018&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;references&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Wickham_2018&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Wickham_2018&#34;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt; H. Wickham, J. Hester and W. Chang. &lt;em&gt;devtools: Tools to Make Developing R Packages Easier&lt;/em&gt;. R package version 1.13.5. 2018. URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Xie_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Xie_2017&#34;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt; Y. Xie, A. P. Hill and A. Thomas. &lt;em&gt;blogdown: Creating Websites with R Markdown&lt;/em&gt;. ISBN 978-0815363729. Boca Raton, Florida: Chapman and Hall/CRC, 2017. URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&#34;&gt;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;reproducibility&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reproducibility&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Session info ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##  setting  value                       
##  version  R version 3.5.0 (2018-04-23)
##  system   x86_64, darwin15.6.0        
##  ui       X11                         
##  language (EN)                        
##  collate  en_US.UTF-8                 
##  tz       America/New_York            
##  date     2018-06-11&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Packages --------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##  package       * version date       source                            
##  backports       1.1.2   2017-12-13 cran (@1.1.2)                     
##  base          * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  bibtex          0.4.2   2017-06-30 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  BiocStyle     * 2.8.1   2018-05-17 Bioconductor                      
##  blogdown        0.6     2018-04-18 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  bookdown        0.7     2018-02-18 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  colorout      * 1.2-0   2018-05-03 Github (jalvesaq/colorout@c42088d)
##  compiler        3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  datasets      * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  devtools      * 1.13.5  2018-02-18 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  digest          0.6.15  2018-01-28 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  evaluate        0.10.1  2017-06-24 cran (@0.10.1)                    
##  graphics      * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  grDevices     * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  htmltools       0.3.6   2017-04-28 cran (@0.3.6)                     
##  httr            1.3.1   2017-08-20 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  jsonlite        1.5     2017-06-01 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  knitcitations * 1.0.8   2017-07-04 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  knitr           1.20    2018-02-20 cran (@1.20)                      
##  lubridate       1.7.4   2018-04-11 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  magrittr        1.5     2014-11-22 cran (@1.5)                       
##  memoise         1.1.0   2017-04-21 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  methods       * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  plyr            1.8.4   2016-06-08 cran (@1.8.4)                     
##  R6              2.2.2   2017-06-17 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  Rcpp            0.12.17 2018-05-18 cran (@0.12.17)                   
##  RefManageR      1.2.0   2018-04-25 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  rmarkdown       1.9     2018-03-01 cran (@1.9)                       
##  rprojroot       1.3-2   2018-01-03 cran (@1.3-2)                     
##  stats         * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  stringi         1.2.2   2018-05-02 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  stringr         1.3.1   2018-05-10 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  tools           3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  utils         * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  withr           2.1.2   2018-03-15 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  xfun            0.1     2018-01-22 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  xml2            1.2.0   2018-01-24 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  yaml            2.1.19  2018-05-01 CRAN (R 3.5.0)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Baltimore friends, I have a paper copy if you want to borrow it for a while.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;It could be a coincidence with other events in my life.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Have you been &#39;relative stupid&#39;?</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/31/Have-you-been-relative-stupid/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/31/Have-you-been-relative-stupid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed reading &amp;#8220;&lt;a href=&#34;http://jcs.biologists.org/content/121/11/1771.full&#34;&gt;The importance of stupidity in scientific research&lt;/a&gt;&#34; by Martin A. Schwartz which I learned existed through &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hmason&#34;&gt;@hmason&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/simplystats&#34;&gt;@simplystats&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found the point of how it&amp;#8217;s normal to feel stupid in academia and specially in Ph.D. programs to be illuminating. But Schwartz clarifies that there are other kinds of stupid:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;we don&amp;#8217;t do a good enough job of teaching our students how to be productively stupid – that is, if we don&amp;#8217;t feel stupid it means we&amp;#8217;re not really trying. I&amp;#8217;m not talking about &#39;relative stupidity&amp;#8217;, in which the other students in the class actually read the material, think about it and ace the exam, whereas you don&amp;#8217;t. I&amp;#8217;m also not talking about bright people who might be working in areas that don&amp;#8217;t match their talents. Science involves confronting our `absolute stupidity&amp;#8217;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t know about you, but I have certainly been &amp;#8216;relative stupid&amp;#8217; at times. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yes, we have to confront our &amp;#8216;absolute stupidity&amp;#8217;. But to me, graduate school is also about learning how to be super efficient with your time. That implies being highly organized, learning how to canalize your distractions, and finding sources of constant motivation. For example, I now read more stats/R/research blogs as part of my set of distractions and have considerably decreased how many sport news I read. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also struggle with the internal challenge of doing great at school, but then also &amp;#8216;having a life&amp;#8217;. So yes, at times I have been &amp;#8216;relative stupid&amp;#8217; but also had a great time. After all, I no longer need to &amp;#8216;ace&amp;#8217; all my exams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning about social networks through an interactive presentation</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/09/28/learning-about-social-networks-through-an-interactive/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/09/28/learning-about-social-networks-through-an-interactive/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During this week&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu/~zhwu/2012journal.html&#34;&gt;journal club meeting&lt;/a&gt; Hilary Parker (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu/~hiparker/&#34;&gt;homepage&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://hilaryparker.com/&#34;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;) led the session on &amp;#8220;Identifying influential and susceptible members of social networks&amp;#8221;. Were there some speakers or why did she &amp;#8220;lead the session&amp;#8221;? By this I mean that Hilary tried a very different (and interesting) format this time. Instead of giving a talk, not a formal one like at seminars, she prepared a short presentation (publicly available &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1wlZvL8z_8bOau2ZQkvxLtOuFwEVoTeOrJeQ9dO7vATs/edit#slide=id.p&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) that begins showing a 20 minute video. This video is by the author of the paper where he presents the key points of his research at another conference. The goal of this format was to get us to speed and hopefully provoke enough discussion to make the meeting highly interactive. Plus the author does a great job in his presentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, given that it&amp;#8217;s a biostat journal club, Hilary included some slides to explain the general Cox Proportional Hazard model before showing some of details used in the paper in question. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that the change of format was a step in the right direction. Hopefully others will follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder=&#34;0&#34; height=&#34;253&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/JmajkTKlEqw&#34; width=&#34;450&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About the paper itself, the topic is interesting since it shows a different view of the &amp;#8220;data science&amp;#8221; vs biostat discussion. The presenter is trying to convince computer scientists that they need to do some statistics too. Over here, we are poking our heads at whether we need to learn some computer science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, the author is in a different setting than academia or industry, which are commonly the two options. He is at NYU, and academic institution, but he is working closely with the industry (thus getting access to interesting data) and might be getting some consultation money along the way. Anyhow, given the recent talk from Amy Heineike on Quid (&lt;a href=&#34;http://fellgernon.tumblr.com/post/32472984157/quid-biostat-jhsph#.UGYOW_l27mY&#34;&gt;more in my previous post&lt;/a&gt;) there is a growing interest among students to learn more about the industry environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made a couple of comments during the discussion, which might be completely wrong. One is that I feel that in academia we care much more about bias and removing sources of error and it seems that in industry that&amp;#8217;s not the main point. There you care more about making something useful which might be biased. You try to minimize it, but the judge are the clients. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second one is that in industry options like getting a larger sample are much more feasible. In the video, at some point the author shows that people eventually joined the app after getting massively spammed. Increasing the exposure is easy in this case, but imagine a public health survey that is carried out door by door. Increasing the number of houses visited is way more expensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point is that the club meeting followed an interesting format, social networks seem fun to analyze, and industry vs academia is kind of a hot topic in our department right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Hilary for publicly sharing her journal club presentation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
