<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gmail on L. Collado-Torres</title>
    <link>/tags/gmail/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Gmail on L. Collado-Torres</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2011-{year} Leonardo Collado Torres under (CC) BY-NC-SA 4.0. All thoughts and opinions here are my own.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://lcolladotor.github.io/tags/gmail/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Liking &#34;Inbox Zero for Life&#34;</title>
      <link>/2013/02/14/liking-inbox-zero-for-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/02/14/liking-inbox-zero-for-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been using the &amp;#8220;&lt;a href=&#34;http://bit.ly/12vYvIh&#34;&gt;Inbox Zero for Life&lt;/a&gt;&#34; strategy for a few weeks, and I think that it&amp;#8217;s been payed off for me in this short span.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it&amp;#8217;s stated in that long guide, one of the major concerns you might have is that it could end up as just changing a current problem for another one. I think that so far, that hasn&amp;#8217;t been the case for me. Sure, my starred emails is not 0, but it stays at a steady number and doesn&amp;#8217;t increase as my inbox (even with priority inbox) did. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also have a few filters in place that pick up the emails that I will most likely never read. For example, advertising emails and school wide announcements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One point I&amp;#8217;m not sure that I buy is the whole psychological effect of having an empty inbox. But whether or not that&amp;#8217;s true, I certainly didn&amp;#8217;t know that the gmail app in the iPhone/iPad has a weird smiley that looks like a sun telling you something like: &amp;#8220;Your inbox is empty. Have a nice day!&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Credit goes to &lt;a href=&#34;http://bit.ly/12vVmbp&#34;&gt;Hilary&lt;/a&gt; for finding telling us about this strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Check all your accounts for emails at once in Gmail</title>
      <link>/2012/10/02/check-all-your-accounts-for-emails-at-once-in-gmail/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/10/02/check-all-your-accounts-for-emails-at-once-in-gmail/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Do you use Gmail as your primary email account? Primary, what? Well, I&amp;#8217;m sure that you have your personal account somewhere and your work or university account too. You can either log into each email interface or you can integrate them to a single one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gmail makes this easy as you can go to the &amp;#8220;Settings -&amp;gt; Accounts and Import&amp;#8221; to set up Gmail to pull all of your email into it. In that same page you can configure Gmail to send email through your work/university accounts or at least camouflage it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is all great, but as you will soon learn, Gmail pulls the emails from your other accounts at random intervals. It tries to do so in an intelligent way by pulling more frequently during the times of the day that you get more emails from those accounts. But you&amp;#8217;ll soon realize that some emails get pulled an hour later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe this is what you want. Specially if you get TONS of emails and you don&amp;#8217;t want anyone to expect immediate replies from you, thus promoting more intelligent emails from them and hopefully reducing your email traffic load.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But maybe you don&amp;#8217;t like this behavior. That&amp;#8217;s where the &amp;#8221;Multiple Inbox&amp;#8221; Google Lab comes in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://media.tumblr.com/tumblr_mbah5wwEhW1qfs0hy.png&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find it by going to &amp;#8220;Settings -&amp;gt; Labs&amp;#8221;. &amp;#8220;Multiple Inbox&amp;#8221; is designed to help those that have multiple Gmail accounts. But it also changes the behavior of the &amp;#8220;refresh&amp;#8221; button. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://media.tumblr.com/tumblr_mbah1mSYQh1qfs0hy.png&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you enable &amp;#8220;Multiple Inbox&amp;#8221;, the refresh button will automatically look for new emails in ALL of your accounts. Thus you will no longer have to go to &amp;#8220;Settings -&amp;gt; Accounts and Import&amp;#8221; to manually look for new emails by clicking on the &amp;#8220;Check mail now&amp;#8221; links. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that &amp;#8220;Multiple Inbox&amp;#8221; creates automatic &lt;em&gt;panes&lt;/em&gt; if you are using the default inbox. If you don&amp;#8217;t like them, you can simply go to &amp;#8220;Settings -&amp;gt; Multiple Inbox&amp;#8221; and clear the default searches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://media.tumblr.com/tumblr_mbahe4Bu1t1qfs0hy.png&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Edited: minor word change]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
