<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Diversity on L. Collado-Torres</title>
    <link>/tags/Diversity/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Diversity on L. Collado-Torres</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2011-2018 Leonardo Collado Torres under (CC) BY-NC-SA 4.0. All thoughts and opinions here are my own.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 17 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://lcolladotor.github.io/tags/Diversity/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>What about a lawyer-like app as the mininum help for defandants in immigration cases?</title>
      <link>/2018/09/17/what-about-a-lawyer-like-app-as-the-mininum-help-for-defandants-in-immigration-cases/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/09/17/what-about-a-lawyer-like-app-as-the-mininum-help-for-defandants-in-immigration-cases/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I attended the special panel discussion event at JHSPH called &lt;a href=&#34;http://hopkinshumanitarianhealth.org/news-events/events/separated-child-separation-at-the-border-a-health-and-human-rights-perspect&#34;&gt;“Separated: Children Separation at the Border A Health and Human Rights Perspective”&lt;/a&gt;. It got my mind racing and here’s an idea. It’s likely (definitely) incomplete, but maybe it’ll get others to think on related ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-09-17-what-about-a-lawyer-like-app-as-the-mininum-help-for-defandants-in-immigration-cases_files/ChildSepBorder.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;panel-summary&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Panel summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The panel was composed by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Colleen Kraft, President, American Academy of Pediatrics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eric Schwartz, President, Refugee International&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;George Escobar, Chief of Program and Services, CASA da Maryland&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paul Spiegel, Director, Center for Humanitarian Health&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I missed the first 30 minutes or so but I still got to listen to most of it. The panel members presented many facts and here are some that will be relevant to the idea I have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Child separation is just one of the consequences of the current’s administration immigration policies implemented and enforced by the Department of Justice (ultimately headed by Jeff Sessions, the US Attorney General).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The US is the only country (to the panel’s members knowledge) with a child separation policy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Due to empathy many individuals across political lines reacted against child separation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The US immigration system won’t really change much even if Democrats get elected. Obama did deport over 2 million individuals, though he prioritized &lt;em&gt;criminals&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arrested immigrants are not required by law to have representation (a lawyer) provided by the government&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Minors (say 3 year old children) with no lawyers are being highlighted in the media.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Immigration cases where the defendants have lawyers drastically improve&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; the odds for the defendants.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Immigration judges are human.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Immigration judges typically used to (or maybe still do) try to give time for a minor to get a lawyer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Immigration judges are &lt;em&gt;alledgely&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn4&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; being pressured to meet quotas in the range of 700 to 1,000 cases by year under the current administration. Thus judges sometimes have to close cases in a couple of hours.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Immigration judges now basically have 2 options for closing a case: order deportation or (I’m missing the correct term) &lt;em&gt;free&lt;/em&gt; the defendant.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end the panel members highlighted that &lt;em&gt;we&lt;/em&gt; should take some type of action&lt;a href=&#34;#fn5&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; but that we should consider the consequences of our suggested policy changes. They also mentioned that we should take advantage of this moment (child separation got everyone’s attention) to raise the profile of the other problems with the current immigration policies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;my-way-of-taking-action-heres-an-idea&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;My way of taking action: here’s an idea&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m by no means an immigration expert. My way of taking action is to share ideas, like &lt;a href=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/2017/01/25/An-alternative-to-the-Mexico-US-wall-where-the-US-would-gain-millions-of-dollars/#.W6BV4v5Kg0o&#34;&gt;I’ve done in the past&lt;/a&gt;, that might be incomplete, unrealistic or even super flawed, but that hopefully motivate others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bare bones version of my idea was: what if immigrants could have an &lt;em&gt;automatic&lt;/em&gt; (programmed) lawyer and translator during their hearings? This would not be a replacement for actually having lawyers (say those provided by local governments or NGOs as George Escobar mentioned) but would raise the minimum bar for those immigrants who currently have their cases processed with no lawyers at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;getting-into-the-details&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Getting into the details&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine that we could get our hands on dozens/hundreds/thousands? of transcripts of immigration court hearings where we have the following information:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what the judge said&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what the government’s lawyer said&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what the defendant’s lawyer said (either to the judge or to the defendant)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what the defendant said&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like a script for a play. We would additionally need a table with court hearing metadata such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Outcome: deportation, being &lt;em&gt;freed&lt;/em&gt; (term?).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Date of the hearing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;State where the hearing occurred.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then using machine learning (maybe with deep learning methods) process the text and try to determine potential suggestions an actual defendant’s lawyer would give to its defendant or respond to the judge/government’s lawyer. It might not always get things right, but I imagine that it would be better than the current state of affairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The automatic lawyer would need then to work as say a phone app that listens to what others are saying in the room. Say have 3 icons with one per person present (judge, defendant, gov’s lawyer). Then the defendant presses each button when each person is talking. The app then shows some 1 to say 3 suggested responses (with translations)&lt;a href=&#34;#fn6&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref6&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and responds for the defendant in English once the defendant chooses an option (or goes with the top one).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;implementing-an-initial-version-of-the-app&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Implementing an initial version of the app&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that large computing companies like Amazon, Microsoft and Google would be willing to provide some compute credits on their clouds for the initial version of the algorithm that is &lt;em&gt;listening&lt;/em&gt; to the court hearing and then provides suggestions. Think of this as the “suggested text” you get nowadays when typing emails on Gmail or text messages. Maybe these companies have programs where you can apply to have some of their engineers help you for a certain number of hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that one big initial challenge would be to get that collection of transcripts from immigration court hearings where defendant lawyer(s) were present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also imagine that automated lawyers are not allowed currently in courts. But compared to providing human lawyers in all immigration cases, this change might be more &lt;em&gt;realistic&lt;/em&gt; to pass as a law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also imagine that some phone companies might be willing to provide some refurbished phones that only have this app installed and are kept safe in the immigration courts. And well, satisfy any security requirements the government has.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;improving-the-app&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Improving the app&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lets say that you get that alpha version of the app working. If we had volunteer lawyers annotate the transcripts with some information about the intent behind what each person said (it could start with just 3 options: negative, positive, neutral from the perspective of the defendant) that could maybe help the algorithm that processes the transcripts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we also had more detailed court hearing metadata such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Location of the court (I imagine a that a few judges work in each court)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Demographics of the defendants: like which country or even region of the country where they come from, whether the defendant has any family support, etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Category information for the court hearing (maybe cases can be grouped into a few categories)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;then I imagine that the app would be able to have more personalized experience, like re-adjust the suggestions based on which court you are located at and adapt the translations to the Spanish version the defendant is most familiar with (we say &lt;em&gt;buddy&lt;/em&gt; in so many different ways as shown below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-09-17-what-about-a-lawyer-like-app-as-the-mininum-help-for-defandants-in-immigration-cases_files/bromap.png&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/pictoline/photos/a.1611821172410355.1073741828.1598399590419180/1623937737865365/?type=1&amp;amp;fref=nf&#34;&gt;Image source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The app could also be connected to remote human immigration lawyers than can intervene remotely when the suggestions algorithm doensn’t know what to do. Maybe this could be part of some social service that immigration lawyers (regardless of their personal political preferences) could do as some elective during their formation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;doing-some-convincing&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Doing some convincing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that you could try to get support for this automatic immigration lawyer by arguing that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s better than no lawyer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s cheaper than having lawyers for all cases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improves processing times on average (ideally) such that immigration judges can fulfill their quotas (here I’m hoping that it reduces the rate at which cases are closed with deportation orders).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is more humane than having a minor with no help. Though I hope that immigration judges would still try to give time for children to secure a lawyer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Might be implemented earlier (years earlier?) than changes in immigration law requiring that all defendants have a human lawyer in immigration cases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If human lawyers can help through the app, then it also increases the number of jobs for immigration lawyers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This idea has potentially many flaws because like any system, people on both sides will try to game it. This is where having a large set of transcripts would be useful as well as continuous updates to the algorithm such that gaming the system actually becomes hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;acknowledgements&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog post was made possible thanks to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://bioconductor.org/packages/3.8/BiocStyle&#34;&gt;BiocStyle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Oles_2018&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://github.com/Bioconductor/BiocStyle&#39;&gt;Oleś, Morgan, and Huber, 2018&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=blogdown&#34;&gt;blogdown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Xie_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&#39;&gt;Xie, Hill, and Thomas, 2017&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&#34;&gt;devtools&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Wickham_2018&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&#39;&gt;Wickham, Hester, and Chang, 2018&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&#34;&gt;knitcitations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Boettiger_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&#39;&gt;Boettiger, 2017&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;references&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Boettiger_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Boettiger_2017&#34;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt; C. Boettiger. &lt;em&gt;knitcitations: Citations for ‘Knitr’ Markdown Files&lt;/em&gt;. R package version 1.0.8. 2017. URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Oles_2018&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Oles_2018&#34;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt; A. Oleś, M. Morgan and W. Huber. &lt;em&gt;BiocStyle: Standard styles for vignettes and other Bioconductor documents&lt;/em&gt;. R package version 2.9.6. 2018. URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Bioconductor/BiocStyle&#34;&gt;https://github.com/Bioconductor/BiocStyle&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Wickham_2018&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Wickham_2018&#34;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt; H. Wickham, J. Hester and W. Chang. &lt;em&gt;devtools: Tools to Make Developing R Packages Easier&lt;/em&gt;. R package version 1.13.6. 2018. URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Xie_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Xie_2017&#34;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt; Y. Xie, A. P. Hill and A. Thomas. &lt;em&gt;blogdown: Creating Websites with R Markdown&lt;/em&gt;. ISBN 978-0815363729. Boca Raton, Florida: Chapman and Hall/CRC, 2017. URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&#34;&gt;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;reproducibility&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reproducibility&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Session info ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##  setting  value                       
##  version  R version 3.5.1 (2018-07-02)
##  system   x86_64, darwin15.6.0        
##  ui       X11                         
##  language (EN)                        
##  collate  en_US.UTF-8                 
##  tz       America/New_York            
##  date     2018-09-17&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Packages --------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##  package       * version date       source                            
##  backports       1.1.2   2017-12-13 cran (@1.1.2)                     
##  base          * 3.5.1   2018-07-09 local                             
##  bibtex          0.4.2   2017-06-30 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  BiocManager     1.30.2  2018-08-24 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  BiocStyle     * 2.9.6   2018-08-19 Bioconductor                      
##  blogdown        0.8     2018-07-15 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  bookdown        0.7     2018-02-18 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  colorout      * 1.2-0   2018-05-03 Github (jalvesaq/colorout@c42088d)
##  compiler        3.5.1   2018-07-09 local                             
##  datasets      * 3.5.1   2018-07-09 local                             
##  devtools      * 1.13.6  2018-06-27 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  digest          0.6.16  2018-08-22 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  evaluate        0.11    2018-07-17 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  graphics      * 3.5.1   2018-07-09 local                             
##  grDevices     * 3.5.1   2018-07-09 local                             
##  htmltools       0.3.6   2017-04-28 cran (@0.3.6)                     
##  httr            1.3.1   2017-08-20 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  jsonlite        1.5     2017-06-01 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  knitcitations * 1.0.8   2017-07-04 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  knitr           1.20    2018-02-20 cran (@1.20)                      
##  lubridate       1.7.4   2018-04-11 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  magrittr        1.5     2014-11-22 cran (@1.5)                       
##  memoise         1.1.0   2017-04-21 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  methods       * 3.5.1   2018-07-09 local                             
##  plyr            1.8.4   2016-06-08 cran (@1.8.4)                     
##  R6              2.2.2   2017-06-17 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  Rcpp            0.12.18 2018-07-23 CRAN (R 3.5.1)                    
##  RefManageR      1.2.0   2018-04-25 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  rmarkdown       1.10    2018-06-11 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  rprojroot       1.3-2   2018-01-03 cran (@1.3-2)                     
##  stats         * 3.5.1   2018-07-09 local                             
##  stringi         1.2.4   2018-07-20 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  stringr         1.3.1   2018-05-10 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  tools           3.5.1   2018-07-09 local                             
##  utils         * 3.5.1   2018-07-09 local                             
##  withr           2.1.2   2018-03-15 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  xfun            0.3     2018-07-06 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  xml2            1.2.0   2018-01-24 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  yaml            2.2.0   2018-07-25 CRAN (R 3.5.0)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;George Escobar mentioned that they protested the fact that a DUI labeled someone as a criminal, but well, Trump has gone beyond DUIs arrested many individuals with no criminal history.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;George Escobar highlighted that one path of action is to convince local governments to fund/provide lawyers to these individuals.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don’t know by how much.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn4&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Information has leaked about this but I guess that it’s not completely public info.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn5&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Could be with your vote, helping members in your community that are affected, improving how we translate research into terms everyone understands, improving the education about the violent reality many are trying to escape by coming to the US, approaching local governments, etc.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref5&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn6&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The app could show the text but also should &lt;em&gt;read&lt;/em&gt; the translations since very young children will very likely not know how to read. I think that the app should never assume that the defendant knows how to read.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref6&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Harassment, diversity in science and inspiration from my grandmother</title>
      <link>/2018/07/30/harassment-diversity-in-science-and-inspiration-from-my-grandmother/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/07/30/harassment-diversity-in-science-and-inspiration-from-my-grandmother/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today was a big day. I care about many things including diversity in science (STEM) and building a community of R users and developers in Mexico. Both moved forward in two completely separate conferences: one in Mexico: &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/search?q=jsm2018&#34;&gt;CDSBMexico&lt;/a&gt;; and one in Canada: &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/search?q=jsm2018&#34;&gt;JSM2018&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;cdsbmexico&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;CDSBMexico&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a very important day for me. It was the beginning of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.comunidadbioinfo.org/r-bioconductor-developers-workshop-2018/&#34;&gt;Latin American R/BioConductor Developers Workshop 2018&lt;/a&gt; in Cuernavaca, Mexico. I already wrote a blog post about &lt;a href=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/04/19/latin-american-r-bioconductor-developers-workshop-2018/#.W1-lhNhKi50&#34;&gt;why I was super excited about CDSBMexico&lt;/a&gt;, but briefly it’s because this is something we’ve been wanting to see become a reality for years and have been working towards it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Here are my slides for my &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/CDSBMexico?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#CDSBMexico&lt;/a&gt; remote talk tomorrow for day 1 of the &amp;quot;Latin American R/BioConductor Developers Workshop 2018&amp;quot;. 70 slides for ~20 min, I can do this! 💪🏾 Right &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jtleek?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@jtleek&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Shannon_E_Ellis?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@Shannon_E_Ellis&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/xKh2214YbM&#34;&gt;https://t.co/xKh2214YbM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/rstats?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#rstats&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/teaching?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#teaching&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Bioconductor?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@Bioconductor&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/CDSBMexico?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@CDSBMexico&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/SULAoPbHeZ&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/SULAoPbHeZ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; 🇲🇽 Dr. Leonardo Collado-Torres (@fellgernon) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/fellgernon/status/1023665229882961922?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 29, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My job was to give the first keynote to pump up everyone at the workshop. So I had a bit of trouble sleeping and woke up remembering a dream. If you know me, I &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; dream: or never remember my dreams. It was a dream of my grandmother Mercedes Vides Tovar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-07-30-harrassment-diversity-in-science-and-inspiraton-from-my-grandmother_files/2018-07-30%2018.15.38.jpg&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;grandma&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Grandma&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have many things from my grandparents in me, like José’s joviality, Rosa’s love, Rolando’s tenacity to overcome tough moments. Or so I like to think. But my grandma, &lt;em&gt;Abue&lt;/em&gt;, has always been an academic inspiration. She overcame many challenges in her life. She studied at the university to become a doctor, even without total family support (to avoid details). She was a trailblazer in the field of Epidemiology. She had to flee her native country leaving everything behind. She studied at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pasteur.fr/en&#34;&gt;Institut Pasteur&lt;/a&gt; in Paris, France while caring for 3 adolescents as a single mom. She studied in a time when &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/search?q=womeninstem&#34;&gt;WomenInSTEM&lt;/a&gt; had to disguise themselves up as men and were the targets of jokes all the time. Rolando, her classmate at the university, has told me a handful of these &lt;em&gt;jokes&lt;/em&gt;: I wouldn’t be the only one to call many of them harassment. She left academia to start her own business in public health. She was the main health supervisor in the first international conference my dad organized early in his career (which helped him launch it): I was the 6 year old in charge of delivering the gifts in the closing ceremony ^^. She would answer my phone calls when I first started French school and my dad was busy at work: thanks to their time in Paris my dad fell in love with the French way of teaching math.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-07-30-harrassment-diversity-in-science-and-inspiraton-from-my-grandmother_files/2018-07-30%2018.41.52.jpg&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I actually don’t know much more. She passed away when I was 13 after a years long battle with disease. Google tells me that she is a co-author of at least three titles in the field of Public Health:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1968 &lt;a href=&#34;http://saludpublica.mx/index.php/spm/article/download/3327/3212&#34;&gt;Organización del servicio social de los pasantes de Odontología en México&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1970 &lt;a href=&#34;http://saludpublica.mx/index.php/spm/article/viewFile/2346/2234&#34;&gt;Situación epidemiológica de la frontera norte de México y programa de vigilancia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1972 &lt;a href=&#34;http://saludpublica.mx/index.php/spm/article/download/1874/1822&#34;&gt;Proyecto de organización y funcionamiento de los laboratorios de salud pública en los estados de la frontera norte&lt;/a&gt;: also, she’s the sole author.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-07-30-harrassment-diversity-in-science-and-inspiraton-from-my-grandmother_files/2018-07-30%2017.22.57.jpg&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did inherit her souvenirs from her trips (my dad also loves them) and something that is precious to me: a medal with her name. I’ve looked at that medal next to my bed in Mexico many times. I would look at it, search for inspiration, then try harder to solve whatever academic problem I had.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my dream there was a moment where I was sitting next to her (me in my current adult form) and we were revising many of our shared moments. She was explaining to me things she couldn’t explain before because I wouldn’t have understood them. She also pumped me up before my day and wished me luck for my talk. I think that I delivered ^^&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;es&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/CDSBMexico?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@CDSBMexico&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/fellgernon?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@fellgernon&lt;/a&gt; dio una charla inspiradora &amp;lt;3 &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/collaboration?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#collaboration&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/rstats?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#rstats&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/TIBs2018?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#TIBs2018&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/nnb_unam?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@nnb_unam&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Semiramis (@semiramis_cj) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/semiramis_cj/status/1023953817187090435?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 30, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;womeninstem&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;WomenInStem&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today was a big day for &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/search?q=womeninstem&#34;&gt;WomenInSTEM&lt;/a&gt; and in particular in the field of Statistics. Why? Today the Joint Statistical Meetings (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/search?q=jsm2018&#34;&gt;JSM2018&lt;/a&gt;) held a session on “Addressing Sexual Misconduct in Statistics” that was organized by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/stephaniehicks&#34;&gt;Stephanie Hicks&lt;/a&gt; and chaired by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/keegankorthauer&#34;&gt;Keegan Korthauer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;For &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/JSM2018?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#JSM2018&lt;/a&gt;, I organized a session on Addressing Sexual Misconduct in Statistics. If you plan to attend the meeting, I invite you to join us &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/UxpUiqPzTy&#34;&gt;https://t.co/UxpUiqPzTy&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/IdShEPlqi6&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/IdShEPlqi6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Stephanie Hicks (@stephaniehicks) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/stephaniehicks/status/1004467110918213637?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 6, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The session is not a direct response (I think) but it’s definitely related to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/KLdivergence&#34;&gt;Kristian Lum&lt;/a&gt;’s blog post titled &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@kristianlum/statistics-we-have-a-problem-304638dc5de5&#34;&gt;Statistics, we have a problem&lt;/a&gt; and to the more general &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/search?q=metoo&#34;&gt;MeToo&lt;/a&gt; movement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sexual harassment and misconduct not a US problem only. We have a code of conduct at &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/CDSBMexico&#34;&gt;CDSBMexico&lt;/a&gt; both in &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ComunidadBioInfo/R-BioConductor-Developers-Workshop-2018/blob/master/R-Bioconductor-2018_Program.rmd#code-of-conduct&#34;&gt;English&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.comunidadbioinfo.org/codigo-de-conducta/&#34;&gt;Spanish&lt;/a&gt; to help prevent any issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Q by me: what to do when people outside the U.S. say that this is an American problem and they don&amp;#39;t need to have a code of conduct for their meeting? &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/JSM2018?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#JSM2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Michael Hoffman (@michaelhoffman) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/michaelhoffman/status/1024060403138142209?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 30, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t be there, but I wasn’t the only one excited following what has happening online thanks to tweets from many including &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mandyfmejia&#34;&gt;Mandy Mejia&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/michaelhoffman&#34;&gt;Michael Hoffman&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;THIS IS ACTUALLY HAPPENING. Now in CC-West Ballroom A. &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/JSM2018?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#JSM2018&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/Pw9zdlhi02&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/Pw9zdlhi02&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Mandy Mejia (@mandyfmejia) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mandyfmejia/status/1024042337033285632?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 30, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;times-are-changing&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Times are changing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do think that slowly, maybe sometimes quickly, the times are changing. I’ve been telling friends and family for a few years now that I’ve come to realize that we need to keep trying to improve, to stay updated, to do what’s best and maybe sometimes come up with new ideas to improve things. I do care quite a bit for &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/search?q=womeninstem&#34;&gt;WomenInSTEM&lt;/a&gt; but for me, it’s larger than that. It’s about diversity. I don’t know in how many different ways we can label each other and it’s not the point. So yes, gender diversity is a good thing and initiatives like this seem like a good thing to do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Looks like a good thing to do. &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/m2sjLYB1Er&#34;&gt;https://t.co/m2sjLYB1Er&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/ashg18?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#ashg18&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/iKofjrIKTx&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/iKofjrIKTx&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; 🇲🇽 Dr. Leonardo Collado-Torres (@fellgernon) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/fellgernon/status/1024068383564853248?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 30, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then I think immediately of next steps, like race and ethnicity as well as sexual diversity. I want to ask for more, but I sometimes hold myself back. I’m no expert on many of these topics, so maybe what seems like a good policy could easily backfire later. So I think about incremental steps. But maybe that’s too slow and not enough. Maybe careers are suffering but I guess that as a community we are going as safely and fast as we can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;This 💯! My career trajectory would have been completely different in absence of hostile environments. &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/aqmQtVyXUW&#34;&gt;https://t.co/aqmQtVyXUW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Dr. Elana J Fertig (@FertigLab) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/FertigLab/status/1024044326664527875?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 30, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not supporting whoever Michael was referencing in his next tweet. I don’t flirt at conferences: I do socialize and try to make new friends with fellow conference attendees. I do acknowledge that I struggle in my head with what is ok and not ok to do, particularly with people you spend at lot of time with at school, work, etc. I’m not certain of the boundary between clumsy dating skills and sexual misconduct in some scenarios. I think that I’m not the only one because I’ve heard different versions in different sexual harassment prevention sessions. So mostly I end up doing nothing yet sometimes I wonder if I lost out because I didn’t try a bit more with X person. For instance, Mercedes maried her classmate Rolando. What can I say, I’m still learning and we all probably need to learn to differentiate these boundaries better through more training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;We ran out of time so we didn&amp;#39;t get to hear the question from the dude who was saying that something (I presume flirting at conferences) was &amp;quot;human nature&amp;quot;. Our loss, I&amp;#39;m sure &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/JSM2018?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#JSM2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Michael Hoffman (@michaelhoffman) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/michaelhoffman/status/1024066415752433664?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 30, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also know that sometimes I’ve been a bystander and failed to take action. So this next idea sounds good to me. I do try to intervene more now, specially with micro aggressions: because they are less high pressure situations and easier to do something about, at least that’s how I feel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Bystander training might help. It&amp;#39;s not easy to do the right thing in a difficult situation when you have no idea what the right thing is, no training, no experience, no practice. &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/JSM2018?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#JSM2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Michael Hoffman (@michaelhoffman) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/michaelhoffman/status/1024063008987787264?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 30, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To close my post, I encourage you to check their request for feedback!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;If you’re planning to come to our session (211) on sexual misconduct today (and even if you’re not) you might take a look at these scenarios that we’ll use to get the conversation started. Link in RT below. &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/JSM2018?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#JSM2018&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/czjUKYkHq1&#34;&gt;https://t.co/czjUKYkHq1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Kristian Lum (@KLdivergence) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/KLdivergence/status/1023977618104889346?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 30, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if you are an R non-cis male person, you should totally join the R-Ladies community slack!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;📢 Join our new ✨ R-Ladies community Slack! ✨&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It&amp;#39;s aiming for a safe &amp;amp; global space to discuss topics and share ideas around &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/rstats?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#rstats&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; the &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/rladies?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#rladies&lt;/a&gt; community! 💜&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;We invite all non-cis male R users to sign-up via &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/TOXALUGLuf&#34;&gt;https://t.co/TOXALUGLuf&lt;/a&gt; 🚀 &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/ZMNuqkN0HW&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/ZMNuqkN0HW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; R-Ladies Global (@RLadiesGlobal) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/RLadiesGlobal/status/1022031250759053314?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 25, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;acknowledgements&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog post was made possible thanks to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=blogdown&#34;&gt;blogdown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Xie_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&#39;&gt;Xie, Hill, and Thomas, 2017&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&#34;&gt;devtools&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Wickham_2018&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&#39;&gt;Wickham, Hester, and Chang, 2018&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&#34;&gt;knitcitations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Boettiger_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&#39;&gt;Boettiger, 2017&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;references&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Boettiger_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Boettiger_2017&#34;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt; C. Boettiger. &lt;em&gt;knitcitations: Citations for ‘Knitr’ Markdown Files&lt;/em&gt;. R package version 1.0.8. 2017. URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Wickham_2018&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Wickham_2018&#34;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt; H. Wickham, J. Hester and W. Chang. &lt;em&gt;devtools: Tools to Make Developing R Packages Easier&lt;/em&gt;. R package version 1.13.6. 2018. URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Xie_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Xie_2017&#34;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt; Y. Xie, A. P. Hill and A. Thomas. &lt;em&gt;blogdown: Creating Websites with R Markdown&lt;/em&gt;. ISBN 978-0815363729. Boca Raton, Florida: Chapman and Hall/CRC, 2017. URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&#34;&gt;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;reproducibility&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reproducibility&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Session info ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##  setting  value                       
##  version  R version 3.5.1 (2018-07-02)
##  system   x86_64, darwin15.6.0        
##  ui       X11                         
##  language (EN)                        
##  collate  en_US.UTF-8                 
##  tz       America/New_York            
##  date     2018-07-31&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Packages --------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##  package       * version date       source                            
##  backports       1.1.2   2017-12-13 cran (@1.1.2)                     
##  base          * 3.5.1   2018-07-05 local                             
##  bibtex          0.4.2   2017-06-30 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  BiocStyle     * 2.8.2   2018-05-30 Bioconductor                      
##  blogdown        0.8     2018-07-15 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  bookdown        0.7     2018-02-18 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  colorout      * 1.2-0   2018-05-03 Github (jalvesaq/colorout@c42088d)
##  compiler        3.5.1   2018-07-05 local                             
##  datasets      * 3.5.1   2018-07-05 local                             
##  devtools      * 1.13.6  2018-06-27 cran (@1.13.6)                    
##  digest          0.6.15  2018-01-28 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  evaluate        0.11    2018-07-17 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  graphics      * 3.5.1   2018-07-05 local                             
##  grDevices     * 3.5.1   2018-07-05 local                             
##  htmltools       0.3.6   2017-04-28 cran (@0.3.6)                     
##  httr            1.3.1   2017-08-20 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  jsonlite        1.5     2017-06-01 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  knitcitations * 1.0.8   2017-07-04 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  knitr           1.20    2018-02-20 cran (@1.20)                      
##  lubridate       1.7.4   2018-04-11 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  magrittr        1.5     2014-11-22 cran (@1.5)                       
##  memoise         1.1.0   2017-04-21 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  methods       * 3.5.1   2018-07-05 local                             
##  plyr            1.8.4   2016-06-08 cran (@1.8.4)                     
##  R6              2.2.2   2017-06-17 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  Rcpp            0.12.18 2018-07-23 CRAN (R 3.5.1)                    
##  RefManageR      1.2.0   2018-04-25 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  rmarkdown       1.10    2018-06-11 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  rprojroot       1.3-2   2018-01-03 cran (@1.3-2)                     
##  stats         * 3.5.1   2018-07-05 local                             
##  stringi         1.2.4   2018-07-20 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  stringr         1.3.1   2018-05-10 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  tools           3.5.1   2018-07-05 local                             
##  utils         * 3.5.1   2018-07-05 local                             
##  withr           2.1.2   2018-03-15 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  xfun            0.3     2018-07-06 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  xml2            1.2.0   2018-01-24 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  yaml            2.1.19  2018-05-01 CRAN (R 3.5.0)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
