<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>PosterGenius | L. Collado-Torres</title>
    <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/tags/postergenius/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://lcolladotor.github.io/tags/postergenius/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>PosterGenius</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2011-2022. All thoughts and opinions here are my own. The icon was designed by [Mauricio Guzmán](https://www.linkedin.com/in/mauricio-guzman-6529b551/) and is inspired by [Huichol culture](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Huichol); it represents my community building interests</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://lcolladotor.github.io/images/icon_hu2b32c4ab415f12f472f73c7b0301b0d1_19400_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>PosterGenius</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/tags/postergenius/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quickly making posters with PosterGenius</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/10/29/Quickly-making-posters-with-PosterGenius/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/10/29/Quickly-making-posters-with-PosterGenius/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is time to revive &lt;a href=&#34;http://bit.ly/FellgernonBit&#34;&gt;Fellgernon Bit&lt;/a&gt; from it&amp;#8217;s deep hibernation period. A couple of very motivated Ph.D. students from my department (John, Alyssa, Amanda, Jean-Philippe, Elizabeth, etc) are organizing a blogging group. The idea is to review ideas, give suggestions, learn blogging technicalities, write blog posts, review them, and post them. It&amp;#8217;s a great idea! Plus it should us keep our blogs active.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So for my first post I am going to talk about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.postergenius.com/cms/index.php&#34;&gt;PosterGenius&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;#8217;s a simple to use piece of software for making posters. In my case, I presented a poster at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://genomics.jhu.edu/symposium.html&#34;&gt;7th Annual Young Investigators Symposium and Poster Session on Genomics and Bioinformatics&lt;/a&gt;. It was a relatively small event and I had a limited amount of time to make the poster. The idea behind &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.postergenius.com/cms/index.php&#34;&gt;PosterGenius&lt;/a&gt; is that you separate your poster into several sections (intro, methods, results, references), have some material for each (text and or figures), and just have to put it together with a simple background.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, there are plenty of other tools for doing this. But in my case, I was able to make a poster in lunch hour by using slides from a presentation on the same subject and just organizing the content. The basic steps are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Choose a poster template, number of columns, height and width.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose how many sections and their titles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fill in the authors, affiliations, title and institutional logos.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enter the pictures using their picture manager. You might have to choose the appropriate size of the pictures (zoom percent). For example, my slides had white space on the borders, which &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.postergenius.com/cms/index.php&#34;&gt;PosterGenius&lt;/a&gt; did not know, so some space was being wasted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Review it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Print it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the following post you can find some pictures from the creation of the poster in question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- Place this tag in your head or just before your close body tag. --&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;https://apis.google.com/js/plusone.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;!-- Place this tag where you want the widget to render. --&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;g-post&#34; data-href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/109750712877885290236/posts/59ZNCeUshK1&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.postergenius.com/cms/index.php&#34;&gt;PosterGenius&lt;/a&gt; has the cool feature of creating a poster, a presentation, and a handout from the same material. For other meetings, I have actually printed out a couple of handouts to give to those interested in the material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it is not free (they have discounts for students), I think that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.postergenius.com/cms/index.php&#34;&gt;PosterGenius&lt;/a&gt; is a very simple to use, produces good looking posters, and their optimal distance to read feature is quite accurate.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
