<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Work-life on L. Collado-Torres</title>
    <link>/tags/work-life/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Work-life on L. Collado-Torres</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2011-2018 Leonardo Collado Torres under (CC) BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/work-life/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>LCG-UNAM 11 years ago</title>
      <link>/2016/03/10/LCGUNAM/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/03/10/LCGUNAM/</guid>
      <description>This has been a busy week. I just flew in last night from #ENAR2016 and I&#39;m getting ready for a postdoc interview tomorrow, which means that I&#39;m also flying today. On the flight back from #ENAR2016 I started reading a book my friend John Muschelli bought for me. It&#39;s called The Happiness Advantage by Shawn Anchor and so far I&#39;m loving it. There are several things that it talks about that I&#39;ve done in the past, but maybe not in the past year.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What are reasonable work hours and salary expectations for biostats/genomics careers?</title>
      <link>/2015/02/12/salary-work-hours-expectations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/02/12/salary-work-hours-expectations/</guid>
      <description>My advisor recently asked me to fill a career planning document (he&#39;ll blog about it at some point) that has lots of questions and is being very useful. Trying to fill answer all these questions has gotten me thinking about other important things for the future. Two of them being reasonable expectations for work hours and salary in a biostats/genomics academic career.
I find these questions hard to answer and even hard to talk about, and if you know me, I&#39;m a person that asks lots of questions.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>