<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>JHU Biostat on L. Collado-Torres</title>
    <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/categories/JHU-Biostat/</link>
    <description>Recent content in JHU Biostat on L. Collado-Torres</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2011-2018 Leonardo Collado Torres under (CC) BY-NC-SA</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://lcolladotor.github.io/categories/JHU-Biostat/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Third Student Cultural Mixer</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/11/20/StudentMixer3/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/11/20/StudentMixer3/</guid>
      <description>Note: the Fall event will be student and post doc only while the Spring event will be open to the whole department. This is to smooth the integration process for the new students. A survey showed that at least some first year students would be more likely to either attend or present if it&#39;s a student-only event.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My strategy for quickly grading homeworks</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/11/08/fast-grading/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/11/08/fast-grading/</guid>
      <description>For the past year and a half I have been a teaching assistant (TA) for the Statistical Methods in Public Health I to IV (140.621 to 140.624) courses. As part of being a TA for these courses, we have to grade between 30 and 50 homeworks every two weeks or so: four problem sets per eight week terms. For example, I now have to grade 37 homeworks:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bmore Biostats is born!</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/11/07/bmorebiostats/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/11/07/bmorebiostats/</guid>
      <description>In recent weeks, I have met with a group of students @jhubiostat interested in blogging about their research, tutorials, pieces of R code, among plenty of other subjects. Within this group we had the idea to aggregate our blogs so it would be easier for others to follow us and to easily promote our own blogs to a much larger audience. Basically, do what R-bloggers does but focused on blogs from students at Johns Hopkins Biostatistics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Epi vs Biostat Kickball match Spring 2013</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/04/24/Epi-vs-Biostat-Kickball-match-Spring-2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/04/24/Epi-vs-Biostat-Kickball-match-Spring-2013/</guid>
      <description>This past Saturday the Epi and Biostat troops met for another fun kickball match. Obviously Biostat beat Epi, yup I know: again! This time the score was 15-8 (according to our bookkeeper and captain John) or 12-8 (according to some in Epi).
There was a hint of a surprise at the beginning when Epi scored two runs in the top of the first inning. However, the tide changed back with a homerun by Rumen.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predicting who will win a NFL match at half time</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/23/Predicting-who-will-win-a-NFL-match-at-half-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/23/Predicting-who-will-win-a-NFL-match-at-half-time/</guid>
      <description>It was great to have a little break, Spring break, although the weather didn&amp;#8217;t feel like spring at all! During the early part of the break I worked on my final project for Jeff Leek&amp;#8217;s data analysis class, which we call 140.753 here. Continuing my previous posts on the topic, this time I&amp;#8217;ll share the results of my final project.
At the beginning of the course, we had to submit a project plan (more like a proposal) and in mine I announced my interest to look into some sports data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analyzing SimplyStatistics visits info</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/09/Analyzing-SimplyStatistics-visits-info/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/09/Analyzing-SimplyStatistics-visits-info/</guid>
      <description>Recently we had to analyze the data of the number of visits per day to SimplyStatistics.org. There were two goals:
Estimate the fraction of visitors retained after a spike in the number of visitors Identify (if any) any factors that influence the fraction estimated in 1. For me it was a fun project in part because I like SimplyStatistics but also because I think that finding the answers to the questions would be interesting and help understand the readers of that blog.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Second cultural mixer today!</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/02/15/Second-cultural-mixer-today/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/02/15/Second-cultural-mixer-today/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sharing my work for &#34;Advanced Methods III&#34;</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/02/13/Sharing-my-work-for-Advanced-Methods-III/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/02/13/Sharing-my-work-for-Advanced-Methods-III/</guid>
      <description>This semester I&amp;#8217;m taking the live version of the Data Analysis class by Jeff Leek. His more popular version of the course is available through Coursera. One of the things that Jeff promotes is reproducibility and sharing code. I share that tendency and thus created a Git repository for my homework and code for the class: lcollado753. I&amp;#8217;m hosting it with GitHub to try it out since I started with Mercurial via Bitbucket.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why aren&#39;t all of our graphs interactive?</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/10/08/Why-arent-all-of-our-graphs-interactive/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/10/08/Why-arent-all-of-our-graphs-interactive/</guid>
      <description>During the last pre-happy hour seminar, Karl Broman talked about Why aren&amp;#8217;t all of our graphs interactive? I didn&amp;#8217;t know, but a few years ago Karl worked in the department and clearly promoted beer-drinking and is the heart of the department. I&amp;#8217;m a fan of our pre-happy hour seminars since you have a get to listen to good/fun talks over a beer or two.
But I&amp;#8217;m also a fan of reproducible research and useful graphics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>JHSPH-Biostat through Coursera</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/10/01/JHSPH-Biostat-through-Coursera/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/10/01/JHSPH-Biostat-through-Coursera/</guid>
      <description>Have you heard of online education? If you are in the US or Mexico I&amp;#8217;m sure that you have seen some ads about online universities. Well, that&amp;#8217;s not the type of education I&amp;#8217;m talking about. I&amp;#8217;m talking about free high-quality education. For some years, the top option has been the Open Courseware (OCW) organized under the Open Courseware Consortium (OCWC). Back in 2009 I was pushed my undergrad (LCG-UNAM) to design and teach OCW-compliant courses.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quid @Biostat-JHSPH</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/09/28/Quid-Biostat-JHSPH/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/09/28/Quid-Biostat-JHSPH/</guid>
      <description>Just like most scientific departments, we have a seminar (weekly over here) where very bright people come to us to talk about their work. Being a Biostatistics department, we mostly get faculty from other Biostatistics departments from universities to talk to us. This week was quite different. Amy Heineike from Quid gave us a talk describing their product, which fits perfectly in what is now called &amp;#8220;data science&amp;#8221;. You can see Amy at the end of the table in the picture below.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing Git while making your academic webpage</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/09/24/Introducing-Git-while-making-your-academic-webpage/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/09/24/Introducing-Git-while-making-your-academic-webpage/</guid>
      <description>Last week I gave a presentation during our computing club on how to use git (a version control system). I used as a motivating example the first steps of creating your own academic webpage. The goal was to make it interesting to both new students (who might have been more interested on the webpage part) and older students (for whom version control should be a must). The slides and all the material is publicly available through the following Bitbucket repository: https://bitbucket.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting up your computer for bioinformatics/biostatistics and a compedium of resources</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/08/23/setting-up-your-computer-for/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/08/23/setting-up-your-computer-for/</guid>
      <description>Jumping on the train set by Hilary Parker &amp;#8220;The Setup (Part 1)&#34; and Alyssa Frazee &amp;#8220;my software/hardware setup&amp;#8221;, I&amp;#8217;m going to share my setup and hopefully add something new. They both did a great job already, so make sure you read their posts!
I have some experience with all three main OS: Windows, Linux and Mac. That being said, I know some of the basic stuff for each but I surely use Google very frequently to get help.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>