<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Industry on L. Collado-Torres</title>
    <link>/tags/Industry/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Industry on L. Collado-Torres</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2011-2018 Leonardo Collado Torres under (CC) BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/Industry/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning about social networks through an interactive presentation</title>
      <link>/2012/09/28/learning-about-social-networks-through-an-interactive/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/09/28/learning-about-social-networks-through-an-interactive/</guid>
      <description>During this week&amp;#8217;s journal club meeting Hilary Parker (homepage, blog) led the session on &amp;#8220;Identifying influential and susceptible members of social networks&amp;#8221;. Were there some speakers or why did she &amp;#8220;lead the session&amp;#8221;? By this I mean that Hilary tried a very different (and interesting) format this time. Instead of giving a talk, not a formal one like at seminars, she prepared a short presentation (publicly available here) that begins showing a 20 minute video.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simply Statistics: Why statisticians should join and launch startups</title>
      <link>/2012/01/24/simply-statistics-why-statisticians-should-join-and/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/01/24/simply-statistics-why-statisticians-should-join-and/</guid>
      <description>Simply Statistics: Why statisticians should join and launch startupsI really like this post in SimplyStatistics by leekgroup. The topic is worth considering, but what got me hooked was the list of links to startups, which were all new to me. 100plus looks promising, though I don&amp;#8217;t have a clue as to what they are going to offer. Sure, I know the general topic, but not much beyond that. As I just flew back to town, Flightcaster and Hipmunk caught my attention.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>