<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Fun on L. Collado-Torres</title>
    <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/tags/Fun/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Fun on L. Collado-Torres</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2011-2018 Leonardo Collado Torres under (CC) BY-NC-SA</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://lcolladotor.github.io/tags/Fun/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>LCG-UNAM 11 years ago</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2016/03/10/LCGUNAM/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2016/03/10/LCGUNAM/</guid>
      <description>This has been a busy week. I just flew in last night from #ENAR2016 and I&#39;m getting ready for a postdoc interview tomorrow, which means that I&#39;m also flying today. On the flight back from #ENAR2016 I started reading a book my friend John Muschelli bought for me. It&#39;s called The Happiness Advantage by Shawn Anchor and so far I&#39;m loving it. There are several things that it talks about that I&#39;ve done in the past, but maybe not in the past year.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Automatically coloring your R output in the terminal using colorout</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2014/02/17/colorout/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2014/02/17/colorout/</guid>
      <description>Thanks to Alyssa Frazee I just learned about the colorout package (Aquino, 2013). It modifies R so that the output is in different colors, making it much more pleasant to use R in the terminal.
Do note that colorout is not available from CRAN, but you can easily install by following the instructions on the colorout site (Official site) reproduced below:
download.file(&amp;quot;http://www.lepem.ufc.br/jaa/colorout_1.0-2.tar.gz&amp;quot;, destfile = &amp;quot;colorout_1.0-2.tar.gz&amp;quot;) install.packages(&amp;quot;colorout_1.0-2.tar.gz&amp;quot;, type = &amp;quot;source&amp;quot;, repos = NULL)  The next step is to then load colorout automatically when I start R.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>rMaps released</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2014/02/10/rMaps-released/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2014/02/10/rMaps-released/</guid>
      <description>Ramnath Vaidyanathan just released his new R interactive package, rMaps (Vaidyanathan, 2014). The packages relies on the development version of his widely known rCharts package (Vaidyanathan, 2013) as well as javascript libraries that specialize in maps. If you don&#39;t know Ramnath, he is one of the most active R developers out there!! You can see that from his GitHub profile.
The package is very new and still under development, but I bet that Ramnath released it to get us users excited and maybe find some helpful hands to document it and further develop it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Third Student Cultural Mixer</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/11/20/StudentMixer3/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/11/20/StudentMixer3/</guid>
      <description>Note: the Fall event will be student and post doc only while the Spring event will be open to the whole department. This is to smooth the integration process for the new students. A survey showed that at least some first year students would be more likely to either attend or present if it&#39;s a student-only event.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Epi vs Biostat Kickball match Spring 2013</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/04/24/Epi-vs-Biostat-Kickball-match-Spring-2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/04/24/Epi-vs-Biostat-Kickball-match-Spring-2013/</guid>
      <description>This past Saturday the Epi and Biostat troops met for another fun kickball match. Obviously Biostat beat Epi, yup I know: again! This time the score was 15-8 (according to our bookkeeper and captain John) or 12-8 (according to some in Epi).
There was a hint of a surprise at the beginning when Epi scored two runs in the top of the first inning. However, the tide changed back with a homerun by Rumen.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Second cultural mixer today!</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/02/15/Second-cultural-mixer-today/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/02/15/Second-cultural-mixer-today/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>