<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>LaTeX | L. Collado-Torres</title>
    <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/tags/latex/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://lcolladotor.github.io/tags/latex/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>LaTeX</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2011-2021. All thoughts and opinions here are my own. The icon was designed by [Mauricio Guzmán](https://www.linkedin.com/in/mauricio-guzman-6529b551/) and is inspired by [Huichol culture](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Huichol); it represents my community building interests</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://lcolladotor.github.io/images/icon_hu2b32c4ab415f12f472f73c7b0301b0d1_19400_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>LaTeX</title>
      <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/tags/latex/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to write academic documents with GoogleDocs</title>
      <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2019/04/02/how-to-write-academic-documents-with-googledocs/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2019/04/02/how-to-write-academic-documents-with-googledocs/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;These past months I’ve been mostly working on one &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; project which might be close to an end, hopefully! This project involves a massive manuscript with many supplementary figures and tables. Today we sent it out to other members in our team, and to celebrate, I’m now writing more 😅: though this is a blog post. I’m allowing myself to do so before I dive into the pile of tasks I haven’t completed&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. So I’m going to share with you the tools I’ve been using since 2018 or so for writing academic documents shared via &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/document/u/0/&#34;&gt;Google Docs&lt;/a&gt;. You can use these tools for manuscripts&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, capstone projects&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and well, basically any document where you want to do any of the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automatic figure/table numbering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Insert math equations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cite the literature&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, you can do both with &lt;code&gt;LaTeX&lt;/code&gt; and you can collaborate with others using &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.overleaf.com&#34;&gt;Overleaf&lt;/a&gt;, but it’s really hard to convince others to use &lt;code&gt;LaTeX&lt;/code&gt; in my experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;citations&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Citations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many tools out there for you to organize the literature items you are reading or keeping tabs on. Some of them are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zotero.org/&#34;&gt;Zotero&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mendeley.com/&#34;&gt;Mendeley&lt;/a&gt;, which you might have heard about. The one that I highly recommend for writing documents with Google Docs is &lt;a href=&#34;https://f1000.com/work/&#34;&gt;F1000Workspace&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;get-an-account&#34; class=&#34;section level4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Get an account&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, you need to make an account. Worried about paying? Don’t worry, the accounts are &lt;strong&gt;free&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2019-04-02-how-to-write-academic-documents-with-googledocs_files/Screen%20Shot%202019-04-02%20at%205.37.26%20PM.png&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I strongly recommend that you use your academic email here if you have one, because I believe that it grants you access for an unlimited free account. Your university might also give you free access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;start-a-project&#34; class=&#34;section level4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Start a project&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have your account set up, start a &lt;em&gt;shared project&lt;/em&gt;. I mean, private ones also work, but shared ones allow you to collaborate with others so that your teammembers can also update the citations in your document. For example, we have one called &lt;code&gt;brainseq phase2&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2019-04-02-how-to-write-academic-documents-with-googledocs_files/Screen%20Shot%202019-04-02%20at%205.36.15%20PM.png&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2019-04-02-how-to-write-academic-documents-with-googledocs_files/Screen%20Shot%202019-04-02%20at%205.36.54%20PM.png&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you open your project page, at the top left you’ll see a big blue button called &lt;code&gt;Import References&lt;/code&gt;. Click on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2019-04-02-how-to-write-academic-documents-with-googledocs_files/Screen%20Shot%202019-04-02%20at%205.43.57%20PM.png&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, F1000Workspace allows you to import references from many different sources. I typically import using identifiers, either a &lt;code&gt;DOI&lt;/code&gt; or a &lt;code&gt;PMID&lt;/code&gt; one. They also have a browser add-on that you can use to import references into your library when using websites such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed&#34;&gt;PubMed&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;insert-references-into-a-google-doc&#34; class=&#34;section level4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Insert references into a Google Doc&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On your Google Chrome browser, install the F1000Workspace Google Docs add-on available &lt;a href=&#34;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/f1000/daojhpgpccggokldfgfdmeckecckheej?utm_source=permalink&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Next, open up your Google Doc and you’ll see that &lt;code&gt;F1000&lt;/code&gt; appears in your toolbar. If you click on it, the F1000 interface will open on the right sidebar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2019-04-02-how-to-write-academic-documents-with-googledocs_files/Screen%20Shot%202019-04-02%20at%205.54.46%20PM.png&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That interface lets you link your Google Doc to a particular F1000Workspace project, which I recommend doing. You can then go to &lt;code&gt;Insert citations&lt;/code&gt; and start searching your project citations. I typically search by name or by the identifier, which is particularly useful if I just added the reference to the project via the identifier on a separate browser tab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2019-04-02-how-to-write-academic-documents-with-googledocs_files/Screen%20Shot%202019-04-02%20at%205.54.10%20PM.png&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;update-your-documents-bibliography&#34; class=&#34;section level4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Update your document’s bibliography&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lets say that you’ve added a few citations in your document and now want to format them appropriately. In your Google Doc, click on &lt;code&gt;F1000&lt;/code&gt;, then navigate to the &lt;code&gt;Format citations and bibliography&lt;/code&gt; section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2019-04-02-how-to-write-academic-documents-with-googledocs_files/Screen%20Shot%202019-04-02%20at%205.57.12%20PM.png&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before you click the big blue button that says &lt;code&gt;Update citations and bibliography&lt;/code&gt; you’ll notice a dropdown menu that lets you choose your favorite citation style (or whichever the journal you want to send your manuscript requires).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The end!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;notes&#34; class=&#34;section level4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Notes&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, not really. You’ll likely keep adding many citations as you keep working on your document. One thing that I’ve noticed is that the F1000Workspace add-on has a bit of trouble under “suggesting” mode or when the citation was inserted as a suggestion. So I recommend that you accept the suggestion first, then use “editing” mode for updating your bibliography file. It’s always good to keep an eye on what the add-on is doing so you can notice anything weird and undo it with ctrl + z (cmd + z in macOS).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And hey, did you know that F1000Workspace also works with Microsoft Word?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more details, check the &lt;a href=&#34;https://f1000.com/work/#/faq/google-docs-add-on&#34;&gt;FAQs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://player.vimeo.com/video/153753002&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; title=&#34;vimeo video&#34; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://player.vimeo.com/video/141798183&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; title=&#34;vimeo video&#34; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;automatic-figure-numbering&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Automatic figure numbering&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we have figured out citations in Google Docs, lets learn how to cross reference figures, tables, equations, and whatever else you want. This is something that &lt;code&gt;LaTeX&lt;/code&gt; users are familiar with but that you can’t do out of the box in Google Docs or Microsoft Word (as far as I know). Luckily others have made add-ons that solve this problem. The one I use, and so do other 11,197 people as of today, is &lt;code&gt;Cross Reference&lt;/code&gt; available from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/cross-reference/hknkaiempgninehdhkgekoeoilkapgob?utm_source=permalink&#34;&gt;Google Chrome Store&lt;/a&gt; for free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This add-on allows the user to label equations, figures and tables and refer to them within the text. It now also allows users to create labels for any element. These elements are numbered automatically and references are updated to match. If their order changes, references update to match. If one is removed, references to it are highlighted in red in the text. The text and style of references and labels can be customised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Insert labels and references as hyperlinks. Instead of a URL, add a code recognised by Cross Reference, then an underscore, then your choice of name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;configuration&#34; class=&#34;section level4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Configuration&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you install &lt;code&gt;Cross Reference&lt;/code&gt;, you’ll see it listed under the &lt;code&gt;Add-ons&lt;/code&gt; menu in your Google Doc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2019-04-02-how-to-write-academic-documents-with-googledocs_files/Screen%20Shot%202019-04-02%20at%206.12.03%20PM.png&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll see all the different types of elements that you have configured with &lt;code&gt;Cross Reference&lt;/code&gt;. Some come out of the box, like &lt;code&gt;Figures&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2019-04-02-how-to-write-academic-documents-with-googledocs_files/Screen%20Shot%202019-04-02%20at%206.14.07%20PM.png&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For every element you have to configure the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The code you will use for the label, here &lt;code&gt;#figur&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The text that will be displayed before the number. In this case, &lt;code&gt;Figure&lt;/code&gt; (yes, there’s a space there).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The style of the label; bold here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then the same thing for the reference. In this case, the code for the reference is &lt;code&gt;#fig&lt;/code&gt;. The codes have to be at least 3 characters long for the references and 5 characters long for the labels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my documents I typically add configurations for supplementary figures and tables using:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th&gt;type&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;code: label&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;code: reference&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;text&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Supplementary Figure&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;#sfigu&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;#sfi&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;Figure S&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Supplementary Table&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;#stabl&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;#sta&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;Table S&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Supplementary File&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;#supfi&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;#sup&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;Supplementary File&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;usage&#34; class=&#34;section level4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Usage&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that you have configured &lt;code&gt;Cross Reference&lt;/code&gt; you can start using it. Lets say that I want to write the text &lt;code&gt;We did many things (Figure S1)&lt;/code&gt; where &lt;code&gt;Figure S1&lt;/code&gt; links to my overview figure whose description starts &lt;code&gt;Figure S1. Overview of my project&lt;/code&gt;. Since we are talking about the overview figure, lets use &lt;code&gt;_overview&lt;/code&gt; as the unique identifier for this figure. As this is a supplementary figure, the label code is &lt;code&gt;#sfigu&lt;/code&gt; and the reference code is &lt;code&gt;#sfi&lt;/code&gt;. Meaning that we must write the label code once in the figure description using &lt;code&gt;#sfigu_overview&lt;/code&gt; and we can reference to it as many times as we want using &lt;code&gt;#sfi_overview&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last tricky part is that you can write whatever you want, lets say &lt;code&gt;hello&lt;/code&gt;, and then you need to create a link (shortcut is cmd + k in macOS) with the correct code (either the reference or the label one). So the text that you would write would be &lt;code&gt;We did many things ([hello](#sfi_overview))&lt;/code&gt; and later on when you describe the overview figure you need &lt;code&gt;[whatever you want](#sfi_overview). Overview of my project&lt;/code&gt; where here I’m using the Markdown syntax for links: &lt;code&gt;[text](link)&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve inserted the links both for the reference and the label, you can then go to &lt;code&gt;Add-ons&lt;/code&gt;, navigate to &lt;code&gt;Cross Reference&lt;/code&gt; and click &lt;code&gt;Update document&lt;/code&gt;. Doing so will change the text you had initially filed in for the correct text. So it will look like this: &lt;code&gt;We did many things ([Figure S1](#sfi_overview))&lt;/code&gt; plus &lt;code&gt;[Figure S1](#sfi_overview). Overview of my project&lt;/code&gt;. Here’s a real case example where my identifier for the first supplementary figure is &lt;code&gt;_rna&lt;/code&gt;, thus the full reference code is &lt;code&gt;#sfi_rna&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2019-04-02-how-to-write-academic-documents-with-googledocs_files/Screen%20Shot%202019-04-02%20at%206.32.29%20PM.png&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And you are done!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;notes-1&#34; class=&#34;section level4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Notes&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number used for the item your reference depends on what order the reference codes are listed in the Google Doc. To check that the numbering order is correct (Table S1 appears in the text before Table S2, etc), I recommend opening your google document in two separate tabs. In one tab, you start reading your document from the top. If you encounter items out of order, then on tab two you can switch them around. That way you don’t have to scroll around and waste time, which is a more cumbersome problem as the document gets longer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, this process that takes a bit of time and can break due to a typo. So I highly recommend that you update your cross references as soon as you make a new one, so you can easily trace any typos and fix them easily. If you don’t, then it can become very hard to track down what went wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;equations&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Equations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, lets say that you want to insert equations. You can insert some equations with Google Docs, but you might want more fine control. If you use &lt;code&gt;LaTeX&lt;/code&gt; I recommend the &lt;code&gt;Auto-LaTeX Equations&lt;/code&gt; add-on available from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/auto-latex-equations/iaainhiejkciadlhlodaajgbffkebdog?utm_source=permalink&#34;&gt;Google Chrome Store&lt;/a&gt; for free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This add-on lets you automatically convert every LaTeX equation in your document into beautiful images! Simply enclose your math equations within &lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[ ... \]&lt;/span&gt; and click the button in the sidebar, and all of your equations will be rendered in LaTeX!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s as simple as it sounds. What this add-on does is that it takes your &lt;code&gt;LaTeX&lt;/code&gt; equation code, renders an image with the equation, and then inserts it back into your Google Doc. It also enables you to restore the &lt;code&gt;LaTeX&lt;/code&gt; equation code so you can edit it if you find a typo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;wrapping-up&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Wrapping up&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope that you’ll find this blog post / tutorial useful when writing your own academic documents. These tools have saved me so much time when writing academic documents in collaboration with others. I don’t want to imagine having to re-number all the references manually whenever we added each of the 48 supplementary figures, 17 supplementary tables, and 11 equations to the project we are about to complete 😱.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;acknowledgments&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Acknowledgments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors of F1000Workspace, Cross Reference and Auto-LaTeX equations add-ons have made my life much easier. THANK YOU!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog post was made possible thanks to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://bioconductor.org/packages/3.10/BiocStyle&#34;&gt;BiocStyle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Oles_2020&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://github.com/Bioconductor/BiocStyle&#39;&gt;Oleś, Morgan, and Huber, 2020&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=blogdown&#34;&gt;blogdown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Xie_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&#39;&gt;Xie, Hill, and Thomas, 2017&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&#34;&gt;knitcitations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Boettiger_2019&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&#39;&gt;Boettiger, 2019&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=sessioninfo&#34;&gt;sessioninfo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Csardi_2018&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=sessioninfo&#39;&gt;Csárdi, core, Wickham, Chang, et al., 2018&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;references&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Boettiger_2019&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Boettiger_2019&#34;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt;
C. Boettiger.
&lt;em&gt;knitcitations: Citations for ‘Knitr’ Markdown Files&lt;/em&gt;.
R package version 1.0.10.
2019.
URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Csardi_2018&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Csardi_2018&#34;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt;
G. Csárdi, R. core, H. Wickham, W. Chang, et al.
&lt;em&gt;sessioninfo: R Session Information&lt;/em&gt;.
R package version 1.1.1.
2018.
URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=sessioninfo&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=sessioninfo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Oles_2020&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Oles_2020&#34;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt;
A. Oleś, M. Morgan, and W. Huber.
&lt;em&gt;BiocStyle: Standard styles for vignettes and other Bioconductor documents&lt;/em&gt;.
R package version 2.14.4.
2020.
URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Bioconductor/BiocStyle&#34;&gt;https://github.com/Bioconductor/BiocStyle&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Xie_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Xie_2017&#34;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt;
Y. Xie, A. P. Hill, and A. Thomas.
&lt;em&gt;blogdown: Creating Websites with R Markdown&lt;/em&gt;.
ISBN 978-0815363729.
Boca Raton, Florida: Chapman and Hall/CRC, 2017.
URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&#34;&gt;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;reproducibility&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reproducibility&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## ─ Session info ───────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────
##  setting  value                       
##  version  R version 3.6.2 (2019-12-12)
##  os       macOS Catalina 10.15.2      
##  system   x86_64, darwin15.6.0        
##  ui       X11                         
##  language (EN)                        
##  collate  en_US.UTF-8                 
##  ctype    en_US.UTF-8                 
##  tz       America/New_York            
##  date     2020-02-12                  
## 
## ─ Packages ───────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────
##  package       * version date       lib source                            
##  assertthat      0.2.1   2019-03-21 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  bibtex          0.4.2.2 2020-01-02 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  BiocManager     1.30.10 2019-11-16 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.1)                    
##  BiocStyle     * 2.14.4  2020-01-09 [1] Bioconductor                      
##  blogdown        0.17    2019-11-13 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.1)                    
##  bookdown        0.17    2020-01-11 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  cli             2.0.1   2020-01-08 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  colorout      * 1.2-1   2019-05-07 [1] Github (jalvesaq/colorout@7ea9440)
##  crayon          1.3.4   2017-09-16 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  digest          0.6.23  2019-11-23 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  evaluate        0.14    2019-05-28 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  fansi           0.4.1   2020-01-08 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  glue            1.3.1   2019-03-12 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  htmltools       0.4.0   2019-10-04 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  httr            1.4.1   2019-08-05 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  jsonlite        1.6     2018-12-07 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  knitcitations * 1.0.10  2019-09-15 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  knitr           1.27    2020-01-16 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  lubridate       1.7.4   2018-04-11 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  magrittr        1.5     2014-11-22 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  plyr            1.8.5   2019-12-10 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  R6              2.4.1   2019-11-12 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.1)                    
##  Rcpp            1.0.3   2019-11-08 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  RefManageR      1.2.12  2019-04-03 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  rlang           0.4.3   2020-01-24 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.2)                    
##  rmarkdown       2.1     2020-01-20 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  sessioninfo   * 1.1.1   2018-11-05 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  stringi         1.4.5   2020-01-11 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  stringr         1.4.0   2019-02-10 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  withr           2.1.2   2018-03-15 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  xfun            0.12    2020-01-13 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  xml2            1.2.2   2019-08-09 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  yaml            2.2.0   2018-07-25 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
## 
## [1] /Library/Frameworks/R.framework/Versions/3.6/Resources/library&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Including answering some questions on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://support.bioconductor.org/&#34;&gt;Bioconductor support forum&lt;/a&gt;, finishing another manuscript, etc.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Like this &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2018/09/26/426213&#34;&gt;one&lt;/a&gt; or this other &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2018/09/29/428391&#34;&gt;one&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Like my former student &lt;a href=&#34;https://amy-peterson.github.io/&#34;&gt;Amy Peterson&lt;/a&gt; did in 2018.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn4&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;For up to 3 projects.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting up your computer for bioinformatics/biostatistics and a compedium of resources</title>
      <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/08/23/setting-up-your-computer-for/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/08/23/setting-up-your-computer-for/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Jumping on the train set by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu/~hiparker/&#34;&gt;Hilary Parker&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#8220;&lt;a href=&#34;http://hilaryparker.com/2012/08/16/the-setup-part-1/&#34;&gt;The Setup (Part 1)&lt;/a&gt;&#34; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://biostat.jhsph.edu/~afrazee/&#34;&gt;Alyssa Frazee&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#8220;&lt;a href=&#34;http://alyssafrazee.wordpress.com/&#34;&gt;my software/hardware setup&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8221;, I&amp;#8217;m going to share my setup and hopefully add something new. They both did a great job already, so make sure you read their posts!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have some experience with all three main OS: Windows, Linux and Mac. That being said, I know some of the basic stuff for each but I surely use Google very frequently to get help. I used to have a dual Windows / Linux (Ubuntu) set up but now I have a Windows laptop/desktop (it&amp;#8217;s a monster :P) at home and I&amp;#8217;m happy working with my Mac. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m going to start by mentioning the software I use(d) in each OS and then add some other tools that I really like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Windows&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Text editor: &lt;a href=&#34;http://notepad-plus-plus.org/&#34;&gt;Notepad++&lt;/a&gt;. It outperforms Notepad by light years! A must for me is the “View -&amp;gt; Word wrap” option. I would definitely go to “Settings -&amp;gt; Preferences -&amp;gt; New Document/Default Directory” and change the new document format from Windows (Dos) to Unix. This will save you time later when you want to work on a Unix system like the cluster. If you didn’t, you can change a specific document’s EOL (end of line) by using “Edit -&amp;gt; EOL conversion -&amp;gt; UNIX format”. Another feature that I like is the “Search -&amp;gt; Replace…” which allows you to use regular expressions (like Perl). &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Statistical software: &lt;a href=&#34;http://cran.r-project.org/&#34;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt; of course! It’s best to do a custom installation and choose a directory without spaces in it. That will help later (further below). If you want to be convinced to join the R community read &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2009/01/07/technology/business-computing/07program.html?_r=3&amp;amp;scp=1&amp;amp;sq=robert%20gentleman&amp;amp;st=cse&#34;&gt;Data Analysits Captivated by R’s power&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://bits.blogs.nytimes.com/2009/01/08/r-you-ready-for-r/?scp=1&amp;amp;sq=Robert%20Gentleman&amp;amp;st=cse&#34;&gt;R You Ready for R?&lt;/a&gt; or just take a look at what others are using. Remember that the R project is open source, free and easy to contribute to. If you end up choosing Excel as your statistical software, well, there is &lt;strong&gt;no&lt;/strong&gt; hope for you!!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;R code editor: Notepad++ with &lt;a href=&#34;http://sourceforge.net/projects/npptor/&#34;&gt;NppToR&lt;/a&gt;. For a long time I used Emacs modified to work with Windows by Vincent Goulet available &lt;a href=&#34;http://vgoulet.act.ulaval.ca/en/emacs/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It works great and saves you quite a bit of setup time. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xemacs.org/&#34;&gt;XEmacs&lt;/a&gt; is another option that a friend of mine used, but it never convinced me. Anyhow, I ended up changing from Emacs to Notepad++ with NppToR because I could:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Force quit R (and not lose code changes) in case I crashed R by doing something stupid like printing something huge or w/e :P &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Access help pages in a separate window. I’m sure you can do it too with Emacs, but I was just lazy to configure it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shorter shortcuts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Later on I found the NppToR to PuTTy feature which is very useful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can create an R syntax dictionary (or something like that) in Notepad++ which will scan all your R packages and add the function names so they are colored when you type them. Also Notepad++ will auto-complete some function names and show you the arguments. Great stuff! (Forgot the name, so… google it :P)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SSH: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/putty/&#34;&gt;PuTTY&lt;/a&gt;. As said before, works well with Notepad++ and NppToR.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SCP: &lt;a href=&#34;http://winscp.net/eng/index.php&#34;&gt;WinSCP&lt;/a&gt;. There are others that work too like &lt;a href=&#34;http://filezilla-project.org/&#34;&gt;Filezilla&lt;/a&gt; but well, WinSCP does the job well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PDF viewer: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.adobe.com/products/acrobatpro.html&#34;&gt;Adobe Acrobat Professional&lt;/a&gt;. I’m using the X version now. I like how I can highlight, underline, cross out, free hand, sticky note, combine files into a single pdf, combine pdfs, and change the highlight colors easily. It also has a change tracker (kind of like Word has). I’ve seen other use PDF Annotator which is available for free for Hopkins students. Anyhow, I simply love Acrobat for reading papers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LaTeX: &lt;a href=&#34;http://miktex.org/&#34;&gt;MiKTeX&lt;/a&gt;. For writing TeX files I used either Emacs or Notepad++. There is another software which has drop down menus and the like called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.winedt.com/&#34;&gt;WinEdt&lt;/a&gt;. I got used to typing LaTeX from scratch, well, I have a template.Rnw somewhere. Oh yeah, I always use Sweave when writing TeX files (even if I don’t use R). &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;R reports: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.statistik.lmu.de/~leisch/Sweave/&#34;&gt;Sweave by Friedrich Leisch&lt;/a&gt;, one of the champions of reproducibility! To learn more about Sweave first &lt;a href=&#34;http://stat.epfl.ch/webdav/site/stat/shared/Regression/EPFL-Sweave-powerdot.pdf&#34;&gt;read this pdf&lt;/a&gt; by Nicola Sartori. This is another &lt;a href=&#34;http://users.stat.umn.edu/~geyer/Sweave/foo.pdf&#34;&gt;Sweave demo&lt;/a&gt; by Charles J Geyer. Check out this great &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.johndcook.com/troubleshooting_sweave.html&#34;&gt;Windows Sweave troubleshooting page&lt;/a&gt; by John D Cook.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Building R packages from source. You will definitely need &lt;a href=&#34;http://cran.fhcrc.org/bin/windows/Rtools/&#34;&gt;Rtools&lt;/a&gt; installed. I would also install &lt;a href=&#34;http://qpdf.sourceforge.net/&#34;&gt;QPDF&lt;/a&gt; which can be used by R to compress your pdf files, which is a good thing if you want to have a small-sized tarball. Last but not least, check out &lt;a href=&#34;http://robjhyndman.com/researchtips/building-r-packages-for-windows/&#34;&gt;Building R packages for Windows&lt;/a&gt; by Rob J Hyndman.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn to modify your PATH! Check 1.3 from the previous link by Rob J Hyndman. If you are going to use Sweave, it’s best to add to your PATH the path for the directory containing your Sweave.sty file so that you won’t need to copy it to every single directory. This is why it pays off to do an R custom installation and put it in C:/R/R-current-version or something like that instead of C:/Program Files/ bla bla with spaces. It used to be more important a few years ago. Also, I created a sw.bat file and put it somewhere where my PATH would find it. That sw.bat file ran Sweave, pdflatex twice, then bibtex and finally opened the pdf file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PDF viewer for LaTeX files. I only learnt about pdf sync and the like a year ago. You should google how to set this up with SumatraPDF (Adobe Acrobat doesn’t work!).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Version control: &lt;a href=&#34;http://mercurial.selenic.com/&#34;&gt;Mercurial&lt;/a&gt;. It’s very easy to use and you can get an account at &lt;a href=&#34;https://bitbucket.org/&#34;&gt;Bitbucket.org&lt;/a&gt; with unlimited number of private repositories if you have an academic email. Even if you are not doing a collaborative project, you will love using a version control system! It will clean up your directories very nicely and will help you become more organized. Learning a few commands is nothing compared to having lots of files with _v1 v_2, etc at the end. Check out the &lt;a href=&#34;http://mercurial.selenic.com/guide/&#34;&gt;Mercurial guide&lt;/a&gt; to get started. Note that for windows instead of customizing your .hgrc file you will customize a mercurial.ini file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Presentations: both PowerPoint and &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beamer_(LaTeX)&#34;&gt;Beamer&lt;/a&gt; (normally with Sweave too). Rarely I use &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com&#34;&gt;Google Docs&lt;/a&gt; for this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Office: Either Microsoft Office or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.openoffice.org/&#34;&gt;OpenOffice&lt;/a&gt; (free).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Poster creator: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.postergenius.com/cms/index.php&#34;&gt;PosterGenius&lt;/a&gt; (academic discount price). It was very easy to use and I would surely give the free trial version a go. It adds a watermark, but well, you will appreciate the time you save compared to using PowerPoint. I guess that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.adobe.com/products/photoshop.html&#34;&gt;Adobe Photoshop&lt;/a&gt; is another option, but I’ve only used it to edit photos here and there, not to make a whole poster. The most I did was create &lt;a href=&#34;https://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/NUiUno0H6MZ8dfTN8ZqF9yRO-Af4bmaijyeT4dbBml0?feat=embedwebsite&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To de-compress RAR files: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.win-rar.com/start.html?&amp;amp;L=0&#34;&gt;WinRAR&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anti-spyware: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.avast.com/free-antivirus-download&#34;&gt;Avast&lt;/a&gt; (free version). I normally keep it in silent (gaming) mode so it doesn’t show pop ups.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cccp-project.net/&#34;&gt;CCCP codec pack&lt;/a&gt; which includes the Media Player Classic. Great for watching video files and dumping the crappy Windows Media Player.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Linux (Ubuntu)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu provides Linux distributions that are very user friendly and that look much like Mac OS does now. You&amp;#8217;ll find it easy to run multi-core programs which were a pain to do with Windows. Beware that even if you use Ubuntu you will need to learn stuff like how to compile. Also, please check before you install that your computer is supported. For example, some laptops with very new video cards might not work properly. That being said, with Ubuntu you will feel very at ease working in an area like mine (genomics) because a lot of the software runs in Linux (normally in a cluster, but you can test in your lap).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will want to check and/or keep for reference &lt;a href=&#34;http://faculty.ucr.edu/~tgirke/Documents/UNIX/linux_manual.html&#34;&gt;LINUX Essentials&lt;/a&gt; by Thomas Girke (more from him below), &lt;a href=&#34;http://freeengineer.org/learnUNIXin10minutes.html&#34;&gt;Learn Linux in 10 minutes&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.linux-tutorial.info/toc&#34;&gt;The Linux tutorial&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.basicconfig.com/linux/vi&#34;&gt;Linux vi editor tutorial&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
* If you are going to use Linux (Ubuntu) at some point you will want to compile something from source and find out that you are missing a dependency. That&amp;#8217;s when I google, then use&amp;#160;:
1. apt-cache search something
2. sudo apt-get install something 
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Note that you will frequently need the yyyy-devel version which includes c headers and stuff that you need to compile.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will find a lot of things through the package installer (forgot what it’s called). Learn the pseudonym for your Ubuntu version so you select the appropriate version of the software in case that you are downloading it from another place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SSH/SCP: terminal commands :) I just wanted to mention that rsync is a nice command for synching folders (recursively too) between your computer and say the cluster.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Version control: Mercurial again. The configuration file is .hgrc not mercurial.ini&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Text editor: Nedit or Emacs. Vi when doing in-terminal modifications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can get R through aptitude or if you want the very latest (or a devel version) you’ll have to compile it. The first time you will have to install plenty of dependencies, but it’s good practice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Office: go with OpenOffice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LaTeX: install the texlive distribution. I normally get everything so that later when I’m trying to use a TeX package I won’t have to go install it (which is what MiKTeX does for you in Windows). &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Video player: VLC.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mac&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Terminal: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iterm2.com&#34;&gt;iTerm2&lt;/a&gt;. Mac comes with a native terminal, but iTerm2 has other nice functions like tabs and more options to customize it. Check &lt;a href=&#34;http://code.google.com/p/iterm2/wiki/ColorGallery&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; for free color palettes. I like the Homebrew one from &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mbadolato/iTerm2-Color-Schemes&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LaTeX and R editor: &lt;a href=&#34;http://aquamacs.org/&#34;&gt;Aquamacs&lt;/a&gt; is a version of Emacs that works great. However, as I discussed in the Windows section I’m moving away from Emacs. Well, to be honest, I don’t want to put the time to learn how to customize Emacs properly and do amazing stuff with it like Kasper does. Recently (since June) I’ve been using &lt;a href=&#34;http://macromates.com/&#34;&gt;TextMate&lt;/a&gt;. It has this thing called “Bundles” which provides different hotkeys depending on the file you are editing. Meaning that for Rnw files you can Sweave them directly there and for R files you can either send the code to R or to the terminal (much like Notepad++). The one thing is that it is not free BUT there is a 2.0 alpha release &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/textmate/textmate&#34;&gt;available on github&lt;/a&gt; that you can compile. &lt;a href=&#34;http://developers.slashdot.org/story/12/08/09/1947234/textmate-2-released-as-open-source&#34;&gt;This lengthly discussion&lt;/a&gt; can be worth reading if you want to know more about the 2.0 version and the future of TextMate. Someone said there that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sublimetext.com/&#34;&gt;Sublime&lt;/a&gt; might be replacing TextMate but I haven’t looked for any R integration in it. Anyhow, I liked how TextMate included an auto-spell checker that recognizes Sweave/LaTeX code from the box :)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Package installer: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.macports.org/&#34;&gt;MacPorts&lt;/a&gt;. It’s kind of similar to aptitude from Linux but it’s Mac only. Note that you will definitely need to get &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.apple.com/xcode/&#34;&gt;XCode&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PDF viewer: also Adobe Acrobat Pro for the reasons mentioned previously.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PDF viewer for LaTeX: TeXShop which I think comes with the MacTeX distribution. It has the forward sync that Alyssa mentions in her blog.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Text editor: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.barebones.com/products/TextWrangler/&#34;&gt;TextWrangler&lt;/a&gt;. Has several of the functions I talked about in the Notepad++ section like search and replace with regular expressions. It definitely outperforms the native text editor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SCP: &lt;a href=&#34;http://cyberduck.ch&#34;&gt;Cyberduck&lt;/a&gt;. I haven’t tried others, but it works and I’m happy with it. I also use the terminal to push/retrieve files like I would do in Linux. Same for ssh and Mercurial.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Version control: Mercurial. Note that you might have to add a site key (like bitbucket’s) to your .hgrc file so it doesn’t complain when pushing files.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Productivity: &lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/my-little-pomodoro/id412699095?mt=12&#34;&gt;My Little Pomodoro&lt;/a&gt; available from the Mac app store. I love it for following the Pomodoro technique (you can use any other timer that you like) which Hilary introduced me to. It works like a charm when you are under stress and need to be productive. After all, I’m prone to escape the stress and distract myself, so this helps me keep my distractions limited. I’ve also found that when I’m stuck in a problem and I take the 5 min break thinking about something else, well, the machine keeps working and when I come back from the break I have a new idea to try out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Video player: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.videolan.org/vlc/index.html&#34;&gt;VLC&lt;/a&gt; (includes codecs).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other stuff&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Browser: I used to love&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mozilla.org/en-US/&#34;&gt;Mozilla Firefox&lt;/a&gt; (it has a nice sync functionality) but I’ve moved to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/intl/en/chrome/browser/&#34;&gt;Google Chrome&lt;/a&gt;. It’s kind of a shame that Google started to compete with Mozilla, but oh well bye bye 2007. I use Chrome because it works a tad bit better with other Google tools, but that’s it. It also syncs your bookmarks. Both work great and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.opera.com/&#34;&gt;Opera&lt;/a&gt; is still my favorite backup browser. I guess anything but Internet Explorer and Safari.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning R. I would definitely check Thomas Girke &lt;a href=&#34;http://manuals.bioinformatics.ucr.edu/home/programming-in-r&#34;&gt;Programming in R&lt;/a&gt; page and Frank McCown’s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.harding.edu/fmccown/R/&#34;&gt;Producing Simple Graphs with R&lt;/a&gt; tutorial. I have my own share of R related slides &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu/~lcollado/teaching.html#.UDblsWie5Ng&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning Bioconductor. Thomas Girke again wrote a great resource for learning how to use &lt;a href=&#34;http://manuals.bioinformatics.ucr.edu/home/ht-seq#Introduction&#34;&gt;Bioconductor for analyzing high-throughput sequencing data files&lt;/a&gt;. Bioconductor hosts packages for other technologies/problems, so I would also look at it’s own help pages like the Workflows section. I also like &lt;a href=&#34;http://www2.warwick.ac.uk/fac/sci/moac/people/students/peter_cock/r&#34;&gt;Peter’s R programming pages&lt;/a&gt;, specially the heatmap section. I have my own share of Bioconductor related slides &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu/~lcollado/teaching.html#.UDblsWie5Ng&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning LaTeX. I learnt the hard way I guess… I learnt by comparing Sweave files and their output and seeing what changed if I modified the code. Nowadays, I would very highly recommend that you first check the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uwlax.edu/faculty/matchett/late/late.htm&#34;&gt;How to Use LaTeX&lt;/a&gt; short series of exercises/files by Andrew Matchett. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://tobi.oetiker.ch/lshort/lshort.pdf&#34;&gt;Not so short introduction to LaTeX&lt;/a&gt; is a great resource. For very specific symbols, check the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ung.si/~sstanic/teaching/CIS/LaTeX_symbols-a4.pdf&#34;&gt;Comprehensive LaTeX symbol list&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using a SGE (Sun Grid Engine) cluster. For some basic commands look &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rcc.uh.edu/hpc-docs/49-using-torque-to-submit-and-monitor-jobs.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. For the Hopkins cluster, definitely read &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu/bit/cluster-usage.html&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;. Finally, for running array jobs check &lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.duke.edu/display/SCSC/SGE+Array+Jobs&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LaTeX and math. You should definitely &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/LaTeX/Mathematics&#34;&gt;read the wiki books page for this topic&lt;/a&gt;. I kept going back to it over my first year at Hopkins when I really needed to learn all this. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/LaTeX/Theorems&#34;&gt;theorems page&lt;/a&gt; is nice, but not a must. Same for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.ubc.ca/~webmaste/howto/editor/texerr.html&#34;&gt;Common TeX/LaTeX errors&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Figures in LaTeX. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hep.manchester.ac.uk/u/jenny/jcwdocs/latex/figures.html&#34;&gt;Here is a basic overview &lt;/a&gt;but the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/LaTeX/Floats,_Figures_and_Captions&#34;&gt;wiki books page for the topic&lt;/a&gt; is a must check.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accents in LaTeX. Check this &lt;a href=&#34;http://fontignie.blogspot.com/2006/04/accents-in-latex.html&#34;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; by “Bugs and Solutions”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blogging R code: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.inside-r.org/pretty-r&#34;&gt;Pretty-R&lt;/a&gt;. I haven’t really used it but it surely looks pretty!!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cloud storage: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/&#34;&gt;Dropbox&lt;/a&gt; works great and tons of iPad apps have an option to backup to it which works great with my note-taking apps. &lt;a href=&#34;https://drive.google.com/&#34;&gt;Google Drive&lt;/a&gt; and others are also around.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paper (biobliography) organizer: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zotero.org/&#34;&gt;Zotero&lt;/a&gt; is amazing! I simply love it :) I pull the bibliography from pubmed or the magazine page itself and to avoid any hassle, I have a “papers” folder in my Dropbox where I only organize them by last name. Then if I want to find something, I go to Zotero and look use it’s great search function. I rarely use it to annotate webpages and I hear that it can now upload files to the cloud. Anyhow, I first used it in my Windows/Ubuntu dual setup. You can use it as a Zotero Firefox plugin or as Zotero stand-alone with Zotero Connector (Google Chrome for example). Finally, Zotero can export your bibliography into a BibTex file :)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blog: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tumblr.com/dashboard&#34;&gt;Tumblr&lt;/a&gt;. Some like WordPress better, but I like how Tumblr is not only a blogging platform but also a social media tool. I’ve written &lt;a href=&#34;http://fellgernon.tumblr.com/tagged/Blog#.UDbiDGie5Ng&#34;&gt;several posts before on how to customize your blog&lt;/a&gt; and other blog related tools. But a must in my point of view is to get your RSS feed “burnt” with &lt;a href=&#34;http://feedburner.google.com&#34;&gt;feedburner&lt;/a&gt;. It has lots of interesting tools and is much better than a plain XML RSS feed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notes: &lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/notability-take-notes-annotate/id360593530?mt=8&#34;&gt;Notability&lt;/a&gt; iPad app. Great stuff and doesn’t blow up on you (aka, doesn’t lose your notes) like &lt;a href=&#34;http://notesplusapp.com/&#34;&gt;NotesPlus&lt;/a&gt; did to me. Anyhow, note-taking in my iPad with auto-cloud backups greatly changed my classroom experience. THere are other apps like this one out there.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I use &lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/voice-recorder-hd/id373045717?mt=8&#34;&gt;Voice Recorder HD&lt;/a&gt; iPad app for recording lectures. It’s useful when you miss something the professor went over quickly and you are trying to understand it later on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Email: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gmail.com&#34;&gt;Gmail&lt;/a&gt; with keyboard shortcuts enabled. I also use “Canned Responses” from the Google Labs to specify my signature. I have an academic one, one for Mexico, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Send emails later: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.boomeranggmail.com/&#34;&gt;Boomerang for Gmail&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Calendar: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/calendar&#34;&gt;Google Calendar&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Task manager: Google Tasks from within Google Calendar (not from Gmail, which is doable too) with &lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/gotasks-google-tasks-client/id389113399?mt=8&#34;&gt;GoTasks&lt;/a&gt; in my iPhone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RSS reader: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.google.com/reader/view/&#34;&gt;Google Reader&lt;/a&gt;. Works great. By the way, Orbvious interest (below) also works with Google Reader and has a customizable hotkey for it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mark pages to read later: &lt;a href=&#34;http://shalom.craimer.org/projects/orbviousinterest/&#34;&gt;Orbvious Interest&lt;/a&gt; for Google Chrome. Great stuff! It syncs between computers and you can use Pocket in your iPad to view the links. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maps: &lt;a href=&#34;https://maps.google.com/&#34;&gt;Google Maps&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Video conversation: &lt;a&gt;Skype&lt;/a&gt;, Google Hangouts. If I’m going to help someone remotely, then I use &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.teamviewer.com/en/index.aspx&#34;&gt;TeamViewer&lt;/a&gt; which is free for non-profit purposes. With it you can move their mouse, which makes things much easier for support issues!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Photos: &lt;a href=&#34;http://picasa.google.com/&#34;&gt;Picasa&lt;/a&gt;. I pay the 5 bucks a year for 20 GB on Picasa Web Albums so all my photos are on the cloud.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dictionary: &lt;a href=&#34;http://dictionary.die.net/&#34;&gt;die.net&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Network visualizer/analyzer: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cytoscape.org/&#34;&gt;Cytoscape&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://bioinformatics.psb.ugent.be/webtools/Venn/&#34;&gt;Venn diagrams&lt;/a&gt; with more than 2 sets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Setting up your website. I pretty much followed Alyssa’s instructions and got my CSS template for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu/~lcollado/#.UDbpKmie5Ng&#34;&gt;my academic page&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.freecsstemplates.org/&#34;&gt;FCT&lt;/a&gt;. Then I used simple html to modify it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I pretty much dumped a ton of my bookmarks in this huuuuge post! Well, I hope that it will be useful to someone. At least now I&amp;#8217;m happy to have contributed to Hilary&amp;#8217;s computing-resources-post drive.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
