<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Science | L. Collado-Torres</title>
    <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/category/science/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://lcolladotor.github.io/category/science/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Science</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 16 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://lcolladotor.github.io/media/icon_hu2b32c4ab415f12f472f73c7b0301b0d1_19400_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Science</title>
      <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/category/science/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>CZI Lat Am Meeting 2023: some questions I have before the meeting</title>
      <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2023/04/16/czi-lat-am-meeting-2023-some-questions-i-have-before-the-meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2023/04/16/czi-lat-am-meeting-2023-some-questions-i-have-before-the-meeting/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m excited for the opportunity to participate at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/search?q=%23CZILatAmMtg&amp;amp;src=typed_query&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;#CZILatAmMtg&lt;/a&gt; in 2023 organized by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/cziscience&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CZI Science&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m also thankful to those who nominated me, and in particular to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/AleMedinaRivera&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Alejandra Medina Rivera&lt;/a&gt;. I believe that one of the reasons I&amp;rsquo;m here is for my volunteer work at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://comunidadbioinfo.github.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Community of Bioinformatics Software Developers&lt;/a&gt; in Mexico (CDSB), where &lt;a href=&#34;https://comunidadbioinfo.github.io/#people&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;many&lt;/a&gt; have made very important contributions. Some also know me from my time in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://bioconductor.org/about/community-advisory-board/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Bioconductor Community Advisory Board&lt;/a&gt;, from which I stepped down earlier this year once my 3 year term ended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having said that, I have been sharing with some other event attendees that I do feel burned out. I had envisioned that at CDSB we would train and empower those who would eventually replace us. And we&amp;rsquo;ve had quite a bit of success in doing so (3/7 CDSB board members are not founders). However, it&amp;rsquo;s been limited to a few key new volunteers, who then they risk burning out themselves. Since I want CDSB to continue on for many more years to come, I sometimes feel like I should again involve myself on organizing CDSB events. Doing so would involve volunteering on my free time. Given my position as a principal investigator, I actually spend more extra hours on activities related to that job, so I don&amp;rsquo;t have much free time to give. There are also other non-academic interests I want to pursue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, I want to chat with others that organize short courses through their own organizations to learn how they plan to pass on the torch and see if those ideas can apply to CDSB as well as renew my own fire. Maybe others don&amp;rsquo;t plan to pass on the torch for many years as organizing these short courses becomes part of their main job. At CDSB (and LCG-UNAM) courses, I like the path of having students in year 1, that become teaching assistants in year 2, that then teach a portion of the course in year 3, then can organize part of or a full course in year 4. But that&amp;rsquo;s a long ramp, and I think that I failed to anticipate what would happen after year 4. Like there needs to be more structure to help them continue this cycle and reach a point where they can apply for grants without the names of the founders. I also failed to notice that founders would need to be involved for a longer period of time, until we reach a larger critical mass of highly trained volunteers, which at time point can fully replace us and keep CDSB going for more years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I also have other questions and topics I want to discuss with others. For example, I&amp;rsquo;m really curious to learn about justifications others use to convince their employers to let them spend work time on these type of initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some arguments I&amp;rsquo;ve used are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are training the future staff we want to recruit. I learned this from a former &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sacnas.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;SACNAS&lt;/a&gt; president and it was useful to argue for time to teach (in my case in Mexico) without having to take vacations time to do so for a week or two per year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is one I used recently in the context of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://research.libd.org/rstatsclub/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;LIBD rstats club&lt;/a&gt; I organize at work: &amp;ldquo;YouTube analytics tell me that we&amp;rsquo;ve had 4,621 views in the last 365 days for a total watch time of 280.7 hours. That&amp;rsquo;s an average of 5.4 hours per week, which is 13.5% of a 40 hour work week that we saved a full time employee on average per week this last year. For example, for a base salary of $x$ or $y$ that&amp;rsquo;s &amp;gt;10,000 or &amp;gt;20,000 USD in savings per year taking into account fringe costs. These videos remain in perpetuity, and while some might become outdated, they are definitely an asset for the institute.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m also curious to hear what arguments others use to convince their employers to let them apply to grants that limit indirect costs. For example, US-based institutions depend on those indirect costs to function, and will not like it if you apply for a grant that will limit your effort available for other grants if that grant provides, let&amp;rsquo;s say, less than 25% or 50% of the indirect costs other grants provide. Direct costs are like research costs and salary support for your team. Like if you are doing so well that you get funding for 100% of your effort, then of course institutions would like it for you to have the max indirect costs rate possible. Though well, a grant with a lower indirect costs rate is better than no grant if you don&amp;rsquo;t have 100% funded effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe something funding bodies could do is request that a small portion of the grantees time is used to teach communities in need for these opportunities (here we are talking about Latin America, but it could be other ones). Another idea is that they could reward with a higher indirect cost rate those institutions that allow grantees to do this during work hours. These ideas might have no legs, but maybe they could. We&amp;rsquo;ll see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While change takes a lot of effort and sometimes one might feel alone, I am definitely excited about the discussions we&amp;rsquo;ll have the next two days. Though I&amp;rsquo;m also aware of potential pitfalls, like fighting for a piece of the cake. Hopefully we can make the cake bigger!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://giphy.com/embed/9u8GF7MuhdvS8&#34; width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;366&#34; frameBorder=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;giphy-embed&#34; allowFullScreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://giphy.com/gifs/cake-slice-9u8GF7MuhdvS8&#34;&gt;via GIPHY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research Scientist: an academic career launch pad</title>
      <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2020/03/16/research-scientist-an-academic-career-launch-pad/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2020/03/16/research-scientist-an-academic-career-launch-pad/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/authors/admin/avatar_hub730ffb954e879fe0ab174cacb839b41_1326712_270x270_fill_lanczos_center_2.png&#34; align=&#34;center&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a long start to 2020 including the past four very busy weeks, I&amp;rsquo;m happy to announce that today March 16th 2020 I accepted a position as &lt;strong&gt;Research Scientist&lt;/strong&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.libd.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Lieber Institute for Brain Development&lt;/a&gt; in Baltimore, MD, USA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://giphy.com/embed/jRZXsVd7xbBAIF08eH&#34; width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;270&#34; frameBorder=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;giphy-embed&#34; allowFullScreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://giphy.com/gifs/basketsfx-sign-autograph-there-jRZXsVd7xbBAIF08eH&#34;&gt;via GIPHY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-will-i-do-as-a-research-scientist-at-libd&#34;&gt;What will I do as a Research Scientist at LIBD?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At LIBD we currently have the following scientific ranks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Research Technician&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Research Assistant&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Research Associate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Staff Scientist I, II and III&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Research Scientist (+ Lead and Senior)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Investigator (+ Lead and Senior)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research Scientists carry out research, do so scholarly, are tasked with being creative, are encouraged to seek funding, and can have supervisory and mentor roles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my agreement with LIBD, I will remain affiliated with the Data Science Team I led by &lt;a href=&#34;http://aejaffe.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Andrew E Jaffe&lt;/a&gt; while also having the opportunity to interact with and collaborate with fantastic biologists, data scientists, and researchers at LIBD, Johns Hopkins University, and beyond. Furthermore, I will officially help mentor LIBD scientists in data science and R tools. LIBD will support me while I build a small team around my research interests and prepare my first set of grant submissions. There will be a transition period and many things I need to learn: from requesting a budget to writing a job ad, as well as many details about grant requests. But ultimately, LIBD offered me a launch pad for an academic career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://giphy.com/embed/xiN0BXMETVsx0AxTXt&#34; width=&#34;315&#34; height=&#34;480&#34; frameBorder=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;giphy-embed&#34; allowFullScreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://giphy.com/gifs/usnationalarchives-night-nasa-xiN0BXMETVsx0AxTXt&#34;&gt;via GIPHY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;details&#34;&gt;Details&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my first tasks will be to refine the details of my role. For example, right now on the teaching side of things I&amp;rsquo;m imagining doing the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lead a weekly &lt;a href=&#34;http://research.libd.org/rstatsclub/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;LIBD rstats club&lt;/a&gt; meeting where I can go over topics common to several users.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hold one-on-one data science guidance sessions, similar to the MPH capstone sessions I did during my teaching assistant years at JHBSPH.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Occasionally lead internal workshops, which could benefit from workshops I prepare for &lt;a href=&#34;https://comunidadbioinfo.github.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CDSB&lt;/a&gt; and elsewhere.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get &lt;a href=&#34;https://education.rstudio.com/trainers/#info&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;certified by RStudio&lt;/a&gt; and attend more R conferences &amp;amp; workshops.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the scientific side, I will also learn more about the biological questions my LIBD colleagues are working on. These hypothesis-driven projects will provide me a new set of challenges and I will perform what me and my &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lcg.unam.mx/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;LCG-UNAM&lt;/a&gt; classmates were trained to do: to function as a bridge between multiple fields. I will also keep learning from my JHU colleagues and working with them as I refine my ideas. Currently, this is how I have framed my research interests:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My research aims to better understand the roots and signatures of disease (particularly psychiatric disorders) by zooming in across dimensions of gene activity: from studying gene expression at all feature levels (genes to exons to exon-exon junctions and un-annotated regions of expression), to using different gene expression measurement technologies (bulk RNA-seq, single cell/nuclei RNA-seq to spatial transcriptomics) that provide finer biological resolution and localization of gene expression. I&amp;rsquo;m interested in both hypothesis-driven projects as well as building general resources such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://jhubiostatistics.shinyapps.io/recount/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;recount2&lt;/a&gt; that enable us to contextualize our findings across all of the public human gene expression landscape. I use the &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;R programming language&lt;/a&gt; for nearly all my work and like to organize my code in R packages that I share mostly through the &lt;a href=&#34;http://bioconductor.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Bioconductor project&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2020-03-16-research-scientist-an-academic-career-launch-pad_files/marvin-meyer-SYTO3xs06fU-unsplash.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
{width=800px}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a style=&#34;background-color:black;color:white;text-decoration:none;padding:4px 6px;font-family:-apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;San Francisco&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, Helvetica, Ubuntu, Roboto, Noto, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Arial, sans-serif;font-size:12px;font-weight:bold;line-height:1.2;display:inline-block;border-radius:3px&#34; href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/@marvelous?utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=photographer-credit&amp;amp;utm_content=creditBadge&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34; title=&#34;Download free do whatever you want high-resolution photos from Marvin Meyer&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&#34;&gt;&lt;svg xmlns=&#34;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&#34; style=&#34;height:12px;width:auto;position:relative;vertical-align:middle;top:-2px;fill:white&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 32 32&#34;&gt;&lt;title&gt;unsplash-logo&lt;/title&gt;&lt;path d=&#34;M10 9V0h12v9H10zm12 5h10v18H0V14h10v9h12v-9z&#34;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&#34;&gt;Marvin Meyer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for building my team, I know that overall one of the challenges everyone faces is recruiting talent. I&amp;rsquo;ll give this complicated process a shot by tapping into my network which includes many immigrants. I will also expand my network online and through conferences. Furthermore, I am committed to my outreach projects such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://comunidadbioinfo.github.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CDSB&lt;/a&gt; but will synergize them even more: re-use training materials, potentially recruit team members, and help me expand my network. In the meantime, if you are interested in working with me or my colleagues, please let me know!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;final-decision&#34;&gt;Final decision&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The decision I had to make was challenging, but in the end, I decided to stay at LIBD because they offered me a path to become a principal investigator in academia which it&amp;rsquo;s something I want to explore and see where it leads me. I will also formally be someone&amp;rsquo;s boss and gain managerial experience, work much closer with biologists in hypothesis-driven projects, and overall gain more experience and skills. My brother&amp;rsquo;s job tasks changed last week, to which I told him: &amp;ldquo;welcome to the real world&amp;rdquo;. Well, I guess that&amp;rsquo;s how it&amp;rsquo;ll be for me too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;acknowledgments&#34;&gt;Acknowledgments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to thank everyone that helped me through this decision-making process, provided me with information, asked me questions, answered questions, expanded my universe, advocated for me, advised me, cheered for me, and supported me. Thank you! I look forward to working with you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://giphy.com/embed/jafcQpzkQK8HX58GKj&#34; width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;270&#34; frameBorder=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;giphy-embed&#34; allowFullScreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://giphy.com/gifs/pbs-season-5-gbbo-jafcQpzkQK8HX58GKj&#34;&gt;via GIPHY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog post was made possible thanks to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://bioconductor.org/packages/3.17/BiocStyle&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;BiocStyle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Oles_2023&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://bioconductor.org/packages/BiocStyle&#39;&gt;Oleś, 2023&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=blogdown&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;blogdown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Xie_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown/&#39;&gt;Xie, Hill, and Thomas, 2017&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;knitcitations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Boettiger_2021&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&#39;&gt;Boettiger, 2021&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=sessioninfo&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;sessioninfo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Wickham_2021&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=sessioninfo&#39;&gt;Wickham, Chang, Flight, Müller et al., 2021&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Boettiger_2021&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Boettiger_2021&#34;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt;
C. Boettiger.
&lt;em&gt;knitcitations: Citations for &#39;Knitr&#39; Markdown Files&lt;/em&gt;.
R package version 1.0.12.
2021.
URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Oles_2023&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Oles_2023&#34;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt;
A. Oleś.
&lt;em&gt;BiocStyle: Standard styles for vignettes and other Bioconductor documents&lt;/em&gt;.
R package version 2.28.0.
2023.
DOI: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.18129/B9.bioc.BiocStyle&#34;&gt;10.18129/B9.bioc.BiocStyle&lt;/a&gt;.
URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://bioconductor.org/packages/BiocStyle&#34;&gt;https://bioconductor.org/packages/BiocStyle&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Wickham_2021&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Wickham_2021&#34;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt;
H. Wickham, W. Chang, R. Flight, K. Müller, et al.
&lt;em&gt;sessioninfo: R Session Information&lt;/em&gt;.
R package version 1.2.2.
2021.
URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=sessioninfo&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=sessioninfo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Xie_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Xie_2017&#34;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt;
Y. Xie, A. P. Hill, and A. Thomas.
&lt;em&gt;blogdown: Creating Websites with R Markdown&lt;/em&gt;.
Boca Raton, Florida: Chapman and Hall/CRC, 2017.
ISBN: 978-0815363729.
URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown/&#34;&gt;https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;reproducibility&#34;&gt;Reproducibility&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34; data-lang=&#34;go&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;─&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;Session&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;info&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;───────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;setting&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;value&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;version&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;version&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2023&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;06&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;16&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;os&lt;/span&gt;       &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;macOS&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;Ventura&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;13.4&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;system&lt;/span&gt;   &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;aarch64&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;darwin20&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;ui&lt;/span&gt;       &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;X11&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;language&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;EN&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;collate&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;en_US&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;UTF&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;8&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;ctype&lt;/span&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;en_US&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;UTF&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;8&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;tz&lt;/span&gt;       &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;America&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;New_York&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;date&lt;/span&gt;     &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2023&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;07&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;11&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;pandoc&lt;/span&gt;   &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;3.1.5&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;@&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;opt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;homebrew&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;bin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;via&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;rmarkdown&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;─&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;Packages&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;───────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;kn&#34;&gt;package&lt;/span&gt;       &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;version&lt;/span&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;date&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;UTC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;lib&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;source&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;backports&lt;/span&gt;       &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;1.4.1&lt;/span&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2021&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;12&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;13&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;bibtex&lt;/span&gt;          &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;0.5.1&lt;/span&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2023&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;01&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;26&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;BiocManager&lt;/span&gt;     &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;1.30.21&lt;/span&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2023&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;06&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;BiocStyle&lt;/span&gt;     &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;2.28.0&lt;/span&gt;     &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2023&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;04&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;25&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;Bioconductor&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;blogdown&lt;/span&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;1.18&lt;/span&gt;       &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2023&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;06&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;19&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;bookdown&lt;/span&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;0.34&lt;/span&gt;       &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2023&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;05&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;09&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;bslib&lt;/span&gt;           &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;0.5.0&lt;/span&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2023&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;06&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;09&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;cachem&lt;/span&gt;          &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;1.0.8&lt;/span&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2023&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;05&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;01&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;cli&lt;/span&gt;             &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;3.6.1&lt;/span&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2023&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;03&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;23&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;colorout&lt;/span&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;1.2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2023&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;05&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;06&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;Github&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;jalvesaq&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;colorout&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;@&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;79931&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;fd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;digest&lt;/span&gt;          &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;0.6.31&lt;/span&gt;     &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2022&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;12&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;11&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;evaluate&lt;/span&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;0.21&lt;/span&gt;       &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2023&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;05&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;05&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;fastmap&lt;/span&gt;         &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;1.1.1&lt;/span&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2023&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;02&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;24&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;generics&lt;/span&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;0.1.3&lt;/span&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2022&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;07&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;05&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;glue&lt;/span&gt;            &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;1.6.2&lt;/span&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2022&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;02&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;24&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;htmltools&lt;/span&gt;       &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;0.5.5&lt;/span&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2023&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;03&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;23&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;httr&lt;/span&gt;            &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;1.4.6&lt;/span&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2023&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;05&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;08&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;jquerylib&lt;/span&gt;       &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;0.1.4&lt;/span&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2021&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;04&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;26&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;jsonlite&lt;/span&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;1.8.7&lt;/span&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2023&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;06&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;29&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;knitcitations&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;1.0.12&lt;/span&gt;     &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2021&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;01&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;knitr&lt;/span&gt;           &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;1.43&lt;/span&gt;       &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2023&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;05&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;25&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;lifecycle&lt;/span&gt;       &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;1.0.3&lt;/span&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2022&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;07&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;lubridate&lt;/span&gt;       &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;1.9.2&lt;/span&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2023&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;02&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;magrittr&lt;/span&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;2.0.3&lt;/span&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2022&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;03&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;30&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;plyr&lt;/span&gt;            &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;1.8.8&lt;/span&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2022&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;11&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;11&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R6&lt;/span&gt;              &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;2.5.1&lt;/span&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2021&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;08&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;19&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;Rcpp&lt;/span&gt;            &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;1.0.10&lt;/span&gt;     &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2023&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;01&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;22&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;RefManageR&lt;/span&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;1.4.0&lt;/span&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2022&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;09&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;30&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;rlang&lt;/span&gt;           &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;1.1.1&lt;/span&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2023&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;04&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;28&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;rmarkdown&lt;/span&gt;       &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;2.23&lt;/span&gt;       &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2023&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;07&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;01&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;rstudioapi&lt;/span&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;0.14&lt;/span&gt;       &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2022&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;08&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;22&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;sass&lt;/span&gt;            &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;0.4.6.9000&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2023&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;05&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;06&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;Github&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;rstudio&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;sass&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;@&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;f248fe5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;sessioninfo&lt;/span&gt;   &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;1.2.2&lt;/span&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2021&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;12&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;06&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;stringi&lt;/span&gt;         &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;1.7.12&lt;/span&gt;     &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2023&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;01&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;11&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;stringr&lt;/span&gt;         &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;1.5.0&lt;/span&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2022&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;12&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;02&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;timechange&lt;/span&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;0.2.0&lt;/span&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2023&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;01&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;11&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;xfun&lt;/span&gt;            &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;0.39&lt;/span&gt;       &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2023&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;04&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;20&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;xml2&lt;/span&gt;            &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;1.3.4&lt;/span&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2023&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;04&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;27&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;yaml&lt;/span&gt;            &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;2.3.7&lt;/span&gt;      &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2023&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mo&#34;&gt;01&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;23&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;Library&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;Frameworks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;framework&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;Versions&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mf&#34;&gt;4.3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;arm64&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;Resources&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nx&#34;&gt;library&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;##&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;err&#34;&gt;──────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Diving together into the unknown world of spatial transcriptomics</title>
      <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2020/02/29/diving-together-into-the-unknown-world-of-spatial-transcriptomics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2020/02/29/diving-together-into-the-unknown-world-of-spatial-transcriptomics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday was an extremely exciting day for me and my colleagues. We finished a project we had been working on and shared it with the world. Meaning, it’s done and we can relax for a little bit while we wait for feedback from our peers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this was not any project, at least not for me. Why do you ask? In general terms, it involved an analysis that you could not search on Google and find the answer for. That is, it involved diving into the unknown!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://giphy.com/embed/5dY4XX5ZCvjZ3AENUu&#34; width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;201&#34; frameBorder=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;giphy-embed&#34; allowFullScreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://giphy.com/gifs/disneystudios-disney-frozen-2-5dY4XX5ZCvjZ3AENUu&#34;&gt;via GIPHY&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The unknown is scary and as the lyrics say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve had my adventure, I don’t need something new
I’m afraid of what I’m risking if I follow you
Into the unknown&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of us have been building our careers with other types of data and/or experiments, and taking on a new type of data knowing we had an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biospace.com/article/10x-genomics-begins-shipments-of-visium-spatial-gene-expression-solution/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;early access advantage&lt;/a&gt; over others was quite the challenge. I don’t know about my co-authors, but maybe some of them shared thoughts like mine that were along the lines: can I do this? can I make it work? do my analysis choices make sense? what will experts think of doing once they have access to this data? All while racing against time, even if it was just an illusion in our minds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it’s not my first adventure and I’ve picked up skills and confidence along the way. In particular, I’ve written &lt;a href=&#34;https://bioconductor.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Bioconductor&lt;/a&gt; R packages, dealt with &lt;code&gt;pkgdown&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;travis&lt;/code&gt; issues like &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/r-lib/pkgdown/issues/1206&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;#1206&lt;/a&gt;, made &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=shiny&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;shiny&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; web applications, analyzed large RNA-seq data, &lt;a href=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/2019/04/02/how-to-write-academic-documents-with-googledocs/#.XlnnqJNKg0o&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;written papers using GoogleDocs&lt;/a&gt;, gotten better at asking for help, among other skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;It&amp;#39;s Thurs but here&amp;#39;s the &amp;quot;more&amp;quot; I promised &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/4gahvWDbWE&#34;&gt;https://t.co/4gahvWDbWE&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/travisci?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@travisci&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/pkgdown?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#pkgdown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;+my fam of &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/rstats?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#rstats&lt;/a&gt; issues today &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/iGFfHLtasM&#34;&gt;https://t.co/iGFfHLtasM&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/M8DZEHryJZ&#34;&gt;https://t.co/M8DZEHryJZ&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/FU8qq3f5p6&#34;&gt;https://t.co/FU8qq3f5p6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I&amp;#39;m the pest that visits your GH issues here &amp;amp; there😅Nah, I put lots of 👨🏾‍💻into them!😊 &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/1G0nd5ZwUJ&#34;&gt;https://t.co/1G0nd5ZwUJ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; 🇲🇽 Leonardo Collado-Torres (@lcolladotor) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/lcolladotor/status/1233186931590123522?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;February 28, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve also gotten more comfortable with the idea that I can’t do it all. Others will shortly develop new methods for this type of data, or proper infrastructure to handle this data, or faster visualizations, and so goes on the list. But I’m proud and really happy to say that we built quite the robust prototype. Plus maybe we’ll be involved in shaping this future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And you noticed that I mentioned &lt;em&gt;we&lt;/em&gt;. That’s because I have been learning over the years how to foster collaborations. This particular project involved working with two other members of my workplace who are awesome and that I didn’t know that well. It also involved a new collaboration with someone I’ve known for a while now (we initially met through Twitter in 2014) but hadn’t had the chance to work with. Thus we dove into the unknown together 👩‍🚀🧑‍🚀.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://giphy.com/embed/Ph0nUfRpbMcQvA7ue8&#34; width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;199&#34; frameBorder=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;giphy-embed&#34; allowFullScreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://giphy.com/gifs/disneystudios-disney-frozen-2-Ph0nUfRpbMcQvA7ue8&#34;&gt;via GIPHY&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel like we complemented each other quite well and all I can confidently say that our new adventure so far has been very stimulating, even it cost me some sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Woke up at 3:30 am dreaming about code 👨🏻‍💻 😴 and on an off till 5:30. Gave up and went to work early... hopefully I can remember the dreams 😅&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/CodeWhileDreaming?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#CodeWhileDreaming&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/RestFuelsIdeas?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#RestFuelsIdeas&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/h0mYHAaL5W&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/h0mYHAaL5W&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; 🇲🇽 Leonardo Collado-Torres (@lcolladotor) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/lcolladotor/status/1230107491372912641?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;February 19, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;spatial-transcriptomics&#34;&gt;Spatial transcriptomics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, where does &lt;em&gt;spatial transcriptomics&lt;/em&gt; come into play and what does it mean? I work with gene &lt;em&gt;activity&lt;/em&gt; data which we formally refer to as &lt;em&gt;gene expression&lt;/em&gt; 🧬. That is, we measure 🔍🧮 the activity levels of genes for a particular biological condition or tissue sample. For several years now (about since 2007-2009) we have been able to measure many genes from a tissue sample, called bulk RNA-sequencing and abbreviated as RNA-seq.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s great! But biology is complicated and a single tissue sample is composed of multiple cells of various types. For example, in the brain there are cells that send signals around (neurons) and others that give structure to the brain. That is why technologies for measuring the gene expression at the single cell level were developed, abbreviated as scRNA-seq. scRNA-seq has been used widely to study mouse brains to live tissue samples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent years I’ve been working with data from the human brain 🧠. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://libd.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Lieber Institute for Brain Development&lt;/a&gt; has about two thousand brain samples. To preserve them for years to come, the brains are frozen 🥶. Cells are a bit fragile and freezing them breaks them. This fact has made it challenging to study data from frozen human brains. Several of my colleagues work on adapting research protocols to handle frozen human brain tissue. The research field overall has been able to generate single nucleus RNA sequencing (snRNA-seq) data and we are all generating some more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;snRNA-seq and scRNA-seq are great because you can measure what genes (pieces of the cell) are active, classify them into groups, and use prior knowledge to label these groups. However, you lose information about what part of the tissue they come from. That’s where technologies for &lt;em&gt;spatial transcriptomics&lt;/em&gt;, that is, measuring gene expression 🧬 as close a possible to the single cell level yet retaining spatial coordinates are being actively developed. Thus, you end up with two main sources of data: the gene expression measurements but also images from the tissue (&lt;em&gt;histology&lt;/em&gt; information). &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41386-019-0484-7&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;My coworkers anticipated&lt;/a&gt; what could these technologies be used for and what type of research questions they help us answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;oh hey, that&amp;#39;s us! stay tuned for a biorxiv preprint!  &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/LieberInstitute?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@LieberInstitute&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/martinowk?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@martinowk&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kr_maynard?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@kr_maynard&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/fellgernon?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@fellgernon&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/stephaniehicks?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@stephaniehicks&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/lmwebr?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@lmwebr&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/uYpwQu52pS&#34;&gt;https://t.co/uYpwQu52pS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Andrew Jaffe (@andrewejaffe) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/andrewejaffe/status/1232009768006344704?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;February 24, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;our-projects-history&#34;&gt;Our project’s history&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My coworkers got early access to a specific new type of spatial transcriptomics technology called &lt;a href=&#34;https://wp.10xgenomics.com/spatial-transcriptomics/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Visium from the 10x Genomics company&lt;/a&gt; and started piloting it on human brain tissue. They recruited me to their project in early November 2019 (11th) and I recruited more colleagues in early December (4th). Today on February 28th 2020 we made public our research advances, code, and software we built for this project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that we have many potential websites others can find us through, we decided to unify as much as possible the documentation even if that meant repeating it. The basic start of our documentation is included further below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;spatiallibd&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;spatialLIBD&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://research.libd.org/spatialLIBD/reference/figures/logo.png&#34; align=&#34;right&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the &lt;code&gt;spatialLIBD&lt;/code&gt; project! It is composed of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a &lt;a href=&#34;https://shiny.rstudio.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;shiny&lt;/a&gt; web application that we are hosting at &lt;a href=&#34;http://spatial.libd.org/spatialLIBD/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;spatial.libd.org/spatialLIBD/&lt;/a&gt; that can handle a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/LieberInstitute/spatialLIBD/issues/2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;limited&lt;/a&gt; set of concurrent users,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a Bioconductor package at &lt;a href=&#34;http://bioconductor.org/packages/spatialLIBD&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;bioconductor.org/packages/spatialLIBD&lt;/a&gt; (or from &lt;a href=&#34;http://research.libd.org/spatialLIBD/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) that lets you analyze the data and run a local version of our web application (with our data or yours),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and a &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41593-020-00787-0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;research article&lt;/a&gt; with the scientific knowledge we drew from this dataset. The analysis code for our project is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/LieberInstitute/HumanPilot/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and the high quality figures for the manuscript are available through &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.13623902.v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Figshare&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The web application allows you to browse the LIBD human dorsolateral pre-frontal cortex (DLPFC) spatial transcriptomics data generated with the 10x Genomics Visium platform. Through the &lt;a href=&#34;https://bioconductor.org/packages/spatialLIBD&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;R/Bioconductor package&lt;/a&gt; you can also download the data as well as visualize your own datasets using this web application. Please check the &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41593-020-00787-0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;manuscript&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.02.28.969931v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;bioRxiv pre-print&lt;/a&gt; for more details about this project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you tweet about this website, the data or the R package please use the &lt;code&gt;#spatialLIBD&lt;/code&gt; hashtag. You can find previous tweets that way as shown &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/search?q=%23spatialLIBD&amp;src=typed_query&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Thank you! &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?button_hashtag=spatialLIBD&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34; class=&#34;twitter-hashtag-button&#34; data-show-count=&#34;false&#34;&gt;Tweet #spatialLIBD&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;study-design&#34;&gt;Study design&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a quick overview, the data presented here is from portion of the DLPFC that spans six neuronal layers plus white matter (&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;) for a total of three subjects with two pairs of spatially adjacent replicates (&lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt;). Each dissection of DLPFC was designed to span all six layers plus white matter (&lt;strong&gt;C&lt;/strong&gt;). Using this web application you can explore the expression of known genes such as &lt;em&gt;SNAP25&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;strong&gt;D&lt;/strong&gt;, a neuronal gene), &lt;em&gt;MOBP&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;strong&gt;E&lt;/strong&gt;, an oligodendrocyte gene), and known layer markers from mouse studies such as &lt;em&gt;PCP4&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;strong&gt;F&lt;/strong&gt;, a known layer 5 marker gene).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://research.libd.org/spatialLIBD/reference/figures/paper_figure1.jpg&#34; align=&#34;center&#34; width=&#34;800px&#34; /&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;shiny-website-mirrors&#34;&gt;Shiny website mirrors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://spatial.libd.org/spatialLIBD/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Main shiny application website&lt;/a&gt; (note that the link must have a trailing slash &lt;code&gt;/&lt;/code&gt; for it to work)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://libd.shinyapps.io/spatialLIBD/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Shinyapps&lt;/a&gt; This version has less RAM memory but is typically deployed using the latest version of &lt;code&gt;spatialLIBD&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;rbioconductor-package&#34;&gt;R/Bioconductor package&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;spatialLIBD&lt;/code&gt; package contains functions for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accessing the spatial transcriptomics data from the LIBD Human Pilot project (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/LieberInstitute/HumanPilot&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;code on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;) generated with the Visium platform from 10x Genomics. The data is retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;http://bioconductor.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Bioconductor&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;code&gt;ExperimentHub&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Visualizing the spot-level spatial gene expression data and clusters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inspecting the data interactively either on your computer or through &lt;a href=&#34;http://spatial.libd.org/spatialLIBD/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;spatial.libd.org/spatialLIBD/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more details, please check the &lt;a href=&#34;http://lieberinstitute.github.io/spatialLIBD&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;documentation website&lt;/a&gt; or the Bioconductor package landing page &lt;a href=&#34;https://bioconductor.org/packages/spatialLIBD&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;installation-instructions&#34;&gt;Installation instructions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get the latest stable &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; release from &lt;a href=&#34;http://cran.r-project.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/a&gt;. Then install &lt;code&gt;spatialLIBD&lt;/code&gt; from &lt;a href=&#34;http://bioconductor.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Bioconductor&lt;/a&gt; using the following code:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34; data-lang=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;if &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;requireNamespace&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;BiocManager&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;quietly&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;kc&#34;&gt;TRUE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;install.packages&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;BiocManager&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;BiocManager&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;install&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;spatialLIBD&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;access-the-data&#34;&gt;Access the data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through the &lt;code&gt;spatialLIBD&lt;/code&gt; package you can access the processed data in it’s final R format. However, we also provide a table of links so you can download the raw data we received from 10x Genomics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;processed-data&#34;&gt;Processed data&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using &lt;code&gt;spatialLIBD&lt;/code&gt; you can access the Human DLPFC spatial transcriptomics data from the 10x Genomics Visium platform. For example, this is the code you can use to access the layer-level data. For more details, check the help file for &lt;code&gt;fetch_data()&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34; data-lang=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;## Load the package&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;library&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;spatialLIBD&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;## Download the spot-level data&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;spe&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;fetch_data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;type&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;spe&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;## This is a SpatialExperiment object&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;spe&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## class: SpatialExperiment 
## dim: 33538 47681 
## metadata(0):
## assays(2): counts logcounts
## rownames(33538): ENSG00000243485 ENSG00000237613 ... ENSG00000277475
##   ENSG00000268674
## rowData names(9): source type ... gene_search is_top_hvg
## colnames(47681): AAACAACGAATAGTTC-1 AAACAAGTATCTCCCA-1 ...
##   TTGTTTCCATACAACT-1 TTGTTTGTGTAAATTC-1
## colData names(69): sample_id Cluster ... array_row array_col
## reducedDimNames(6): PCA TSNE_perplexity50 ... TSNE_perplexity80
##   UMAP_neighbors15
## mainExpName: NULL
## altExpNames(0):
## spatialCoords names(2) : pxl_col_in_fullres pxl_row_in_fullres
## imgData names(4): sample_id image_id data scaleFactor
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34; data-lang=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;## Note the memory size&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;lobstr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;obj_size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;spe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## 2.04 GB
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34; data-lang=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;## Remake the logo image with histology information&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;vis_clus&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;spe&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;spe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;clustervar&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;layer_guess_reordered&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;sampleid&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;151673&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;colors&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;libd_layer_colors&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;    &lt;span class=&#34;kc&#34;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s&#34;&gt;&amp;#39; DLPFC Human Brain Layers\nMade with github.com/LieberInstitute/spatialLIBD&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2020-02-29-diving-together-into-the-unknown-world-of-spatial-transcriptomics_files/figure-html/access_data-1.png&#34; width=&#34;864&#34; /&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;Citation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is the citation output from using &lt;code&gt;citation(&#39;spatialLIBD&#39;)&lt;/code&gt; in R. Please
run this yourself to check for any updates on how to cite &lt;strong&gt;spatialLIBD&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34; data-lang=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;citation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;spatialLIBD&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## To cite package &#39;spatialLIBD&#39; in publications use:
## 
##   Pardo B, Spangler A, Weber LM, Hicks SC, Jaffe AE, Martinowich K,
##   Maynard KR, Collado-Torres L (2022). &amp;quot;spatialLIBD: an R/Bioconductor
##   package to visualize spatially-resolved transcriptomics data.&amp;quot; _BMC
##   Genomics_. doi:10.1186/s12864-022-08601-w
##   &amp;lt;https://doi.org/10.1186/s12864-022-08601-w&amp;gt;,
##   &amp;lt;https://doi.org/10.1186/s12864-022-08601-w&amp;gt;.
## 
##   Maynard KR, Collado-Torres L, Weber LM, Uytingco C, Barry BK,
##   Williams SR, II JLC, Tran MN, Besich Z, Tippani M, Chew J, Yin Y,
##   Kleinman JE, Hyde TM, Rao N, Hicks SC, Martinowich K, Jaffe AE
##   (2021). &amp;quot;Transcriptome-scale spatial gene expression in the human
##   dorsolateral prefrontal cortex.&amp;quot; _Nature Neuroscience_.
##   doi:10.1038/s41593-020-00787-0
##   &amp;lt;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41593-020-00787-0&amp;gt;,
##   &amp;lt;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41593-020-00787-0&amp;gt;.
## 
##   Huuki-Myers LA, Spangler A, Eagles NJ, Montgomergy KD, Kwon SH, Guo
##   B, Grant-Peters M, Divecha HR, Tippani M, Sriworarat C, Nguyen AB,
##   Ravichandran P, Tran MN, Seyedian A, Consortium P, Hyde TM, Kleinman
##   JE, Battle A, Page SC, Ryten M, Hicks SC, Martinowich K,
##   Collado-Torres L, Maynard KR (2023). &amp;quot;Integrated single cell and
##   unsupervised spatial transcriptomic analysis defines molecular
##   anatomy of the human dorsolateral prefrontal cortex.&amp;quot; _bioRxiv_.
##   doi:10.1101/2023.02.15.528722
##   &amp;lt;https://doi.org/10.1101/2023.02.15.528722&amp;gt;,
##   &amp;lt;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2023.02.15.528722v1&amp;gt;.
## 
##   Kwon SH, Parthiban S, Tippani M, Divecha HR, Eagles NJ, Lobana JS,
##   Williams SR, Mark M, Bharadwaj RA, Kleinman JE, Hyde TM, Page SC,
##   Hicks SC, Martinowich K, Maynard KR, Collado-Torres L (2023).
##   &amp;quot;Influence of Alzheimer’s disease related neuropathology on local
##   microenvironment gene expression in the human inferior temporal
##   cortex.&amp;quot; _bioRxiv_. doi:10.1101/2023.04.20.537710
##   &amp;lt;https://doi.org/10.1101/2023.04.20.537710&amp;gt;,
##   &amp;lt;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2023.04.20.537710v1&amp;gt;.
## 
## To see these entries in BibTeX format, use &#39;print(&amp;lt;citation&amp;gt;,
## bibtex=TRUE)&#39;, &#39;toBibtex(.)&#39;, or set
## &#39;options(citation.bibtex.max=999)&#39;.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please note that the &lt;code&gt;spatialLIBD&lt;/code&gt; was only made possible thanks to many other R and bioinformatics software authors. We have cited their work either in the pre-print or the vignette of the R package.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.libd.org/&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/media/LIBD_logo.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;closing-remarks&#34;&gt;Closing remarks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, this project has everything that I like: R code, a Bioconductor package, challenging and interest biological data, excellent collaborator team, open communication, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, these are early days of the 10x Genomics Visium platform and there’s much we and others want to learn. So if you have the chance to hear anyone in our team talk more in detail about the project or you simply want to chat with them, here are some opportunities for you to do so as we’d love to collaborate with you or even hire you. Check &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/stephaniehicks/status/1229448057462382597?s=20&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stephanie’s tweet&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.libd.org/careers&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;LIBD career website&lt;/a&gt; for more details or simply get in touch with us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kristen R Maynard and me will present a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.the-scientist.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Scientist&lt;/a&gt; webinar on March 19th&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keri Martinowich will be at &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/VirginiaNeuro/status/1214256625290240000&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CVCSN 2020&lt;/a&gt; March 26-27th&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I’ll present a seminar at &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/LIIGH_UNAM&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;LIIGH-UNAM&lt;/a&gt; on March 30th&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kristen R Maynard will be at the 2020 Single Cell Symposium on April 20th&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Likely Andrew E Jaffe and others will be at &lt;a href=&#34;https://meetings.cshl.edu/meetings.aspx?meet=GENOME&amp;amp;year=20&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Biology of Genomes 2020&lt;/a&gt; May 5-9th&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stephanie Hicks will present at &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/erum2020_conf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;eRum 2020&lt;/a&gt; May 27-30&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Likely some of us will attend &lt;a href=&#34;https://bioc2020.bioconductor.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;BioC2020&lt;/a&gt; July 29-31&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2020-02-29-diving-together-into-the-unknown-world-of-spatial-transcriptomics_files/IMG_3284.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, here’s the pre-print twitter thread:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;🔥off the press! 👀 our &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/biorxivpreprint?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@biorxivpreprint&lt;/a&gt; on human 🧠brain &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/LieberInstitute?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@LieberInstitute&lt;/a&gt; spatial 🌌🔬transcriptomics data 🧬using Visium &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/10xGenomics?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@10xGenomics&lt;/a&gt;🎉&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/spatialLIBD?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#spatialLIBD&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;🔍&lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/RTW0VscUKR&#34;&gt;https://t.co/RTW0VscUKR&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br&gt;👩🏾‍💻&lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/bsg04XKONr&#34;&gt;https://t.co/bsg04XKONr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;📚&lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/FJDOOzrAJ6&#34;&gt;https://t.co/FJDOOzrAJ6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;📦&lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/Au5jwADGhY&#34;&gt;https://t.co/Au5jwADGhY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/PiWEDN9q2N&#34;&gt;https://t.co/PiWEDN9q2N&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/aWy0yLlR50&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/aWy0yLlR50&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; 🇲🇽 Leonardo Collado-Torres (@lcolladotor) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/lcolladotor/status/1233661576433061888?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;February 29, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you for getting this far!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://giphy.com/embed/26FxykLpuDxQiFbnG&#34; width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;256&#34; frameBorder=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;giphy-embed&#34; allowFullScreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://giphy.com/gifs/veep-26FxykLpuDxQiFbnG&#34;&gt;via GIPHY&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;reproducibility&#34;&gt;Reproducibility&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## ─ Session info ───────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────
##  setting  value
##  version  R version 4.3.1 (2023-06-16)
##  os       macOS Ventura 13.4
##  system   aarch64, darwin20
##  ui       X11
##  language (EN)
##  collate  en_US.UTF-8
##  ctype    en_US.UTF-8
##  tz       America/New_York
##  date     2023-07-11
##  pandoc   3.1.5 @ /opt/homebrew/bin/ (via rmarkdown)
## 
## ─ Packages ───────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────
##  package                * version    date (UTC) lib source
##  AnnotationDbi            1.62.1     2023-05-08 [1] Bioconductor
##  AnnotationHub            3.8.0      2023-04-25 [1] Bioconductor
##  attempt                  0.3.1      2020-05-03 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  backports                1.4.1      2021-12-13 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  beachmat                 2.16.0     2023-04-25 [1] Bioconductor
##  beeswarm                 0.4.0      2021-06-01 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  benchmarkme              1.0.8      2022-06-12 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  benchmarkmeData          1.0.4      2020-04-23 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  bibtex                   0.5.1      2023-01-26 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  Biobase                * 2.60.0     2023-04-25 [1] Bioconductor
##  BiocFileCache            2.8.0      2023-04-25 [1] Bioconductor
##  BiocGenerics           * 0.46.0     2023-04-25 [1] Bioconductor
##  BiocIO                   1.10.0     2023-04-25 [1] Bioconductor
##  BiocManager              1.30.21    2023-06-10 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  BiocNeighbors            1.18.0     2023-04-25 [1] Bioconductor
##  BiocParallel             1.34.2     2023-05-28 [1] Bioconductor
##  BiocSingular             1.16.0     2023-04-25 [1] Bioconductor
##  BiocStyle              * 2.28.0     2023-04-25 [1] Bioconductor
##  BiocVersion              3.17.1     2022-12-20 [1] Bioconductor
##  Biostrings               2.68.1     2023-05-16 [1] Bioconductor
##  bit                      4.0.5      2022-11-15 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  bit64                    4.0.5      2020-08-30 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  bitops                   1.0-7      2021-04-24 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  blob                     1.2.4      2023-03-17 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  blogdown                 1.18       2023-06-19 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  bookdown                 0.34       2023-05-09 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  bslib                    0.5.0      2023-06-09 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  cachem                   1.0.8      2023-05-01 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  cli                      3.6.1      2023-03-23 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  codetools                0.2-19     2023-02-01 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.1)
##  colorout                 1.2-2      2023-05-06 [1] Github (jalvesaq/colorout@79931fd)
##  colorspace               2.1-0      2023-01-23 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  config                   0.3.1      2020-12-17 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  cowplot                  1.1.1      2020-12-30 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  crayon                   1.5.2      2022-09-29 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  curl                     5.0.1      2023-06-07 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  data.table               1.14.8     2023-02-17 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  DBI                      1.1.3      2022-06-18 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  dbplyr                   2.3.2      2023-03-21 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  DelayedArray             0.26.3     2023-05-28 [1] Bioconductor
##  DelayedMatrixStats       1.22.0     2023-05-08 [1] Bioconductor
##  digest                   0.6.31     2022-12-11 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  doParallel               1.0.17     2022-02-07 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  dotCall64                1.0-2      2022-10-03 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  dplyr                    1.1.2      2023-04-20 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  dqrng                    0.3.0      2021-05-01 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  DropletUtils             1.20.0     2023-05-08 [1] Bioconductor
##  DT                       0.28       2023-05-18 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  edgeR                    3.42.4     2023-05-31 [1] Bioconductor
##  ellipsis                 0.3.2      2021-04-29 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  evaluate                 0.21       2023-05-05 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  ExperimentHub            2.8.0      2023-04-25 [1] Bioconductor
##  fansi                    1.0.4      2023-01-22 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  farver                   2.1.1      2022-07-06 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  fastmap                  1.1.1      2023-02-24 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  fields                   14.1       2022-08-12 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  filelock                 1.0.2      2018-10-05 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  foreach                  1.5.2      2022-02-02 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  generics                 0.1.3      2022-07-05 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  GenomeInfoDb           * 1.36.0     2023-05-08 [1] Bioconductor
##  GenomeInfoDbData         1.2.10     2023-05-06 [1] Bioconductor
##  GenomicAlignments        1.36.0     2023-04-25 [1] Bioconductor
##  GenomicRanges          * 1.52.0     2023-04-25 [1] Bioconductor
##  ggbeeswarm               0.7.2      2023-04-29 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  ggplot2                  3.4.2      2023-04-03 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  ggrepel                  0.9.3      2023-02-03 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  glue                     1.6.2      2022-02-24 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  golem                    0.4.1      2023-06-05 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  gridExtra                2.3        2017-09-09 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  gtable                   0.3.3      2023-03-21 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  HDF5Array                1.28.1     2023-05-01 [1] Bioconductor
##  highr                    0.10       2022-12-22 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  htmltools                0.5.5      2023-03-23 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  htmlwidgets              1.6.2      2023-03-17 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  httpuv                   1.6.11     2023-05-11 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  httr                     1.4.6      2023-05-08 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  interactiveDisplayBase   1.38.0     2023-04-25 [1] Bioconductor
##  IRanges                * 2.34.0     2023-05-08 [1] Bioconductor
##  irlba                    2.3.5.1    2022-10-03 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  iterators                1.0.14     2022-02-05 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  jquerylib                0.1.4      2021-04-26 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  jsonlite                 1.8.7      2023-06-29 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  KEGGREST                 1.40.0     2023-04-25 [1] Bioconductor
##  knitcitations          * 1.0.12     2021-01-10 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  knitr                    1.43       2023-05-25 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  labeling                 0.4.2      2020-10-20 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  later                    1.3.1      2023-05-02 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  lattice                  0.21-8     2023-04-05 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.1)
##  lazyeval                 0.2.2      2019-03-15 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  lifecycle                1.0.3      2022-10-07 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  limma                    3.56.2     2023-06-04 [1] Bioconductor
##  lobstr                   1.1.2      2022-06-22 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  locfit                   1.5-9.8    2023-06-11 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  lubridate                1.9.2      2023-02-10 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  magick                   2.7.4      2023-03-09 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  magrittr                 2.0.3      2022-03-30 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  maps                     3.4.1      2022-10-30 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  Matrix                   1.5-4.1    2023-05-18 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.1)
##  MatrixGenerics         * 1.12.0     2023-05-08 [1] Bioconductor
##  matrixStats            * 1.0.0      2023-06-02 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  memoise                  2.0.1      2021-11-26 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  mime                     0.12       2021-09-28 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  munsell                  0.5.0      2018-06-12 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  paletteer                1.5.0      2022-10-19 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  pillar                   1.9.0      2023-03-22 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  pkgconfig                2.0.3      2019-09-22 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  plotly                   4.10.2     2023-06-03 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  plyr                     1.8.8      2022-11-11 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  png                      0.1-8      2022-11-29 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  prettyunits              1.1.1      2020-01-24 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  promises                 1.2.0.1    2021-02-11 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  purrr                    1.0.1      2023-01-10 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  R.methodsS3              1.8.2      2022-06-13 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  R.oo                     1.25.0     2022-06-12 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  R.utils                  2.12.2     2022-11-11 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  R6                       2.5.1      2021-08-19 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  rappdirs                 0.3.3      2021-01-31 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  RColorBrewer             1.1-3      2022-04-03 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  Rcpp                     1.0.10     2023-01-22 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  RCurl                    1.98-1.12  2023-03-27 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  RefManageR               1.4.0      2022-09-30 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  rematch2                 2.1.2      2020-05-01 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  restfulr                 0.0.15     2022-06-16 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  rhdf5                    2.44.0     2023-04-25 [1] Bioconductor
##  rhdf5filters             1.12.1     2023-04-30 [1] Bioconductor
##  Rhdf5lib                 1.22.0     2023-04-25 [1] Bioconductor
##  rjson                    0.2.21     2022-01-09 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  rlang                    1.1.1      2023-04-28 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  rmarkdown                2.23       2023-07-01 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  Rsamtools                2.16.0     2023-04-25 [1] Bioconductor
##  RSQLite                  2.3.1      2023-04-03 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  rstudioapi               0.14       2022-08-22 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  rsvd                     1.0.5      2021-04-16 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  rtracklayer              1.60.0     2023-04-25 [1] Bioconductor
##  S4Arrays                 1.0.4      2023-05-14 [1] Bioconductor
##  S4Vectors              * 0.38.1     2023-05-02 [1] Bioconductor
##  sass                     0.4.6.9000 2023-05-06 [1] Github (rstudio/sass@f248fe5)
##  ScaledMatrix             1.8.1      2023-05-03 [1] Bioconductor
##  scales                   1.2.1      2022-08-20 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  scater                   1.28.0     2023-04-25 [1] Bioconductor
##  scuttle                  1.10.1     2023-05-02 [1] Bioconductor
##  sessioninfo            * 1.2.2      2021-12-06 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  shiny                    1.7.4      2022-12-15 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  shinyWidgets             0.7.6      2023-01-08 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  SingleCellExperiment   * 1.22.0     2023-04-25 [1] Bioconductor
##  spam                     2.9-1      2022-08-07 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  sparseMatrixStats        1.12.0     2023-05-08 [1] Bioconductor
##  SpatialExperiment      * 1.10.0     2023-04-25 [1] Bioconductor
##  spatialLIBD            * 1.13.4     2023-05-24 [1] Github (LieberInstitute/spatialLIBD@edc8b72)
##  statmod                  1.5.0      2023-01-06 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  stringi                  1.7.12     2023-01-11 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  stringr                  1.5.0      2022-12-02 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  SummarizedExperiment   * 1.30.2     2023-06-11 [1] Bioconductor
##  tibble                   3.2.1      2023-03-20 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  tidyr                    1.3.0      2023-01-24 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  tidyselect               1.2.0      2022-10-10 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  timechange               0.2.0      2023-01-11 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  utf8                     1.2.3      2023-01-31 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  vctrs                    0.6.3      2023-06-14 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  vipor                    0.4.5      2017-03-22 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  viridis                  0.6.3      2023-05-03 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  viridisLite              0.4.2      2023-05-02 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  withr                    2.5.0      2022-03-03 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  xfun                     0.39       2023-04-20 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  XML                      3.99-0.14  2023-03-19 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  xml2                     1.3.4      2023-04-27 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  xtable                   1.8-4      2019-04-21 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  XVector                  0.40.0     2023-04-25 [1] Bioconductor
##  yaml                     2.3.7      2023-01-23 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  zlibbioc                 1.46.0     2023-04-25 [1] Bioconductor
## 
##  [1] /Library/Frameworks/R.framework/Versions/4.3-arm64/Resources/library
## 
## ──────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to write academic documents with GoogleDocs</title>
      <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2019/04/02/how-to-write-academic-documents-with-googledocs/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2019/04/02/how-to-write-academic-documents-with-googledocs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;These past months I’ve been mostly working on one &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; project which might be close to an end, hopefully! This project involves a massive manuscript with many supplementary figures and tables. Today we sent it out to other members in our team, and to celebrate, I’m now writing more 😅: though this is a blog post. I’m allowing myself to do so before I dive into the pile of tasks I haven’t completed&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. So I’m going to share with you the tools I’ve been using since 2018 or so for writing academic documents shared via &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/document/u/0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Google Docs&lt;/a&gt;. You can use these tools for manuscripts&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, capstone projects&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and well, basically any document where you want to do any of the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automatic figure/table numbering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Insert math equations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cite the literature&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, you can do both with &lt;code&gt;LaTeX&lt;/code&gt; and you can collaborate with others using &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.overleaf.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Overleaf&lt;/a&gt;, but it’s really hard to convince others to use &lt;code&gt;LaTeX&lt;/code&gt; in my experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;citations&#34;&gt;Citations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many tools out there for you to organize the literature items you are reading or keeping tabs on. Some of them are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zotero.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Zotero&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mendeley.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mendeley&lt;/a&gt;, which you might have heard about. The one that I highly recommend for writing documents with Google Docs is &lt;a href=&#34;https://f1000.com/work/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;F1000Workspace&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;get-an-account&#34;&gt;Get an account&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, you need to make an account. Worried about paying? Don’t worry, the accounts are &lt;strong&gt;free&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2019-04-02-how-to-write-academic-documents-with-googledocs_files/Screen%20Shot%202019-04-02%20at%205.37.26%20PM.png&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I strongly recommend that you use your academic email here if you have one, because I believe that it grants you access for an unlimited free account. Your university might also give you free access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;start-a-project&#34;&gt;Start a project&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have your account set up, start a &lt;em&gt;shared project&lt;/em&gt;. I mean, private ones also work, but shared ones allow you to collaborate with others so that your teammembers can also update the citations in your document. For example, we have one called &lt;code&gt;brainseq phase2&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2019-04-02-how-to-write-academic-documents-with-googledocs_files/Screen%20Shot%202019-04-02%20at%205.36.15%20PM.png&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2019-04-02-how-to-write-academic-documents-with-googledocs_files/Screen%20Shot%202019-04-02%20at%205.36.54%20PM.png&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you open your project page, at the top left you’ll see a big blue button called &lt;code&gt;Import References&lt;/code&gt;. Click on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2019-04-02-how-to-write-academic-documents-with-googledocs_files/Screen%20Shot%202019-04-02%20at%205.43.57%20PM.png&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, F1000Workspace allows you to import references from many different sources. I typically import using identifiers, either a &lt;code&gt;DOI&lt;/code&gt; or a &lt;code&gt;PMID&lt;/code&gt; one. They also have a browser add-on that you can use to import references into your library when using websites such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PubMed&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;insert-references-into-a-google-doc&#34;&gt;Insert references into a Google Doc&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On your Google Chrome browser, install the F1000Workspace Google Docs add-on available &lt;a href=&#34;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/f1000/daojhpgpccggokldfgfdmeckecckheej?utm_source=permalink&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Next, open up your Google Doc and you’ll see that &lt;code&gt;F1000&lt;/code&gt; appears in your toolbar. If you click on it, the F1000 interface will open on the right sidebar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2019-04-02-how-to-write-academic-documents-with-googledocs_files/Screen%20Shot%202019-04-02%20at%205.54.46%20PM.png&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That interface lets you link your Google Doc to a particular F1000Workspace project, which I recommend doing. You can then go to &lt;code&gt;Insert citations&lt;/code&gt; and start searching your project citations. I typically search by name or by the identifier, which is particularly useful if I just added the reference to the project via the identifier on a separate browser tab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2019-04-02-how-to-write-academic-documents-with-googledocs_files/Screen%20Shot%202019-04-02%20at%205.54.10%20PM.png&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-your-documents-bibliography&#34;&gt;Update your document’s bibliography&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lets say that you’ve added a few citations in your document and now want to format them appropriately. In your Google Doc, click on &lt;code&gt;F1000&lt;/code&gt;, then navigate to the &lt;code&gt;Format citations and bibliography&lt;/code&gt; section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2019-04-02-how-to-write-academic-documents-with-googledocs_files/Screen%20Shot%202019-04-02%20at%205.57.12%20PM.png&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before you click the big blue button that says &lt;code&gt;Update citations and bibliography&lt;/code&gt; you’ll notice a dropdown menu that lets you choose your favorite citation style (or whichever the journal you want to send your manuscript requires).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The end!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;notes&#34;&gt;Notes&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, not really. You’ll likely keep adding many citations as you keep working on your document. One thing that I’ve noticed is that the F1000Workspace add-on has a bit of trouble under “suggesting” mode or when the citation was inserted as a suggestion. So I recommend that you accept the suggestion first, then use “editing” mode for updating your bibliography file. It’s always good to keep an eye on what the add-on is doing so you can notice anything weird and undo it with ctrl + z (cmd + z in macOS).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And hey, did you know that F1000Workspace also works with Microsoft Word?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more details, check the &lt;a href=&#34;https://f1000.com/work/#/faq/google-docs-add-on&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;FAQs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://player.vimeo.com/video/153753002&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; title=&#34;vimeo video&#34; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://player.vimeo.com/video/141798183&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; title=&#34;vimeo video&#34; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;automatic-figure-numbering&#34;&gt;Automatic figure numbering&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we have figured out citations in Google Docs, lets learn how to cross reference figures, tables, equations, and whatever else you want. This is something that &lt;code&gt;LaTeX&lt;/code&gt; users are familiar with but that you can’t do out of the box in Google Docs or Microsoft Word (as far as I know). Luckily others have made add-ons that solve this problem. The one I use, and so do other 11,197 people as of today, is &lt;code&gt;Cross Reference&lt;/code&gt; available from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/cross-reference/hknkaiempgninehdhkgekoeoilkapgob?utm_source=permalink&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Google Chrome Store&lt;/a&gt; for free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This add-on allows the user to label equations, figures and tables and refer to them within the text. It now also allows users to create labels for any element. These elements are numbered automatically and references are updated to match. If their order changes, references update to match. If one is removed, references to it are highlighted in red in the text. The text and style of references and labels can be customised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Insert labels and references as hyperlinks. Instead of a URL, add a code recognised by Cross Reference, then an underscore, then your choice of name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;configuration&#34;&gt;Configuration&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you install &lt;code&gt;Cross Reference&lt;/code&gt;, you’ll see it listed under the &lt;code&gt;Add-ons&lt;/code&gt; menu in your Google Doc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2019-04-02-how-to-write-academic-documents-with-googledocs_files/Screen%20Shot%202019-04-02%20at%206.12.03%20PM.png&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll see all the different types of elements that you have configured with &lt;code&gt;Cross Reference&lt;/code&gt;. Some come out of the box, like &lt;code&gt;Figures&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2019-04-02-how-to-write-academic-documents-with-googledocs_files/Screen%20Shot%202019-04-02%20at%206.14.07%20PM.png&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For every element you have to configure the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The code you will use for the label, here &lt;code&gt;#figur&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The text that will be displayed before the number. In this case, &lt;code&gt;Figure&lt;/code&gt; (yes, there’s a space there).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The style of the label; bold here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then the same thing for the reference. In this case, the code for the reference is &lt;code&gt;#fig&lt;/code&gt;. The codes have to be at least 3 characters long for the references and 5 characters long for the labels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my documents I typically add configurations for supplementary figures and tables using:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;type&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;code: label&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;code: reference&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;text&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Supplementary Figure&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;#sfigu&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;#sfi&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;Figure S&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Supplementary Table&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;#stabl&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;#sta&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;Table S&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Supplementary File&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;#supfi&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;#sup&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;Supplementary File&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;usage&#34;&gt;Usage&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that you have configured &lt;code&gt;Cross Reference&lt;/code&gt; you can start using it. Lets say that I want to write the text &lt;code&gt;We did many things (Figure S1)&lt;/code&gt; where &lt;code&gt;Figure S1&lt;/code&gt; links to my overview figure whose description starts &lt;code&gt;Figure S1. Overview of my project&lt;/code&gt;. Since we are talking about the overview figure, lets use &lt;code&gt;_overview&lt;/code&gt; as the unique identifier for this figure. As this is a supplementary figure, the label code is &lt;code&gt;#sfigu&lt;/code&gt; and the reference code is &lt;code&gt;#sfi&lt;/code&gt;. Meaning that we must write the label code once in the figure description using &lt;code&gt;#sfigu_overview&lt;/code&gt; and we can reference to it as many times as we want using &lt;code&gt;#sfi_overview&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last tricky part is that you can write whatever you want, lets say &lt;code&gt;hello&lt;/code&gt;, and then you need to create a link (shortcut is cmd + k in macOS) with the correct code (either the reference or the label one). So the text that you would write would be &lt;code&gt;We did many things ([hello](#sfi_overview))&lt;/code&gt; and later on when you describe the overview figure you need &lt;code&gt;[whatever you want](#sfi_overview). Overview of my project&lt;/code&gt; where here I’m using the Markdown syntax for links: &lt;code&gt;[text](link)&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve inserted the links both for the reference and the label, you can then go to &lt;code&gt;Add-ons&lt;/code&gt;, navigate to &lt;code&gt;Cross Reference&lt;/code&gt; and click &lt;code&gt;Update document&lt;/code&gt;. Doing so will change the text you had initially filed in for the correct text. So it will look like this: &lt;code&gt;We did many things ([Figure S1](#sfi_overview))&lt;/code&gt; plus &lt;code&gt;[Figure S1](#sfi_overview). Overview of my project&lt;/code&gt;. Here’s a real case example where my identifier for the first supplementary figure is &lt;code&gt;_rna&lt;/code&gt;, thus the full reference code is &lt;code&gt;#sfi_rna&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2019-04-02-how-to-write-academic-documents-with-googledocs_files/Screen%20Shot%202019-04-02%20at%206.32.29%20PM.png&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And you are done!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;notes-1&#34;&gt;Notes&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number used for the item your reference depends on what order the reference codes are listed in the Google Doc. To check that the numbering order is correct (Table S1 appears in the text before Table S2, etc), I recommend opening your google document in two separate tabs. In one tab, you start reading your document from the top. If you encounter items out of order, then on tab two you can switch them around. That way you don’t have to scroll around and waste time, which is a more cumbersome problem as the document gets longer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, this process that takes a bit of time and can break due to a typo. So I highly recommend that you update your cross references as soon as you make a new one, so you can easily trace any typos and fix them easily. If you don’t, then it can become very hard to track down what went wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;equations&#34;&gt;Equations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, lets say that you want to insert equations. You can insert some equations with Google Docs, but you might want more fine control. If you use &lt;code&gt;LaTeX&lt;/code&gt; I recommend the &lt;code&gt;Auto-LaTeX Equations&lt;/code&gt; add-on available from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/auto-latex-equations/iaainhiejkciadlhlodaajgbffkebdog?utm_source=permalink&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Google Chrome Store&lt;/a&gt; for free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This add-on lets you automatically convert every LaTeX equation in your document into beautiful images! Simply enclose your math equations within $$ &amp;hellip; $$ and click the button in the sidebar, and all of your equations will be rendered in LaTeX!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s as simple as it sounds. What this add-on does is that it takes your &lt;code&gt;LaTeX&lt;/code&gt; equation code, renders an image with the equation, and then inserts it back into your Google Doc. It also enables you to restore the &lt;code&gt;LaTeX&lt;/code&gt; equation code so you can edit it if you find a typo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;wrapping-up&#34;&gt;Wrapping up&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope that you’ll find this blog post / tutorial useful when writing your own academic documents. These tools have saved me so much time when writing academic documents in collaboration with others. I don’t want to imagine having to re-number all the references manually whenever we added each of the 48 supplementary figures, 17 supplementary tables, and 11 equations to the project we are about to complete 😱.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;acknowledgments&#34;&gt;Acknowledgments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors of F1000Workspace, Cross Reference and Auto-LaTeX equations add-ons have made my life much easier. THANK YOU!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog post was made possible thanks to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://bioconductor.org/packages/3.17/BiocStyle&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;BiocStyle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Oles_2023&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://bioconductor.org/packages/BiocStyle&#39;&gt;Oleś, 2023&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=blogdown&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;blogdown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Xie_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown/&#39;&gt;Xie, Hill, and Thomas, 2017&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;knitcitations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Boettiger_2021&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&#39;&gt;Boettiger, 2021&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=sessioninfo&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;sessioninfo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Wickham_2021&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=sessioninfo&#39;&gt;Wickham, Chang, Flight, Müller et al., 2021&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Boettiger_2021&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Boettiger_2021&#34;&gt;\[1\]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt;
C. Boettiger.
&lt;em&gt;knitcitations: Citations for ‘Knitr’ Markdown Files&lt;/em&gt;.
R package version 1.0.12.
2021.
URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Oles_2023&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Oles_2023&#34;&gt;\[2\]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt;
A. Oleś.
&lt;em&gt;BiocStyle: Standard styles for vignettes and other Bioconductor documents&lt;/em&gt;.
R package version 2.28.0.
2023.
DOI: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.18129/B9.bioc.BiocStyle&#34;&gt;10.18129/B9.bioc.BiocStyle&lt;/a&gt;.
URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://bioconductor.org/packages/BiocStyle&#34;&gt;https://bioconductor.org/packages/BiocStyle&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Wickham_2021&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Wickham_2021&#34;&gt;\[3\]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt;
H. Wickham, W. Chang, R. Flight, K. Müller, et al.
&lt;em&gt;sessioninfo: R Session Information&lt;/em&gt;.
R package version 1.2.2.
2021.
URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=sessioninfo&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=sessioninfo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Xie_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Xie_2017&#34;&gt;\[4\]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt;
Y. Xie, A. P. Hill, and A. Thomas.
&lt;em&gt;blogdown: Creating Websites with R Markdown&lt;/em&gt;.
Boca Raton, Florida: Chapman and Hall/CRC, 2017.
ISBN: 978-0815363729.
URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown/&#34;&gt;https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;reproducibility&#34;&gt;Reproducibility&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## ─ Session info ───────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────
##  setting  value
##  version  R version 4.3.1 (2023-06-16)
##  os       macOS Ventura 13.4
##  system   aarch64, darwin20
##  ui       X11
##  language (EN)
##  collate  en_US.UTF-8
##  ctype    en_US.UTF-8
##  tz       America/New_York
##  date     2023-07-11
##  pandoc   3.1.5 @ /opt/homebrew/bin/ (via rmarkdown)
## 
## ─ Packages ───────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────
##  package       * version    date (UTC) lib source
##  backports       1.4.1      2021-12-13 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  bibtex          0.5.1      2023-01-26 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  BiocManager     1.30.21    2023-06-10 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  BiocStyle     * 2.28.0     2023-04-25 [1] Bioconductor
##  blogdown        1.18       2023-06-19 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  bookdown        0.34       2023-05-09 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  bslib           0.5.0      2023-06-09 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  cachem          1.0.8      2023-05-01 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  cli             3.6.1      2023-03-23 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  colorout        1.2-2      2023-05-06 [1] Github (jalvesaq/colorout@79931fd)
##  digest          0.6.31     2022-12-11 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  evaluate        0.21       2023-05-05 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  fastmap         1.1.1      2023-02-24 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  generics        0.1.3      2022-07-05 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  glue            1.6.2      2022-02-24 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  htmltools       0.5.5      2023-03-23 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  httr            1.4.6      2023-05-08 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  jquerylib       0.1.4      2021-04-26 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  jsonlite        1.8.7      2023-06-29 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  knitcitations * 1.0.12     2021-01-10 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  knitr           1.43       2023-05-25 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  lifecycle       1.0.3      2022-10-07 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  lubridate       1.9.2      2023-02-10 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  magrittr        2.0.3      2022-03-30 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  plyr            1.8.8      2022-11-11 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  R6              2.5.1      2021-08-19 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  Rcpp            1.0.10     2023-01-22 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  RefManageR      1.4.0      2022-09-30 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  rlang           1.1.1      2023-04-28 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  rmarkdown       2.23       2023-07-01 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  rstudioapi      0.14       2022-08-22 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  sass            0.4.6.9000 2023-05-06 [1] Github (rstudio/sass@f248fe5)
##  sessioninfo   * 1.2.2      2021-12-06 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  stringi         1.7.12     2023-01-11 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  stringr         1.5.0      2022-12-02 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  timechange      0.2.0      2023-01-11 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  xfun            0.39       2023-04-20 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  xml2            1.3.4      2023-04-27 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  yaml            2.3.7      2023-01-23 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
## 
##  [1] /Library/Frameworks/R.framework/Versions/4.3-arm64/Resources/library
## 
## ──────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Including answering some questions on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://support.bioconductor.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Bioconductor support forum&lt;/a&gt;, finishing another manuscript, etc.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like this &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2018/09/26/426213&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;one&lt;/a&gt; or this other &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2018/09/29/428391&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;one&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like my former student &lt;a href=&#34;https://amy-peterson.github.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Amy Peterson&lt;/a&gt; did in 2018.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For up to 3 projects.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I applied to join SNI: the Mexican National Researchers registry</title>
      <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/09/29/why-i-applied-to-join-sni-the-mexican-national-researchers-registry/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/09/29/why-i-applied-to-join-sni-the-mexican-national-researchers-registry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A few days ago a friend of mine told me that I was on the list of newly admitted SNI members. A few have asked me since why did I request to join it. So here’s my public reply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;es&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Woo! Ya soy &amp;quot;Investigador Nacional Nivel I&amp;quot; en el Sistema Nacional de Investigadores de CONACyT en México &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Conacyt_MX?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@Conacyt_MX&lt;/a&gt; 🎉💪🏾🇲🇽&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I&amp;#39;m a National Researcher lvl I in the Mexican National Researchers Registry ^_^ 🎆🎉&lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/hud7Z22WLY&#34;&gt;https://t.co/hud7Z22WLY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Gracias &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/malacopa_genome?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@malacopa_genome&lt;/a&gt; por el aviso! &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/NWnf90KOF1&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/NWnf90KOF1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; 🇲🇽 Leonardo Collado-Torres (@lcolladotor) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/lcolladotor/status/1045051193146396674?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;September 26, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;sni&#34;&gt;SNI&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First let me tell you what SNI is. It stands for &lt;em&gt;Sistema Nacional de Investigadores&lt;/em&gt; which translates to National Researchers Registry. It’s a way that the Mexican government created in 1984 to recognize &lt;em&gt;high&lt;/em&gt; quality researchers and encourage them to continue to do great research, teach the next generation of researchers and promote innovation (&lt;a href=&#34;https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sistema_Nacional_de_Investigadores_%28M%C3%A9xico%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;). There are three types of members:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Candidato a Investigador Nacional&lt;/em&gt;: Candidate to National Researcher&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Investigador Nacional&lt;/em&gt;: National Researchers with 3 levels (1, 2 and 3)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Investigador Nacional Emérito&lt;/em&gt;: National Emeritus Researcher&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To become a member you have to submit documentation to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Conacyt_MX&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CONACyT&lt;/a&gt; showing that you have made contributions to science, technology, culture and society through scientific or technological developments, training new students, popularizing or translating science and technology, among other criteria. Once you are a member, you have to keep submitting new documents every couple of years to stay a member or advance in the ranks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-real-reason-behind-joining-sni&#34;&gt;The &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; reason behind joining SNI&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve read a little bit that there are many critics of the SNI system. Most of the criticisms are based on how they decide what is a &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; contribution and how they judge applications. The reality is also that the process of sending the necessary documentation is cumbersome to say the least. The CONACyT website breaks often enough that it can be painful to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why do people want to join the SNI and go through all this complicated process? The main reason (I think) why people want to join the SNI is because being a member comes with a financial supplement. It’s enough that I’ve heard that it can constitute about a third of your salary. You can find headlines such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.elfinanciero.com.mx/empresas/apoyo-del-conacyt-a-investigadores-paso-de-privilegio-a-sueldo&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;how CONACyT’s support to researchers went from a priviledge to a salary&lt;/a&gt;. This financial supplement is given to those members that work 20 hours a week on Mexican institutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given how important this boost in salary is, I can understand very well the frustrations that come with interacting with the CONACyT website: specially when the website goes down and you have to submit your application before a given deadline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;so-why-did-i-apply-to-join-sni&#34;&gt;So why did I apply to join SNI?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find on CONACyT’s website an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.conacytprensa.mx/index.php/sociedad/politica-cientifica/7698-por-que-es-importante-pertenecer-al-sni&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;interview on why it’s important to join SNI&lt;/a&gt; or go elsewhere to read a study on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://sinectica.iteso.mx/index.php/SINECTICA/article/view/155/786&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;motivations people have for joining SNI&lt;/a&gt;. But why did I apply to join SNI given that I’m outside Mexico and won’t be getting the financial supplement?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My main motivation was protection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lets say that I return to Mexico as a researcher at UNAM or another Mexican institution. Currently there is only 1 call for new SNI members per year. If I were to return today (September 2018), I would need to wait several months for the 2019 application cycle. Then I would need to wait several months for all applications to be evaluated and would probably start receiving the financial salary boost on January 2020. That is a lot of time to wait!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, right now I don’t need the salary boost. But if I were to return then it could be a significant portion of my salary. Having all this riding on a cumbersome application (I’d be afraid of making a silly mistake in the application) and on an external evaluation would be stressful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the stakes for me were low right now. Now that I’m a SNI member if I were to return to Mexico I could start receiving that financial boost much sooner. Thus I’m also protecting myself by keeping my options open to stay abroad (in the US for me) or return to Mexico. For example, I have a verbal agreement with my boss on the length of my current job, but technically I’m an employee at will and can be fired pretty easily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also applied because I have several friends that were applying or recently applied and helped me a lot navigate the application process&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Also, you never know if the application process will change and become more complicated later on: though I hope that it will get easier!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But back to protection and security. My father has taught me that it’s our responsibility to cover our backs. Lets imagine that I have dependents. It would be irresponsible of me to miss out on the financial supplement because I didn’t send my documentation on time or because I forgot to send in the renewal documents: maybe it wouldn’t affect me, but it would affect them. Completing my application in time is under my control. What CONACyT cares about, their evaluation process, the clarity and reliability of their website are not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;beyond-sni&#34;&gt;Beyond SNI&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This attitude goes beyond SNI. That is why I compete when I can for awards and scholarships that I think fit me, even if its a long shot. No one will come to you and say, “hey, your work is great, now you are a SNI member” (or any award). I believe that you have to keep working and make it hard for others to say no to your applications. You have to keep trying though because you won’t get them all. That was one of my messages in my recent CDSBMexico keynote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Here are my slides for my &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/CDSBMexico?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#CDSBMexico&lt;/a&gt; remote talk tomorrow for day 1 of the &amp;quot;Latin American R/BioConductor Developers Workshop 2018&amp;quot;. 70 slides for ~20 min, I can do this! 💪🏾 Right &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jtleek?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@jtleek&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Shannon_E_Ellis?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@Shannon_E_Ellis&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/xKh2214YbM&#34;&gt;https://t.co/xKh2214YbM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/rstats?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#rstats&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/teaching?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#teaching&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Bioconductor?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@Bioconductor&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/CDSBMexico?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@CDSBMexico&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/SULAoPbHeZ&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/SULAoPbHeZ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; 🇲🇽 Leonardo Collado-Torres (@lcolladotor) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/lcolladotor/status/1023665229882961922?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 29, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some of my recent applications:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;You still have time to participate in this year&amp;#39;s SciLifeLab prize! I wrote a blog post about it &amp;amp; shared my unsuccessful 2017 entry &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/6y7DOP1m1a&#34;&gt;https://t.co/6y7DOP1m1a&lt;/a&gt; Got Qs? SciLifeLabPrize@aaas.org &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ScienceMagazine?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@sciencemagazine&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/academia?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#academia&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/science?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#science&lt;/a&gt; Thx &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jtleek?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@jtleek&lt;/a&gt; for the last minute recommendation letter! &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/Yfyq7j9RTc&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/Yfyq7j9RTc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; 🇲🇽 Leonardo Collado-Torres (@lcolladotor) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/lcolladotor/status/1009559232931401730?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 20, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Check our &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/Bioinformatics?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#Bioinformatics&lt;/a&gt; Peer Prize III entry at &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/WdggoD6KPh&#34;&gt;https://t.co/WdggoD6KPh&lt;/a&gt; highlighting recount2 &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/tK6iRfUT21&#34;&gt;https://t.co/tK6iRfUT21&lt;/a&gt; We appreciate the votes! Team submission w @AbhiNellore et al &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/RNAseq?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#RNAseq&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/rstats?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#rstats&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/reproducibility?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#reproducibility&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/scitwitter?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#scitwitter&lt;/a&gt; Video code &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/J0nwUcV3O4&#34;&gt;https://t.co/J0nwUcV3O4&lt;/a&gt; w ari &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/seankross?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@seankross&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; 🇲🇽 Leonardo Collado-Torres (@lcolladotor) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/lcolladotor/status/960590896310968320?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;February 5, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I just submitted my rstudio::conf(2019) diversity scholarship app &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/nmZY7UJsiP&#34;&gt;https://t.co/nmZY7UJsiP&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/rstudio?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@rstudio&lt;/a&gt; Text entries have a 1000 char limit!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I&amp;#39;m sharing mine &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/q3wqbSuVbW&#34;&gt;https://t.co/q3wqbSuVbW&lt;/a&gt; in case it helps other &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/LIBDrstats?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@LIBDrstats&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/CDSBMexico?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@CDSBMexico&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/rstats?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#rstats&lt;/a&gt; members at large.&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/tip?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#tip&lt;/a&gt; Always ask for help!&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; 🇲🇽 Leonardo Collado-Torres (@lcolladotor) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/lcolladotor/status/1032287739176267776?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;August 22, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I just submitted my application for the &amp;quot;Early Career Clinical Research Symbiont Award&amp;quot;. If I get selected, then I&amp;#39;ll be able to attend &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/PSB19?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#PSB19&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/PacSymBiocomp?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@PacSymBiocomp&lt;/a&gt;. Thx to someone who prompted me to send my application! You should submit yours too. Deadline 9/30 &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/Pv1aHySVbI&#34;&gt;https://t.co/Pv1aHySVbI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; 🇲🇽 Leonardo Collado-Torres (@lcolladotor) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/lcolladotor/status/1045763904964612096?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;September 28, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what happens now? I updated my CV as a friend suggested to list that I’m a SNI National Researcher Level 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;acknowledgments&#34;&gt;Acknowledgments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to thank my friends that helped me during the SNI application process!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;es&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Gracias &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/sur_hp?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@sur_hp&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/FSanchezQuinto?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@FSanchezQuinto&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mariagutierrez?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@mariagutierrez&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/areyesq?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@areyesq&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/malacopa_genome?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@malacopa_genome&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mgschiavon?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@mgschiavon&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/AleMedinaRivera?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@AleMedinaRivera&lt;/a&gt; por el apoyo en todo el proceso de enviar la solicitud y motivarme a enviarla!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Ahora.... me falta obtener la FIEL para firmar el doc de &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Conacyt_MX?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@Conacyt_MX&lt;/a&gt; (creo)... ugh!&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; 🇲🇽 Leonardo Collado-Torres (@lcolladotor) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/lcolladotor/status/1045053659967639555?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;September 26, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog post was made possible thanks to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://bioconductor.org/packages/3.17/BiocStyle&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;BiocStyle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Oles_2023&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://bioconductor.org/packages/BiocStyle&#39;&gt;Oleś, 2023&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=blogdown&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;blogdown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Xie_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown/&#39;&gt;Xie, Hill, and Thomas, 2017&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=sessioninfo&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;sessioninfo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Wickham_2021&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=sessioninfo&#39;&gt;Wickham, Chang, Flight, Müller et al., 2021&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;knitcitations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Boettiger_2021&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&#39;&gt;Boettiger, 2021&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Boettiger_2021&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Boettiger_2021&#34;&gt;\[1\]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt;
C. Boettiger.
&lt;em&gt;knitcitations: Citations for ‘Knitr’ Markdown Files&lt;/em&gt;.
R package version 1.0.12.
2021.
URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Oles_2023&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Oles_2023&#34;&gt;\[2\]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt;
A. Oleś.
&lt;em&gt;BiocStyle: Standard styles for vignettes and other Bioconductor documents&lt;/em&gt;.
R package version 2.28.0.
2023.
DOI: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.18129/B9.bioc.BiocStyle&#34;&gt;10.18129/B9.bioc.BiocStyle&lt;/a&gt;.
URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://bioconductor.org/packages/BiocStyle&#34;&gt;https://bioconductor.org/packages/BiocStyle&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Wickham_2021&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Wickham_2021&#34;&gt;\[3\]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt;
H. Wickham, W. Chang, R. Flight, K. Müller, et al.
&lt;em&gt;sessioninfo: R Session Information&lt;/em&gt;.
R package version 1.2.2.
2021.
URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=sessioninfo&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=sessioninfo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Xie_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Xie_2017&#34;&gt;\[4\]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt;
Y. Xie, A. P. Hill, and A. Thomas.
&lt;em&gt;blogdown: Creating Websites with R Markdown&lt;/em&gt;.
Boca Raton, Florida: Chapman and Hall/CRC, 2017.
ISBN: 978-0815363729.
URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown/&#34;&gt;https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;reproducibility&#34;&gt;Reproducibility&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## ─ Session info ───────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────
##  setting  value
##  version  R version 4.3.1 (2023-06-16)
##  os       macOS Ventura 13.4
##  system   aarch64, darwin20
##  ui       X11
##  language (EN)
##  collate  en_US.UTF-8
##  ctype    en_US.UTF-8
##  tz       America/New_York
##  date     2023-07-11
##  pandoc   3.1.5 @ /opt/homebrew/bin/ (via rmarkdown)
## 
## ─ Packages ───────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────
##  package       * version    date (UTC) lib source
##  backports       1.4.1      2021-12-13 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  bibtex          0.5.1      2023-01-26 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  BiocManager     1.30.21    2023-06-10 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  BiocStyle     * 2.28.0     2023-04-25 [1] Bioconductor
##  blogdown        1.18       2023-06-19 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  bookdown        0.34       2023-05-09 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  bslib           0.5.0      2023-06-09 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  cachem          1.0.8      2023-05-01 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  cli             3.6.1      2023-03-23 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  colorout        1.2-2      2023-05-06 [1] Github (jalvesaq/colorout@79931fd)
##  digest          0.6.31     2022-12-11 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  evaluate        0.21       2023-05-05 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  fastmap         1.1.1      2023-02-24 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  generics        0.1.3      2022-07-05 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  glue            1.6.2      2022-02-24 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  htmltools       0.5.5      2023-03-23 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  httr            1.4.6      2023-05-08 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  jquerylib       0.1.4      2021-04-26 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  jsonlite        1.8.7      2023-06-29 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  knitcitations * 1.0.12     2021-01-10 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  knitr           1.43       2023-05-25 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  lifecycle       1.0.3      2022-10-07 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  lubridate       1.9.2      2023-02-10 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  magrittr        2.0.3      2022-03-30 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  plyr            1.8.8      2022-11-11 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  R6              2.5.1      2021-08-19 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  Rcpp            1.0.10     2023-01-22 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  RefManageR      1.4.0      2022-09-30 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  rlang           1.1.1      2023-04-28 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  rmarkdown       2.23       2023-07-01 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  rstudioapi      0.14       2022-08-22 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  sass            0.4.6.9000 2023-05-06 [1] Github (rstudio/sass@f248fe5)
##  sessioninfo   * 1.2.2      2021-12-06 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  stringi         1.7.12     2023-01-11 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  stringr         1.5.0      2022-12-02 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  timechange      0.2.0      2023-01-11 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  xfun            0.39       2023-04-20 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  xml2            1.3.4      2023-04-27 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  yaml            2.3.7      2023-01-23 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
## 
##  [1] /Library/Frameworks/R.framework/Versions/4.3-arm64/Resources/library
## 
## ──────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, we are still trying to find out how we can sign the agreement from abroad.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Harassment, diversity in science and inspiration from my grandmother</title>
      <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/07/30/harassment-diversity-in-science-and-inspiration-from-my-grandmother/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/07/30/harassment-diversity-in-science-and-inspiration-from-my-grandmother/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today was a big day. I care about many things including diversity in science (STEM) and building a community of R users and developers in Mexico. Both moved forward in two completely separate conferences: one in Mexico: &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/search?q=jsm2018&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CDSBMexico&lt;/a&gt;; and one in Canada: &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/search?q=jsm2018&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;JSM2018&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;cdsbmexico&#34;&gt;CDSBMexico&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a very important day for me. It was the beginning of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://comunidadbioinfo.github.io/post/r-bioconductor-developers-workshop-2018/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Latin American R/BioConductor Developers Workshop 2018&lt;/a&gt; in Cuernavaca, Mexico. I already wrote a blog post about &lt;a href=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/04/19/latin-american-r-bioconductor-developers-workshop-2018/#.W1-lhNhKi50&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;why I was super excited about CDSBMexico&lt;/a&gt;, but briefly it’s because this is something we’ve been wanting to see become a reality for years and have been working towards it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Here are my slides for my &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/CDSBMexico?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#CDSBMexico&lt;/a&gt; remote talk tomorrow for day 1 of the &amp;quot;Latin American R/BioConductor Developers Workshop 2018&amp;quot;. 70 slides for ~20 min, I can do this! 💪🏾 Right &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jtleek?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@jtleek&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Shannon_E_Ellis?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@Shannon_E_Ellis&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/xKh2214YbM&#34;&gt;https://t.co/xKh2214YbM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/rstats?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#rstats&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/teaching?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#teaching&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Bioconductor?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@Bioconductor&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/CDSBMexico?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@CDSBMexico&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/SULAoPbHeZ&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/SULAoPbHeZ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; 🇲🇽 Leonardo Collado-Torres (@lcolladotor) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/lcolladotor/status/1023665229882961922?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 29, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My job was to give the first keynote to pump up everyone at the workshop. So I had a bit of trouble sleeping and woke up remembering a dream. If you know me, I &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; dream: or never remember my dreams. It was a dream of my grandmother Mercedes Vides Tovar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-07-30-harrassment-diversity-in-science-and-inspiraton-from-my-grandmother_files/2018-07-30%2018.15.38.jpg&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; /&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;grandma&#34;&gt;Grandma&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have many things from my grandparents in me, like Juan’s joviality, Rosa’s love, Rolando’s tenacity to overcome tough moments. Or so I like to think. But my grandma, &lt;em&gt;Abue&lt;/em&gt;, has always been an academic inspiration. She overcame many challenges in her life. She studied at the university to become a doctor, even without total family support (to avoid details). She was a trailblazer in the field of Epidemiology. She had to flee her native country leaving everything behind. She studied at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pasteur.fr/en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Institut Pasteur&lt;/a&gt; in Paris, France while caring for 3 adolescents as a single mom. She studied in a time when &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/search?q=womeninstem&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;WomenInSTEM&lt;/a&gt; had to disguise themselves up as men and were the targets of jokes all the time. Rolando, her classmate at the university, has told me a handful of these &lt;em&gt;jokes&lt;/em&gt;: I wouldn’t be the only one to call many of them harassment. She left academia to start her own business in public health. She was the main health supervisor in the first international conference my dad organized early in his career (which helped him launch it): I was the 6 year old in charge of delivering the gifts in the closing ceremony ^^. She would answer my phone calls when I first started French school and my dad was busy at work: thanks to their time in Paris my dad fell in love with the French way of teaching math.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-07-30-harrassment-diversity-in-science-and-inspiraton-from-my-grandmother_files/2018-07-30%2018.41.52.jpg&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I actually don’t know much more. She passed away when I was 13 after a years long battle with disease. Google tells me that she is a co-author of at least three titles in the field of Public Health:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1968 &lt;a href=&#34;http://saludpublica.mx/index.php/spm/article/download/3327/3212&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Organización del servicio social de los pasantes de Odontología en México&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1970 &lt;a href=&#34;http://saludpublica.mx/index.php/spm/article/viewFile/2346/2234&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Situación epidemiológica de la frontera norte de México y programa de vigilancia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1972 &lt;a href=&#34;http://saludpublica.mx/index.php/spm/article/download/1874/1822&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Proyecto de organización y funcionamiento de los laboratorios de salud pública en los estados de la frontera norte&lt;/a&gt;: also, she’s the sole author.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-07-30-harrassment-diversity-in-science-and-inspiraton-from-my-grandmother_files/2018-07-30%2017.22.57.jpg&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did inherit her souvenirs from her trips (my dad also loves them) and something that is precious to me: a medal with her name. I’ve looked at that medal next to my bed in Mexico many times. I would look at it, search for inspiration, then try harder to solve whatever academic problem I had.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my dream there was a moment where I was sitting next to her (me in my current adult form) and we were revising many of our shared moments. She was explaining to me things she couldn’t explain before because I wouldn’t have understood them. She also pumped me up before my day and wished me luck for my talk. I think that I delivered ^^&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;es&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/CDSBMexico?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@CDSBMexico&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/fellgernon?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@fellgernon&lt;/a&gt; dio una charla inspiradora &amp;lt;3 &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/collaboration?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#collaboration&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/rstats?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#rstats&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/TIBs2018?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#TIBs2018&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/nnb_unam?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@nnb_unam&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Semiramis (@semiramis_cj) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/semiramis_cj/status/1023953817187090435?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 30, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;womeninstem&#34;&gt;WomenInStem&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today was a big day for &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/search?q=womeninstem&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;WomenInSTEM&lt;/a&gt; and in particular in the field of Statistics. Why? Today the Joint Statistical Meetings (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/search?q=jsm2018&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;JSM2018&lt;/a&gt;) held a session on “Addressing Sexual Misconduct in Statistics” that was organized by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/stephaniehicks&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stephanie Hicks&lt;/a&gt; and chaired by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/keegankorthauer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Keegan Korthauer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;For &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/JSM2018?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#JSM2018&lt;/a&gt;, I organized a session on Addressing Sexual Misconduct in Statistics. If you plan to attend the meeting, I invite you to join us &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/UxpUiqPzTy&#34;&gt;https://t.co/UxpUiqPzTy&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/IdShEPlqi6&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/IdShEPlqi6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Stephanie Hicks (@stephaniehicks.bsky.social) (@stephaniehicks) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/stephaniehicks/status/1004467110918213637?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 6, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The session is not a direct response (I think) but it’s definitely related to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/KLdivergence&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Kristian Lum&lt;/a&gt;’s blog post titled &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@kristianlum/statistics-we-have-a-problem-304638dc5de5&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Statistics, we have a problem&lt;/a&gt; and to the more general &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/search?q=metoo&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;MeToo&lt;/a&gt; movement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sexual harassment and misconduct not a US problem only. We have a code of conduct at &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/CDSBMexico&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CDSBMexico&lt;/a&gt; both in &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ComunidadBioInfo/R-BioConductor-Developers-Workshop-2018/blob/master/R-Bioconductor-2018_Program.rmd#code-of-conduct&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;English&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://comunidadbioinfo.github.io/codigo-de-conducta/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Spanish&lt;/a&gt; to help prevent any issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Q by me: what to do when people outside the U.S. say that this is an American problem and they don&amp;#39;t need to have a code of conduct for their meeting? &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/JSM2018?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#JSM2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Michael Hoffman @michaelhoffman.bsky.social (@michaelhoffman) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/michaelhoffman/status/1024060403138142209?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 30, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t be there, but I wasn’t the only one excited following what has happening online thanks to tweets from many including &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mandyfmejia&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mandy Mejia&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/michaelhoffman&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Michael Hoffman&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;THIS IS ACTUALLY HAPPENING. Now in CC-West Ballroom A. &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/JSM2018?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#JSM2018&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/Pw9zdlhi02&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/Pw9zdlhi02&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Mandy Mejia, PhD (@mandyfmejia) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mandyfmejia/status/1024042337033285632?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 30, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;times-are-changing&#34;&gt;Times are changing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do think that slowly, maybe sometimes quickly, the times are changing. I’ve been telling friends and family for a few years now that I’ve come to realize that we need to keep trying to improve, to stay updated, to do what’s best and maybe sometimes come up with new ideas to improve things. I do care quite a bit for &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/search?q=womeninstem&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;WomenInSTEM&lt;/a&gt; but for me, it’s larger than that. It’s about diversity. I don’t know in how many different ways we can label each other and it’s not the point. So yes, gender diversity is a good thing and initiatives like this seem like a good thing to do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Looks like a good thing to do. &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/m2sjLYB1Er&#34;&gt;https://t.co/m2sjLYB1Er&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/ashg18?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#ashg18&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/iKofjrIKTx&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/iKofjrIKTx&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; 🇲🇽 Leonardo Collado-Torres (@lcolladotor) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/lcolladotor/status/1024068383564853248?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 30, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then I think immediately of next steps, like race and ethnicity as well as sexual diversity. I want to ask for more, but I sometimes hold myself back. I’m no expert on many of these topics, so maybe what seems like a good policy could easily backfire later. So I think about incremental steps. But maybe that’s too slow and not enough. Maybe careers are suffering but I guess that as a community we are going as safely and fast as we can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;This 💯! My career trajectory would have been completely different in absence of hostile environments. &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/aqmQtVyXUW&#34;&gt;https://t.co/aqmQtVyXUW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Dr. Elana J Fertig (@FertigLab) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/FertigLab/status/1024044326664527875?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 30, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not supporting whoever Michael was referencing in his next tweet. I don’t flirt at conferences: I do socialize and try to make new friends with fellow conference attendees. I do acknowledge that I struggle in my head with what is ok and not ok to do, particularly with people you spend at lot of time with at school, work, etc. I’m not certain of the boundary between clumsy dating skills and sexual misconduct in some scenarios. I think that I’m not the only one because I’ve heard different versions in different sexual harassment prevention sessions. So mostly I end up doing nothing yet sometimes I wonder if I lost out because I didn’t try a bit more with X person. For instance, Mercedes maried her classmate Rolando. What can I say, I’m still learning and we all probably need to learn to differentiate these boundaries better through more training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;We ran out of time so we didn&amp;#39;t get to hear the question from the dude who was saying that something (I presume flirting at conferences) was &amp;quot;human nature&amp;quot;. Our loss, I&amp;#39;m sure &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/JSM2018?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#JSM2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Michael Hoffman @michaelhoffman.bsky.social (@michaelhoffman) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/michaelhoffman/status/1024066415752433664?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 30, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also know that sometimes I’ve been a bystander and failed to take action. So this next idea sounds good to me. I do try to intervene more now, specially with micro aggressions: because they are less high pressure situations and easier to do something about, at least that’s how I feel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Bystander training might help. It&amp;#39;s not easy to do the right thing in a difficult situation when you have no idea what the right thing is, no training, no experience, no practice. &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/JSM2018?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#JSM2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Michael Hoffman @michaelhoffman.bsky.social (@michaelhoffman) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/michaelhoffman/status/1024063008987787264?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 30, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To close my post, I encourage you to check their request for feedback!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;If you’re planning to come to our session (211) on sexual misconduct today (and even if you’re not) you might take a look at these scenarios that we’ll use to get the conversation started. Link in RT below. &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/JSM2018?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#JSM2018&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/czjUKYkHq1&#34;&gt;https://t.co/czjUKYkHq1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Kristian Lum (@KLdivergence) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/KLdivergence/status/1023977618104889346?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 30, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you are an R non-cis male person, you should totally join the R-Ladies community slack!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;📢 Join our new ✨ R-Ladies community Slack! ✨&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It&amp;#39;s aiming for a safe &amp;amp; global space to discuss topics and share ideas around &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/rstats?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#rstats&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; the &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/rladies?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#rladies&lt;/a&gt; community! 💜&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;We invite all non-cis male R users to sign-up via &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/TOXALUGLuf&#34;&gt;https://t.co/TOXALUGLuf&lt;/a&gt; 🚀 &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/ZMNuqkN0HW&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/ZMNuqkN0HW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; R-Ladies Global (@RLadiesGlobal) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/RLadiesGlobal/status/1022031250759053314?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 25, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;acknowledgments&#34;&gt;Acknowledgments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog post was made possible thanks to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=blogdown&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;blogdown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Xie_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown/&#39;&gt;Xie, Hill, and Thomas, 2017&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;devtools&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Wickham_2022&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&#39;&gt;Wickham, Hester, Chang, and Bryan, 2022&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;knitcitations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Boettiger_2021&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&#39;&gt;Boettiger, 2021&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Boettiger_2021&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Boettiger_2021&#34;&gt;\[1\]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt;
C. Boettiger.
&lt;em&gt;knitcitations: Citations for ‘Knitr’ Markdown Files&lt;/em&gt;.
R package version 1.0.12.
2021.
URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Wickham_2022&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Wickham_2022&#34;&gt;\[2\]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt;
H. Wickham, J. Hester, W. Chang, and J. Bryan.
&lt;em&gt;devtools: Tools to Make Developing R Packages Easier&lt;/em&gt;.
R package version 2.4.5.
2022.
URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Xie_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Xie_2017&#34;&gt;\[3\]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt;
Y. Xie, A. P. Hill, and A. Thomas.
&lt;em&gt;blogdown: Creating Websites with R Markdown&lt;/em&gt;.
Boca Raton, Florida: Chapman and Hall/CRC, 2017.
ISBN: 978-0815363729.
URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown/&#34;&gt;https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;reproducibility&#34;&gt;Reproducibility&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## ─ Session info ───────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────
##  setting  value
##  version  R version 4.3.1 (2023-06-16)
##  os       macOS Ventura 13.4
##  system   aarch64, darwin20
##  ui       X11
##  language (EN)
##  collate  en_US.UTF-8
##  ctype    en_US.UTF-8
##  tz       America/New_York
##  date     2023-07-11
##  pandoc   3.1.5 @ /opt/homebrew/bin/ (via rmarkdown)
## 
## ─ Packages ───────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────
##  package       * version    date (UTC) lib source
##  backports       1.4.1      2021-12-13 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  bibtex          0.5.1      2023-01-26 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  BiocManager     1.30.21    2023-06-10 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  BiocStyle     * 2.28.0     2023-04-25 [1] Bioconductor
##  blogdown        1.18       2023-06-19 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  bookdown        0.34       2023-05-09 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  bslib           0.5.0      2023-06-09 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  cachem          1.0.8      2023-05-01 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  callr           3.7.3      2022-11-02 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  cli             3.6.1      2023-03-23 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  colorout        1.2-2      2023-05-06 [1] Github (jalvesaq/colorout@79931fd)
##  crayon          1.5.2      2022-09-29 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  devtools      * 2.4.5      2022-10-11 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  digest          0.6.31     2022-12-11 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  ellipsis        0.3.2      2021-04-29 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  evaluate        0.21       2023-05-05 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  fastmap         1.1.1      2023-02-24 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  fs              1.6.2      2023-04-25 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  generics        0.1.3      2022-07-05 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  glue            1.6.2      2022-02-24 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  htmltools       0.5.5      2023-03-23 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  htmlwidgets     1.6.2      2023-03-17 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  httpuv          1.6.11     2023-05-11 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  httr            1.4.6      2023-05-08 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  jquerylib       0.1.4      2021-04-26 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  jsonlite        1.8.7      2023-06-29 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  knitcitations * 1.0.12     2021-01-10 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  knitr           1.43       2023-05-25 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  later           1.3.1      2023-05-02 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  lifecycle       1.0.3      2022-10-07 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  lubridate       1.9.2      2023-02-10 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  magrittr        2.0.3      2022-03-30 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  memoise         2.0.1      2021-11-26 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  mime            0.12       2021-09-28 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  miniUI          0.1.1.1    2018-05-18 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  pkgbuild        1.4.2      2023-06-26 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  pkgload         1.3.2      2022-11-16 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  plyr            1.8.8      2022-11-11 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  prettyunits     1.1.1      2020-01-24 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  processx        3.8.2      2023-06-30 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  profvis         0.3.8      2023-05-02 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  promises        1.2.0.1    2021-02-11 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  ps              1.7.5      2023-04-18 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  purrr           1.0.1      2023-01-10 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  R6              2.5.1      2021-08-19 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  Rcpp            1.0.10     2023-01-22 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  RefManageR      1.4.0      2022-09-30 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  remotes         2.4.2      2021-11-30 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  rlang           1.1.1      2023-04-28 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  rmarkdown       2.23       2023-07-01 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  rstudioapi      0.14       2022-08-22 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  sass            0.4.6.9000 2023-05-06 [1] Github (rstudio/sass@f248fe5)
##  sessioninfo     1.2.2      2021-12-06 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  shiny           1.7.4      2022-12-15 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  stringi         1.7.12     2023-01-11 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  stringr         1.5.0      2022-12-02 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  timechange      0.2.0      2023-01-11 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  urlchecker      1.0.1      2021-11-30 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  usethis       * 2.2.1      2023-06-23 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  vctrs           0.6.3      2023-06-14 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  xfun            0.39       2023-04-20 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  xml2            1.3.4      2023-04-27 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  xtable          1.8-4      2019-04-21 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
##  yaml            2.3.7      2023-01-23 [1] CRAN (R 4.3.0)
## 
##  [1] /Library/Frameworks/R.framework/Versions/4.3-arm64/Resources/library
## 
## ──────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SciLifeLab Prize: you still have time to participate! </title>
      <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/06/20/scilifelab-prize-you-still-have-time-to-participate/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/06/20/scilifelab-prize-you-still-have-time-to-participate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-06-20-scilifelab-prize-you-still-have-time-to-participate_files/unnamed.jpg&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have recently been getting reminder emails from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencemag.org/science-scilifelab-prize-young-scientists&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt; &amp;amp; SciLifeLab Prize for Young Scientists&lt;/a&gt;. The application deadline is July 15th, 2018!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year I submitted an entry to this competition and I enjoyed the experience, even if it was a bit rushed. The process of joining the competition is relatively straight forward:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write an essay about your Ph.D. thesis work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get a recommendation letter from your Ph.D. advisor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write a short Ph.D. thesis abstract section, list your affiliation, education, academic and professional awards and professional experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Include references.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don’t need to pay for competing! You already did the very hard part of completing your Ph.D.!!! I also like competitions like this one that invite you to think about your thesis and how to explain it. You should note that you are only eligible to participate once in this competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can read about the 4 winners from 2017 at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencemag.org/prizes/SciLifeLab/2017&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;www.sciencemag.org/prizes/SciLifeLab/2017&lt;/a&gt; and other years too to draw some inspiration from. I didn’t win, but I’m still going to share my entry in case it’s useful to others. I’m also sharing it to keep with the theme of also sharing your failures that I talked in my &lt;a href=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/06/11/mindfulness/#.WyrJbBJKjUI&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;mindfulness post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t know exactly why my entry was not selected (you might have some ideas on how to improve it!). But I can tell you that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I knew the deadline was coming but I wrote it the week it was due.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I didn’t have time to ask for some more specific feedback from others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I forgot that a recommendation letter was needed, so I asked at the very last minute for one by &lt;a href=&#34;http://jtleek.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Jeff Leek&lt;/a&gt;. I don’t know what magic he did (likely skipping a few hours of sleep, sorry!!!) but he managed to send it in time. Oops!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure if I should have emphasized more the impact of my Ph.D. thesis work or what else to do. However, I do know that this exercise was useful. First, just re-reading my essay makes me smile. Also, Figure 1 shown here became a figure in the &lt;code&gt;recount-workflow&lt;/code&gt; paper &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Collado-Torres_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://f1000research.com/articles/6-1558/v1&#39;&gt;Collado-Torres, Nellore, and Jaffe, 2017&lt;/a&gt;). Furthermore, when I was notified about the &lt;a href=&#34;https://bioinformatics-peer-prize-iii.thinkable.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Thinkable Bioinformatics Peer Prize III&lt;/a&gt; I didn’t have to think twice about joining that competition. Finally, since I wrote it in an Rmd file, it was easy to modify for this blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like I’ve said, you have nothing to lose by joining this competition. Yes, you have to invest a bit of time. But it can be helpful and morale boosting! Plus, you have a chance to win it!!! Just remember that the deadline is July 15th, 2018 (and to give your advisor enough time to write their recommendation letter for you)!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case you are curious, here are my full &lt;a href=&#34;https://gist.github.com/lcolladotor/657aaae9d16aff3ce468f44f8780a317&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;entry files&lt;/a&gt; (the figure is here though).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Collado-Torres_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Collado-Torres_2017&#34;&gt;\[1\]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt;
L. Collado-Torres, A. Nellore, and A. E. Jaffe.
“recount workflow: Accessing over 70,000 human RNA-seq samples with Bioconductor \[version 1; referees: 1 approved, 2 approved with reservations\]”.
In: &lt;em&gt;F1000Research&lt;/em&gt; (2017).
DOI: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.12688/f1000research.12223.1&#34;&gt;10.12688/f1000research.12223.1&lt;/a&gt;.
URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://f1000research.com/articles/6-1558/v1&#34;&gt;https://f1000research.com/articles/6-1558/v1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without further ado, here’s my full entry:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;usable-human-gene-expression-data-and-annotation-agnostic-methods&#34;&gt;Usable human gene expression data and annotation-agnostic methods&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the last decade RNA sequencing (RNA-seq) has become the predominant assay for measuring gene expression. RNA-seq allows us to measure all expressed genes, improve gene and transcript annotation, and measure expressed sequences that otherwise are excluded in microarray studies. Typical RNA-seq analysis starts with a matrix containing the number of RNA-seq reads overlapping each gene for each sample (Michael I. Love et al. 2016; Law et al. 2016). To compute such a matrix, you first map the raw data to the genome with aligners such as &lt;em&gt;TopHat2&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;HISAT&lt;/em&gt; (Kim et al. 2013; Kim, Langmead, and Salzberg 2015) and then use tools such as &lt;em&gt;Rsubread&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;HTSeq&lt;/em&gt; (Y, GK, and W 2013; Anders, Pyl, and Huber 2014) to construct the read count matrix. After measuring enough samples, you can determine which genes are differentially expressed between two or more groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I started my graduate studies with Jeff Leek, the most commonly used methods for differential expression analysis were &lt;em&gt;DESeq&lt;/em&gt; (Anders and Huber 2010) and &lt;em&gt;edgeR&lt;/em&gt; (Robinson, McCarthy, and Smyth 2010). Leek and colleagues put together a set of gene count matrices in a project called &lt;em&gt;ReCount&lt;/em&gt; (Alyssa C. Frazee, Langmead, and Leek 2011). &lt;em&gt;ReCount&lt;/em&gt; allowed researchers to access several datasets without having to run the whole processing pipeline. &lt;em&gt;ReCount&lt;/em&gt; then helped the development of new methods such as &lt;em&gt;DESeq2&lt;/em&gt; (Michael I. Love, Huber, and Anders 2014). It was also Leek and colleagues that decided to look at RNA-seq data in a manner less dependent on potentially incomplete gene annotation. With the increase in size of RNA-seq projects, they thought it would be feasible to assess the differential expression signal at base pair resolution in an approach called differentially expressed regions (DER) finder (Alyssa C. Frazee et al. 2014).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was around then that I started to work with Andrew Jaffe, who had RNA-seq data from the human brain. Jaffe and colleagues hypothesized that the gene annotation for the human brain might be incomplete and were interested in applying the DER finder approach to their data. With them, I modified the DER finder approach to make it computationally feasible to analyze these human brain samples at base resolution (Jaffe et al. 2015). We indeed found that the human brain transcriptome was not fully annotated and identified intronic DERs that were present in other brain datasets, including from mouse, and showed these regions were enriched for genetic risk for brain disorders. Further computational improvements to the DER finder approach yielded the &lt;em&gt;derfinder&lt;/em&gt; (Collado-Torres, Nellore, Frazee, et al. 2017) Bioconductor (Huber et al. 2015) package, reducing computing time from days to hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I was working on &lt;em&gt;derfinder&lt;/em&gt;, Abhinav Nellore was developing &lt;em&gt;Rail-RNA&lt;/em&gt; (Nellore, Collado-Torres, et al. 2016) with the goal of aligning large RNA-seq datasets. We determined that we only needed coverage data instead of alignments to use &lt;em&gt;derfinder&lt;/em&gt; and to perform gene level analyses. Coverage data files are much smaller than alignment files, which meant that we could greatly reduce our storage costs when using &lt;em&gt;Rail-RNA&lt;/em&gt; and allowed us to think as big as possible. Initially we looked at 21,504 human RNA-seq samples and explored the landscape of exon-exon junctions (Nellore, Jaffe, et al. 2016). The reads spanning exon-exon junctions provided by &lt;em&gt;Rail-RNA&lt;/em&gt; can be used for a second type of annotation-agnostic analysis as these reads provide information about exon skipping, alternative donor/acceptor sites and novel events. With a fairly conservative filter we determined that 18.6% of exon-exon junctions were missing in the annotation (Nellore, Jaffe, et al. 2016). This observation along with the fact that exon-exon junctions can be used to determine differential transcript usage gave strength to this second annotation-agnostic RNA-seq analysis method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Researchers around the world have shared their raw data via the Sequence Read Archive or via large consortiums such as the Genotype-Tissue Expression study (GTEx) and the Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA). However, it still is complicated to align and compute count matrices for these datasets. We thought that if the public data was uniformly processed that we could make this large body of human expression data more reusable. We were well positioned to carry out this project and just needed resources. Luckily, Jeff Leek, Ben Langmead and others got together and funded the implementation of &lt;em&gt;Rail-RNA&lt;/em&gt; to analyze all the human public RNA-seq data available at the time, over 70,000 samples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34; style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;fig:figure1&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-06-20-scilifelab-prize-you-still-have-time-to-participate_files/figure1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Overview of the data available in recount2. Reads aligned to the reference genome can be used to compute a base pair coverage curve, identify exon-exon junctions and compute gene and exon count matrices. The reads spanning exon-exon junctions (jx) are used to compute a third count matrix that includes un-annotated junctions (jx 3 and 4). Annotation-agnostic expressed regions can be determined from the coverage data.&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
Figure 1: Overview of the data available in recount2. Reads aligned to the reference genome can be used to compute a base pair coverage curve, identify exon-exon junctions and compute gene and exon count matrices. The reads spanning exon-exon junctions (jx) are used to compute a third count matrix that includes un-annotated junctions (jx 3 and 4). Annotation-agnostic expressed regions can be determined from the coverage data.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We computed gene count matrices for these 70,000 samples and made them available as the &lt;em&gt;recount2&lt;/em&gt; resource that can be accessed at &lt;a href=&#34;https://jhubiostatistics.shinyapps.io/recount/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;jhubiostatistics.shinyapps.io/recount/&lt;/a&gt; as well as through the &lt;em&gt;recount&lt;/em&gt; (Collado-Torres, Nellore, Kammers, et al. 2017) Bioconductor package, thus representing a major improvement over &lt;em&gt;ReCount&lt;/em&gt;. To take advantage of the data as much as possible, we also released exon and exon-exon junction count matrices as well as the coverage data files required for the DER finder approach, thus enabling both annotation-agnostic methods we developed that complement traditional methods. Figure 1 illustrates the type of information that is available via &lt;em&gt;recount2&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My colleagues and I believe that &lt;em&gt;recount2&lt;/em&gt; will fuel the development of new analytical methods and greatly increase the usability of the public human gene expression data researchers have collected over the years. In the meantime, we are working hard on improving the data in &lt;em&gt;recount2&lt;/em&gt; (Ellis, Collado-Torres, and Leek 2017; Wilks et al. 2017) and exploring how to leverage results from different RNA-seq analytical approaches (Jaffe et al. 2017).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;phdthesis-abstract&#34;&gt;Ph.D. thesis abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leonardo Collado-Torres’ thesis work is centered around the development of R software packages for analyzing RNA sequencing (RNA-seq) and ChIP sequencing (ChIP-seq) high throughput genomic data. The first chapter describes the &lt;em&gt;derfinder&lt;/em&gt; Bioconductor package which implements the DER Finder approach for identifying differentially expressed regions with RNA-seq data in an annotation-agnostic manner. The second chapter shows how &lt;em&gt;derfinder&lt;/em&gt; can be applied to ChIP-seq data to identify differentially bounded regions. The third chapter describes the &lt;em&gt;regionReport&lt;/em&gt; Bioconductor package for producing HTML or PDF reports from region-based genomic analyses, such as the &lt;em&gt;derfinder&lt;/em&gt; analyses described in the previous chapters. The last thesis project Leonardo Collado-Torres carried out was the development of the &lt;em&gt;recount2&lt;/em&gt; resource and accompanying &lt;em&gt;recount&lt;/em&gt; Bioconductor package using the &lt;em&gt;Rail-RNA&lt;/em&gt; results from processing all the public human RNA-seq data at the time, which spans over 70,000 samples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;affiliation&#34;&gt;Affiliation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lieber Institute for Brain Development, Johns Hopkins Medical Campus, Baltimore, Maryland, 21205, USA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;education&#34;&gt;Education&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2011-2016. Ph.D. in Biostatistics at Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health, Baltimore, US. Advised by Jeff Leek and Andrew Jaffe.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2005-2009. Bachelor in Genomic Sciences (LCG) at the National Autonomous University of Mexico (UNAM), Cuernavaca, MX.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2002-2005. High school at ITESM Campus Cuernavaca, Cuernavaca, MX.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;academic-and-professional-awards&#34;&gt;Academic and professional awards&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2011: Awarded CONACyT Mexico scholarship for PhD studies outside Mexico.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2009: &lt;em&gt;Summa Cum Laude&lt;/em&gt; for bachelor in Genomic Sciences studies at LCG-UNAM.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2005: Best high school average ($\sim$ 200 students): awarded ITESM system 90% scholarship for college studies, declined to join LCG-UNAM.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;professional-experience&#34;&gt;Professional experience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016-current. Data Scientist with Andrew Jaffe lab at LIBD, Baltimore. At LIBD, Dr. Collado-Torres is part of the Data Science team which goals include better understanding and characterizing genomics signatures in the human brain, including DNA methylation and gene expression. Leonardo helps mentor other team members, provides support for LIBD projects and is advancing his academic career as part of Andrew Jaffe’s lab.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2009-2011. Bioinformatician with Enrique Morett lab at IBT-UNAM, Cuernavaca, MX. Identified transcriptions start sites and transcription units in &lt;em&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Geobacter sulfurreducens&lt;/em&gt; with RNA-seq data. Developed the &lt;em&gt;BacterialTranscription&lt;/em&gt; R package.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2009-2011. Scientific executive at Winter Genomics in Cuernavaca, MX. Responsible for recruiting and hiring new personnel, overseeing and supervising bioinformaticians, training new employees, writing research reports and presenting them to colleagues, and organizing all scientific projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2007-2009. Undergraduate research assistant at Guillermo Davila’s lab at CCG-UNAM, Cuernavaca, MX. Determined bacteriophage ecological groups by developing a method based on codon distribution of all phage sequenced genomes. Joint work with Sur Herrera Paredes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2006-2007. Undergraduate research assistant at Roberto Kolter’s lab at Harvard, Boston, US. Supervisor: Elizabeth Shank. Carried out screenings to identify bacteria that activate the production of exopolysaccharide through the activation of the gene tasA in &lt;em&gt;Bacillus subtilis&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;refs&#34; class=&#34;references csl-bib-body hanging-indent&#34;&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-anders2010&#34; class=&#34;csl-entry&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anders, Simon, and Wolfgang Huber. 2010. “Differential Expression Analysis for Sequence Count Data.” &lt;em&gt;Genome Biology&lt;/em&gt; 11 (10): R106. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1186/gb-2010-11-10-r106&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1186/gb-2010-11-10-r106&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-anders2014htseq&#34; class=&#34;csl-entry&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anders, Simon, Paul Theodor Pyl, and Wolfgang Huber. 2014. “HTSeq–a Python Framework to Work with High-Throughput Sequencing Data.” &lt;em&gt;bioRxiv&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-collado-torres-derfinder&#34; class=&#34;csl-entry&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Collado-Torres, Leonardo, Abhinav Nellore, Alyssa C. Frazee, Christopher Wilks, Michael I. Love, Ben Langmead, Rafael A. Irizarry, Jeffrey T. Leek, and Andrew E. Jaffe. 2017. “Flexible Expressed Region Analysis for RNA-Seq with Derfinder.” &lt;em&gt;Nucleic Acids Research&lt;/em&gt; 45 (2): e9–9. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkw852&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkw852&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-collado-torres-recount2&#34; class=&#34;csl-entry&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Collado-Torres, Leonardo, Abhinav Nellore, Kai Kammers, Shannon E. Ellis, Margaret A. Taub, Kasper D. Hansen, Andrew E. Jaffe, Ben Langmead, and Jeffrey T. Leek. 2017. “Reproducible RNA-Seq Analysis Using Recount2.” &lt;em&gt;Nature Biotechnology&lt;/em&gt; 35 (4): 319–21. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/nbt.3838&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/nbt.3838&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-ellis2017&#34; class=&#34;csl-entry&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ellis, Shannon E, Leonardo Collado-Torres, and Jeffrey Leek. 2017. “Improving the Value of Public RNA-Seq Expression Data by Phenotype Prediction.” &lt;em&gt;bioRxiv&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1101/145656&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1101/145656&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-frazee2011&#34; class=&#34;csl-entry&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frazee, Alyssa C., Ben Langmead, and Jeffrey T. Leek. 2011. “ReCount: A Multi-Experiment Resource of Analysis-Ready RNA-Seq Gene Count Datasets.” &lt;em&gt;BMC Bioinformatics&lt;/em&gt; 12: 449. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2105-12-449&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2105-12-449&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-frazee2014&#34; class=&#34;csl-entry&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frazee, Alyssa C, Sarven Sabunciyan, Kasper D Hansen, Rafael A Irizarry, and Jeffrey T Leek. 2014. “Differential Expression Analysis of &lt;span class=&#34;nocase&#34;&gt;RNA-seq&lt;/span&gt; Data at Single-Base Resolution.” &lt;em&gt;Biostatistics (Oxford, England)&lt;/em&gt;, January. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1093/biostatistics/kxt053&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1093/biostatistics/kxt053&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-huber2015&#34; class=&#34;csl-entry&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Huber, Wolfgang, Vincent J Carey, Robert Gentleman, Simon Anders, Marc Carlson, Benilton S Carvalho, Hector Corrada Bravo, et al. 2015. “Orchestrating High-Throughput Genomic Analysis with Bioconductor.” &lt;em&gt;Nature Methods&lt;/em&gt; 12 (2): 115–21. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/nmeth.3252&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/nmeth.3252&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-jaffe2015&#34; class=&#34;csl-entry&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jaffe, Andrew E., Jooheon Shin, Leonardo Collado-Torres, Jeffrey T. Leek, Ran Tao, Chao Li, Yuan Gao, et al. 2015. “Developmental Regulation of Human Cortex Transcription and Its Clinical Relevance at Single Base Resolution.” &lt;em&gt;Nature Neuroscience&lt;/em&gt; 18 (1): 154–61. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/nn.3898&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/nn.3898&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-jaffe2017&#34; class=&#34;csl-entry&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jaffe, Andrew E., Richard Straub, Joo Heon Shin, Ran Tao, Yuan Gao, Leonardo Collado-Torres, Tony Kam-Thong, et al. 2017. “&lt;span class=&#34;nocase&#34;&gt;Developmental and genetic regulation of the human cortex transcriptome in schizophrenia&lt;/span&gt;.” &lt;em&gt;bioRxiv&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-kim2015&#34; class=&#34;csl-entry&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kim, Daehwan, Ben Langmead, and Steven L. Salzberg. 2015. “HISAT: A Fast Spliced Aligner with Low Memory Requirements.” &lt;em&gt;Nature Methods&lt;/em&gt; 12 (4): 357–60. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/nmeth.3317&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/nmeth.3317&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-kim2013&#34; class=&#34;csl-entry&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kim, Daehwan, Geo Pertea, Cole Trapnell, Harold Pimentel, Ryan Kelley, and Steven L Salzberg. 2013. “TopHat2: Accurate Alignment of Transcriptomes in the Presence of Insertions, Deletions and Gene Fusions.” &lt;em&gt;Genome Biology&lt;/em&gt; 14 (4): R36. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1186/gb-2013-14-4-r36&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1186/gb-2013-14-4-r36&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-Law2016a&#34; class=&#34;csl-entry&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Law, Charity W, Monther Alhamdoosh, Shian Su, Gordon K Smyth, and Matthew E Ritchie. 2016. “&lt;span class=&#34;nocase&#34;&gt;RNA-seq analysis is easy as 1-2-3 with limma, Glimma and edgeR.&lt;/span&gt;” &lt;em&gt;F1000Research&lt;/em&gt; 5 (May): 1408. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.12688/f1000research.9005.2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.12688/f1000research.9005.2&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-Love2016&#34; class=&#34;csl-entry&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Love, Michael I., Simon Anders, Vladislav Kim, and Wolfgang Huber. 2016. “&lt;span class=&#34;nocase&#34;&gt;RNA-Seq workflow: gene-level exploratory analysis and differential expression&lt;/span&gt;.” &lt;em&gt;F1000Research&lt;/em&gt; 4 (May): 1070. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.12688/f1000research.7035.2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.12688/f1000research.7035.2&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-love2014&#34; class=&#34;csl-entry&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Love, Michael I, Wolfgang Huber, and Simon Anders. 2014. “Moderated Estimation of Fold Change and Dispersion for RNA-Seq Data with DESeq2.” &lt;em&gt;Genome Biology&lt;/em&gt; 15 (12): 1–21.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-rail-rna&#34; class=&#34;csl-entry&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nellore, Abhinav, Leonardo Collado-Torres, Andrew E. Jaffe, José Alquicira-Hernández, Christopher Wilks, Jacob Pritt, James Morton, Jeffrey T. Leek, and Ben Langmead. 2016. “Rail-RNA: Scalable Analysis of RNA-Seq Splicing and Coverage.” &lt;em&gt;Bioinformatics (Oxford, England)&lt;/em&gt;, September. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btw575&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btw575&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-nellore2016human&#34; class=&#34;csl-entry&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nellore, Abhinav, Andrew E. Jaffe, Jean-Philippe Fortin, José Alquicira-Hernández, Leonardo Collado-Torres, Siruo Wang, Robert A. Phillips Iii, et al. 2016. “Human Splicing Diversity and the Extent of Unannotated Splice Junctions Across Human RNA-Seq Samples on the Sequence Read Archive.” &lt;em&gt;Genome Biology&lt;/em&gt; 17 (1): 266.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-robinson2010&#34; class=&#34;csl-entry&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Robinson, Mark D, Davis J McCarthy, and Gordon K Smyth. 2010. “&lt;span class=&#34;nocase&#34;&gt;edgeR:&lt;/span&gt; A Bioconductor Package for Differential Expression Analysis of Digital Gene Expression Data.” &lt;em&gt;Bioinformatics (Oxford, England)&lt;/em&gt; 26 (1): 139–40. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btp616&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btp616&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-wilks2017&#34; class=&#34;csl-entry&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wilks, Christopher, Phani Gaddipati, Abhinav Nellore, and Benjamin Langmead. 2017. “&lt;span class=&#34;nocase&#34;&gt;Snaptron: querying and visualizing splicing across tens of thousands of RNA-seq samples&lt;/span&gt;.” &lt;em&gt;bioRxiv&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1101/097881&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1101/097881&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-rsubread&#34; class=&#34;csl-entry&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Y, Liao, Smyth GK, and Shi W. 2013. “The Subread Aligner: Fast, Accurate and Scalable Read Mapping by Seed-and-Vote.” &lt;em&gt;Nucleic Acids Research&lt;/em&gt; 41: e108.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Keeping in touch (ENAR2014?) and philosophical questions regarding México&#39;s future in genomics</title>
      <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/06/12/keeping-in-touch-enar2014-and-philosophical/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/06/12/keeping-in-touch-enar2014-and-philosophical/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The following text is an email I sent to several of my friends from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/about&#34;&gt;LCG undergraduate program &lt;/a&gt;I studied. There I talk about keeping in touch, I invite them to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.enar.org/meetings.cfm&#34;&gt;ENAR 2014&lt;/a&gt;, and also talk about some philosophical questions regarding our future. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m posting it here because I don&amp;#8217;t mind sharing these thoughts and because I don&amp;#8217;t have the current email addresses of many former LCG students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Enjoy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hola a todos,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Les escribo por el gusto de mantener el contacto, por razones académicas, y también por un rollo filosófico / a futuro.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contacto&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Como ya les dije, me da mucho gusto escribirles. Cuando lo hago sé que generalmente resulta en mails largos, así que intentando ser corto, siento que hoy termina el ciclo de personas que conocí en la LCG. Digo, hoy se gradua la 7ma generación y realmente no conozco las nuevas. Fueron años muy buenos los que viví con todos allá en Cuerna y ojalá podamos mantener cierto vínculo a través de los años. Sé que cuesta. Por ejemplo, no tengo los correos de algunos (o no los encontré vía google), otros los intenté adivinar vía &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/titulados&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/titulados&#34;&gt;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/titulados&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; y la regla de 8 caracteres, y solo pocos lo siguen teniendo en su página de Facebook (por rollos de seguridad). También soy bastante malo para escribir regularmente (ya sea vía email o mis blogs: &lt;a href=&#34;http://fellgernon.tumblr.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;académico&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;más personal&lt;/span&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Este año en especial he disfrutado (y seguiré disfrutando) mucho de ver a algunos aunque sea un par de horas =)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;También me gusta mucho cuando me piden ayuda sobre algo, aunque sea lento en contestar :P&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ENAR 2014&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;De lo académico, les quiero avisar que en 2014 van a organizar acá en Baltimore el congreso ENAR (Eastern North American Regional) en marzo del 2014. Es un congreso de bioestadística con una buena parte enfocada a la genómica. Y bueno, muchas cosas hechas en R. Mi jefe está organizando un par de las sesiones así que si tienen sugerencias de quienes invitar avísenme. Ustedes mismos ^_&lt;em&gt;^ &lt;/em&gt;(hay un buen número de pláticas por alumnos de posgrado &amp;amp; postdocs), sus jefes, etc. En fin, tal vez les interese el congreso.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;De 2014 no hay mucha info aún &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.enar.org/meetings.cfm&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.enar.org/meetings.cfm&#34;&gt;http://www.enar.org/meetings.cfm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, pero allí pueden ver lo que pasó en otros años.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rollos filosóficos&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;El rollo filosófico / a futuro tiene que ver con:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class=&#34;ol1&#34;&gt;&lt;li class=&#34;li1&#34;&gt;¿Qué condiciones piden para trabajar en México?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&#34;li1&#34;&gt;¿Cómo crear un vínculo más fuerte entre egresados LCG?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&#34;li1&#34;&gt;¿A qué dedicarse? ¿Academia? ¿Industria? ¿Otra cosa?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Del punto (1) lo he platicado con algunos pero creo que es un tema interesante y muy variado. Hay aspectos que tal vez están fuera de nuestro alcance como la seguridad, y hay otros como el ambiente de trabajo y de la ciencia. El rollo de plazas y los esfuerzos de algunos por crear espacios: CCG tiene algunas ahorita, Palacios &amp;amp; Dávila están haciendo un plan grande para repatriar ex-LCGs, el INMEGEN &amp;amp; el CINVESTAV han estado creciendo, o la idea de hacer un plan nosotros. Ojo, a penas me enteré que para tener plaza de investigador en la UNAM te piden tener un postdoc de 2 años: el chiste es que tengas publicaciones &amp;amp; hayas demostrado que la puedes hacer en la ciencia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;¿Sacrificas potencial académico trabajando en México? Dicho de otra forma, ¿cómo te afecta: el rollo del idioma, el de competir en condiciones que parecen ser más difíciles, o el de tener menos colaboradores cerca para crecer con su crítica &amp;amp; datos de última tecnología? O irse fuera de México (no hay por que ser mártir) y sentirse a gusto con esa decisión. Siempre hay formas de colaborar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Del punto (2) yo opino que puede ser a través de comentar artículos con gente ex-LCG involucrada (algo así &lt;a href=&#34;http://fellgernon.tumblr.com/post/45152484977/commenting-scientific-papers#.UbjBemTF1d8&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;describí aquí&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;), o tal vez vía &lt;a href=&#34;http://masciencia.org/&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;Más Ciencia por México&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (no los logré convencer en esto de comentar artículos). Digo, también ayudaría que &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/titulados&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/titulados&#34;&gt;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/titulados&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; tenga ligas a las páginas actuales de cada quien.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Del (3), en mi opinión cubre también todo el rollo de si queremos vivir con &amp;#8220;soft-money&amp;#8221; a través del ciclo de donativos (el pay-line es 10% en EUA ahorita por lo de sequester), de la libertad académica (¿es una realidad o una forma de cautivarnos?), y también depende del tipo de industria. Otra forma de ver este punto es ¿cual es el nivel de estrés con el que estamos dispuestos a vivir? ¿A qué aspiramos? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;En fin, dan ganas de organizar alguna reunión de ex-LCGs!! Mientras, a seguir con estudios &amp;amp; disfrutar la chamba (investigación o lo que estén haciendo).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Si me preguntan que busco con este correo, es simple:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;ul1&#34;&gt;&lt;li class=&#34;li1&#34;&gt;Mantener el contacto&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&#34;li1&#34;&gt;Invitarlos a ENAR 2014&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&#34;li1&#34;&gt;Promover discusión en estos temas filosóficos / a futuro&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;p2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saludos,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leo&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PD Perdón, terminó siendo un mail largo :P&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Have you been &#39;relative stupid&#39;?</title>
      <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/31/Have-you-been-relative-stupid/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/31/Have-you-been-relative-stupid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed reading &amp;#8220;&lt;a href=&#34;http://jcs.biologists.org/content/121/11/1771.full&#34;&gt;The importance of stupidity in scientific research&lt;/a&gt;&#34; by Martin A. Schwartz which I learned existed through &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hmason&#34;&gt;@hmason&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/simplystats&#34;&gt;@simplystats&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found the point of how it&amp;#8217;s normal to feel stupid in academia and specially in Ph.D. programs to be illuminating. But Schwartz clarifies that there are other kinds of stupid:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;we don&amp;#8217;t do a good enough job of teaching our students how to be productively stupid – that is, if we don&amp;#8217;t feel stupid it means we&amp;#8217;re not really trying. I&amp;#8217;m not talking about &#39;relative stupidity&amp;#8217;, in which the other students in the class actually read the material, think about it and ace the exam, whereas you don&amp;#8217;t. I&amp;#8217;m also not talking about bright people who might be working in areas that don&amp;#8217;t match their talents. Science involves confronting our `absolute stupidity&amp;#8217;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t know about you, but I have certainly been &amp;#8216;relative stupid&amp;#8217; at times. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yes, we have to confront our &amp;#8216;absolute stupidity&amp;#8217;. But to me, graduate school is also about learning how to be super efficient with your time. That implies being highly organized, learning how to canalize your distractions, and finding sources of constant motivation. For example, I now read more stats/R/research blogs as part of my set of distractions and have considerably decreased how many sport news I read. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also struggle with the internal challenge of doing great at school, but then also &amp;#8216;having a life&amp;#8217;. So yes, at times I have been &amp;#8216;relative stupid&amp;#8217; but also had a great time. After all, I no longer need to &amp;#8216;ace&amp;#8217; all my exams.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Great commentary on sequestration&#39;s impact on research! National media should talk about this and YOU should read it!!!</title>
      <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/28/great-commentary-on-sequestrations-impact-on-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/28/great-commentary-on-sequestrations-impact-on-research/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu/%7Ejleek/&#34;&gt;Jeffrey T. Leek&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steven_Salzberg&#34;&gt;Steven L. Salzberg&lt;/a&gt; published a paper commentary in Genome Biology today titled “&lt;a href=&#34;http://genomebiology.com/2013/14/3/109&#34;&gt;Sequestration: inadvertently killing biomedical research to score political points&lt;/a&gt;” (&lt;span class=&#34;showtooltip&#34; title=&#34;Leek J and Salzberg S (2013). Sequestration: Inadvertently  Killing Biomedical Research to Score Political Points. _Genome  Biology_, *14*. ISSN 1465-6906,   http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/gb-2013-14-3-109.&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/gb-2013-14-3-109&#34;&gt;Leek &amp;amp; Salzberg, 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;) which I think is a &lt;strong&gt;must read for anyone&lt;/strong&gt;. Seriously!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do not mean &lt;em&gt;anyone involved in research&lt;/em&gt;, or all scientists. I mean, this commentary should be in the &lt;strong&gt;national media&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Why&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, let me approach the technical side first. You might think that anything that appears in a scientific journal—despite any efforts to make it accessible to the general public—will rely on words whose meaning is mostly only understood by scientists. That is not the case in this commentary: it is a dual letter meant to be read by those in Congress, but it is also an educational commentary for the general public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main reason why &lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt; should be reading this commentary is that the consequences of the &amp;#8216;sequester&amp;#8217; are going to affect &lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt;. So if you are interested in your future and the well-being of those who you care for, then you should read it. And if you don&amp;#8217;t know what the sequester is and how it will impact research, well, that&amp;#8217;s another reason why you should read this commentary. Plus you might want to look at this (serious) comic from &lt;code&gt;PhD comics&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;span class=&#34;showtooltip&#34; title=&#34;Cham J (2013). U.S. Budget Sequestration Explained.   http://www.phdcomics.com/comics.php?f=1561.&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.phdcomics.com/comics.php?f=1561&#34;&gt;© Cham, 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;) to get an overall idea. Note that it was published before sequestration hit in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;PhD comic on the sequester&#34; src=&#34;http://www.phdcomics.com/comics/archive/phd021513s.gif&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going back to the commentary piece by Leek and Salzberg, I can imagine someone refuting like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hey, but I don&amp;#8217;t live in the United States so it doesn&amp;#8217;t affect me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is true in a sense because you will likely be affected by your own country&amp;#8217;s policies more directly, and specially in policy topics that have short term impact. Nevertheless, any breakthrough made by U.S.-based research for the most part (aka, when politics doesn&amp;#8217;t get in the way) will reach you. After all, Leek and Salzberg cite (&lt;span class=&#34;showtooltip&#34; title=&#34;(2013). The Sequester Is Going to Devastate U.S. Science Research  for Decades.   http://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2013/03/the-sequester-is-going-to-devastate-us-science-research-for-decades/273925/  [Online. last-accessed: 2013-03-28 03:33:46].   http://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2013/03/the-sequester-is-going-to-devastate-us-science-research-for-decades/273925/.&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2013/03/the-sequester-is-going-to-devastate-us-science-research-for-decades/273925/&#34;&gt;Alivisatos et al in The Atlantic, 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;) where the following statement is made:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nobel Prize-winning economist Robert Solow has &lt;a href=&#34;http://magazine.amstat.org/blog/2011/03/01/econgrowthmar11/&#34;&gt;calculated&lt;/a&gt; that over the past half century, more than half of the growth in our nation&amp;#8217;s GDP has been rooted in scientific discoveries – the kinds of fundamental, mission-driven research that we do at the labs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The claim that it affects other countries is just a generalization of the previous result and what I would consider some common sense. If this is not enough to attract your interest, then you should take a look at Salzberg&amp;#8217;s previous comment “&lt;a href=&#34;http://genome.fieldofscience.com/2013/03/a-breakthrough-cure-for-acute-leukemia.html&#34;&gt;A breakthrough cure for acute leukemia?&lt;/a&gt;” that is a showcase example of successful biomedical research funded by the same institutions being hit by sequestration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope to have convinced you to read Leek and Salzberg&amp;#8217;s commentary by now. So let me talk a little bit about the things that I liked the most.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of all, I like the tone they used because this is not a silly matter and while it may sound as alarming as &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Boy_Who_Cried_Wolf&#34;&gt;the boy who cried wolf&lt;/a&gt;, the reality is that the wolf does exist and will visit you. So while no visible effects have been seen from the sequester this month, that doesn&amp;#8217;t mean that you can just ignore this problem. It is like when you throw a stone in calm water: just a few small ripples are seen at the beginning, but they reach far away. In other words, it will take some time to actually feel the negative effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, I consider Leek and Salzberg&amp;#8217;s work a &lt;strong&gt;wake up call&lt;/strong&gt; to politicians and &lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt;. Either &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; the researcher, but most importantly, &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; the citizen who cares about the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some, specially those who are major supporters of military programs, might disagree with the whole comparison of the F-35 plane which has an estimated cost of $400 billion to the National Institutes of Health (NIH) annual budget of around $31 billion (&lt;span class=&#34;showtooltip&#34; title=&#34;Leek J and Salzberg S (2013). Sequestration: Inadvertently  Killing Biomedical Research to Score Political Points. _Genome  Biology_, *14*. ISSN 1465-6906,   http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/gb-2013-14-3-109.&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/gb-2013-14-3-109&#34;&gt;Leek &amp;amp; Salzberg, 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;). But to me this is just incredible!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strike&gt;To end my comments, I have to say that I am surprised that Leek and Salzberg&amp;#8217;s commentary is behind a paywall. I thought that it would be an open-access piece. After all research articles in Genome Biology are open-access, but this is a commentary so it is not considered a research article. To their credit, Genome Biology does offer 30-day free trial subscriptions. But I am afraid that Leek and Salzberg will lose many readers due to this reason. Hopefully, &lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt; will feel motivated enough to go through the whole trial subscription process, or maybe Genome Biology will make an exception for this commentary.&lt;/strike&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;**Update: Genome Biology changed Leek &amp;amp; Salzberg&amp;#8217;s commentary so &lt;span&gt;as of March 28th &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;it is now open-access (I wrote the post late on the 27th).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, are you not incredulous to see this situation happen? Shouldn&amp;#8217;t the debate be about spending more money in research now that what was spent in the past? The whole sequestration topic is alarming, but the fact that the budget for research hasn&amp;#8217;t increased in years is &lt;strong&gt;shocking&lt;/strong&gt;. Oh wait, you are giving Mexico a chance to catch up to the mighty U.S. in research!!! The whole talk in Mexico about catching up with Brazil or India should be about the U.S. now! (Sadly, Mexico has a lot of catching up to do…)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Citations made with &lt;code&gt;knitcitations&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;span class=&#34;showtooltip&#34; title=&#34;Boettiger C (2013). _knitcitations: Citations for knitr markdown  files_. R package version 0.4-4,   https://github.com/cboettig/knitcitations.&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cboettig/knitcitations&#34;&gt;Boettiger, 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;) and the post was written in the Rmd format powered by &lt;code&gt;knitr&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;span class=&#34;showtooltip&#34; title=&#34;Xie Y (2013). _knitr: A general-purpose package for dynamic report  generation in R_. R package version 1.1,   http://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitr.&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitr&#34;&gt;Xie, 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;(2013) The Sequester Is Going to Devastate U.S. Science Research for Decades. &lt;em&gt;The Atlantic&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2013/03/the-sequester-is-going-to-devastate-us-science-research-for-decades/273925/&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2013/03/the-sequester-is-going-to-devastate-us-science-research-for-decades/273925/&#34;&gt;http://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2013/03/the-sequester-is-going-to-devastate-us-science-research-for-decades/273925/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Carl Boettiger, knitcitations: Citations for knitr markdown files. &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cboettig/knitcitations&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cboettig/knitcitations&#34;&gt;https://github.com/cboettig/knitcitations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yihui Xie, (2013) knitr: A general-purpose package for dynamic report generation in R. &lt;a href=&#34;http://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitr&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitr&#34;&gt;http://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jorge Cham, U.S. Budget Sequestration Explained. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.phdcomics.com/comics.php?f=1561&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.phdcomics.com/comics.php?f=1561&#34;&gt;http://www.phdcomics.com/comics.php?f=1561&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jeffrey T Leek, Steven L Salzberg, (2013) Sequestration: Inadvertently Killing Biomedical Research to Score Political Points. &lt;em&gt;Genome Biology&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;14&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/gb-2013-14-3-109&#34;&gt;10.1186/gb-2013-14-3-109&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Got acknowledged in a paper ^^</title>
      <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/10/31/got-acknowledged-in-a-paper-s4/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/10/31/got-acknowledged-in-a-paper-s4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During the weekend while I was talking with a friend and former colleague, I realized that my name was mentioned in the acknowledgments section of a paper :) I haven&amp;#8217;t been much in touch with what&amp;#8217;s been happening back home, so this was a nice surprise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper is: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2164/13/385&#34;&gt;Genetic changes during a laboratory adaptive evolution process that allowed fast growth in glucose to an &lt;em&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/em&gt; strain lacking the major glucose transport system&lt;/a&gt; by Aguilar&lt;em&gt; et al&lt;/em&gt;. It was published in BMC Genomics in 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Online Bioinformatics Curriculum</title>
      <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/10/07/an-online-bioinformatics-curriculum/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/10/07/an-online-bioinformatics-curriculum/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week I talked about online courses in my &lt;a href=&#34;http://fellgernon.tumblr.com/post/32688589475/jhsph-biostat-through-coursera#.UHH1Q_l26lo&#34;&gt;JHSPH-Biostat through Coursera&lt;/a&gt; post. Now I&amp;#8217;m back to comment on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ploscompbiol.org/article/info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002632&#34;&gt;An Online Bioinformatics Curriculum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; by David B. Searls. &lt;a href=&#34;http://labs.bio.unc.edu/Dangl/people/individuals/Sur.html&#34;&gt;Sur Herrera&lt;/a&gt; pointed out this paper to me, and I have to say that if you are considering learning bioinformatics online it will be very useful to you. David Searls first goes through a history recap of online (free) courses. Notably, in the last year Coursera and other startups offered their first courses. MIT has also evolved and now offers &lt;a href=&#34;http://mitx.mit.edu/&#34;&gt;MITx&lt;/a&gt; courses, where MIT does give certificates. For example, I&amp;#8217;m a bit interested in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.edx.org/courses/MITx/6.00x/2012_Fall/about&#34;&gt;Introduction to Computer Science and Programming 6.00x&lt;/a&gt; course. It aims to cover a wide variety of topics which can be nice for a review/learning and is Python-based. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main body of David Searls&amp;#8217; paper is a huge list of summaries for the main courses out there for bioinformaticians. He covers several tracks depending on what subarea of bioinformatics you are interested in. For each summary, he recommends an specific course to take along with the main reasons why he prefers it over other options. If you have ever looked into OCW, Coursera, etc; you know this is a great resource. After all, there are lots of options for some courses like calculus and it can be a time drain to look through them before deciding which to take. This summary is the best part of the paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David Searls ends it with a conclusion section and some tips on how to make the best of the available resources. How far can free online education go? Well, obviously for informatics it can go almost all the way compared to wet lab biology. Plus, you have to be organized/dedicated/motivated and a good self-learner. Even with all that, you still need good ideas to use as learning projects. If you are looking for one, I would take a look &lt;a href=&#34;http://simplystatistics.org/post/18493330661/statistics-project-ideas-for-students&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://simplystatistics.org/post/32881133740/statistics-project-ideas-for-students-part-2&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; where Jeff Leek lists some of his project suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning about social networks through an interactive presentation</title>
      <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/09/28/learning-about-social-networks-through-an-interactive/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/09/28/learning-about-social-networks-through-an-interactive/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During this week&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu/~zhwu/2012journal.html&#34;&gt;journal club meeting&lt;/a&gt; Hilary Parker (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu/~hiparker/&#34;&gt;homepage&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://hilaryparker.com/&#34;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;) led the session on &amp;#8220;Identifying influential and susceptible members of social networks&amp;#8221;. Were there some speakers or why did she &amp;#8220;lead the session&amp;#8221;? By this I mean that Hilary tried a very different (and interesting) format this time. Instead of giving a talk, not a formal one like at seminars, she prepared a short presentation (publicly available &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1wlZvL8z_8bOau2ZQkvxLtOuFwEVoTeOrJeQ9dO7vATs/edit#slide=id.p&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) that begins showing a 20 minute video. This video is by the author of the paper where he presents the key points of his research at another conference. The goal of this format was to get us to speed and hopefully provoke enough discussion to make the meeting highly interactive. Plus the author does a great job in his presentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, given that it&amp;#8217;s a biostat journal club, Hilary included some slides to explain the general Cox Proportional Hazard model before showing some of details used in the paper in question. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that the change of format was a step in the right direction. Hopefully others will follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder=&#34;0&#34; height=&#34;253&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/JmajkTKlEqw&#34; width=&#34;450&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About the paper itself, the topic is interesting since it shows a different view of the &amp;#8220;data science&amp;#8221; vs biostat discussion. The presenter is trying to convince computer scientists that they need to do some statistics too. Over here, we are poking our heads at whether we need to learn some computer science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, the author is in a different setting than academia or industry, which are commonly the two options. He is at NYU, and academic institution, but he is working closely with the industry (thus getting access to interesting data) and might be getting some consultation money along the way. Anyhow, given the recent talk from Amy Heineike on Quid (&lt;a href=&#34;http://fellgernon.tumblr.com/post/32472984157/quid-biostat-jhsph#.UGYOW_l27mY&#34;&gt;more in my previous post&lt;/a&gt;) there is a growing interest among students to learn more about the industry environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made a couple of comments during the discussion, which might be completely wrong. One is that I feel that in academia we care much more about bias and removing sources of error and it seems that in industry that&amp;#8217;s not the main point. There you care more about making something useful which might be biased. You try to minimize it, but the judge are the clients. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second one is that in industry options like getting a larger sample are much more feasible. In the video, at some point the author shows that people eventually joined the app after getting massively spammed. Increasing the exposure is easy in this case, but imagine a public health survey that is carried out door by door. Increasing the number of houses visited is way more expensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point is that the club meeting followed an interesting format, social networks seem fun to analyze, and industry vs academia is kind of a hot topic in our department right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Hilary for publicly sharing her journal club presentation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is science cool?</title>
      <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/08/27/Is-science-cool/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/08/27/Is-science-cool/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Adam Ruben shares his answer to whether science is cool or not. Since &amp;#8220;cool&amp;#8221; depends on the current trends, this question is set on the recent landing of Curiosity. It&amp;#8217;s the landrover that recently landed on Mars and has been sending some pictures back. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, check his answer &lt;a href=&#34;http://sciencecareers.sciencemag.org/career_magazine/previous_issues/articles/2012_08_24/caredit.a1200095&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I liked this part:&lt;/p&gt;
&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;If the Mars landing draws students to science, it won’t be because they witnessed science doing something cool. It’ll be because they witnessed science doing something human, something genuine, something legitimately appealing on its own merits. Something scientific.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img height=&#34;500&#34; src=&#34;http://www.sciencemag.org/sites/default/files/styles/article_main_large/public/images/20120824_sci_tattoo_Large2.jpg?itok=2YZjjKxZ&amp;c=51fb542122567392ab5e85ed6388a89f&#34; width=&#34;500&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Picture taken from his commentary piece.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pollination video</title>
      <link>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/03/01/great-video-thank-you-aunt-for-sending-it-to-me/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/03/01/great-video-thank-you-aunt-for-sending-it-to-me/</guid>
      <description>&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/xHkq1edcbk4&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Great video! Thank you aunt for sending it to me =)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
