<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Science on L. Collado-Torres</title>
    <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/tags/Science/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Science on L. Collado-Torres</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2011-2018 Leonardo Collado Torres under (CC) BY-NC-SA 4.0. All thoughts and opinions here are my own.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://lcolladotor.github.io/tags/Science/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>A knot of threads: from CSHL to LCG-UNAM to Aldo Barrientos to diversity scholarship opportunities</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/11/06/a-knot-of-threads-from-cshl-to-lcg-unam-to-aldo-barrientos-to-diversity-scholarship-opportunities/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/11/06/a-knot-of-threads-from-cshl-to-lcg-unam-to-aldo-barrientos-to-diversity-scholarship-opportunities/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I can’t tell you how many times I’ve started to write this post in my mind since May 2018. Today I’m finally typing it on the computer. This will be a rather long post that ties in several threads. I’ll talk about Cold Spring Harbor’s Biology of Genomes conference and its relationship to my undergrad in Mexico. I’ll also introduce you to Aldo Barrientos (1987-2011) who was was my undergrad classmate. Then I’ll tell you about myself and how regardless of your situation, privileged or not, you should ask for help and get to know the people around you. Finally, I want to highlight that many other Mexican researchers are doing great work and would love to be invited to talk about their work. Or simply, the opportunity to compete for scholarships and grants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;cshl-and-lcg-unam&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;CSHL and LCG-UNAM&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This past May I was selected to give a talk at &lt;a href=&#34;http://meetings.cshl.edu/Genome18&#34;&gt;Biology of Genomes 2018&lt;/a&gt; (BOG) at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cshl.edu/&#34;&gt;Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory&lt;/a&gt; (CSHL). This was my first time being there and I had plenty of time to reflect before my talk&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. For me, attending BOG was like a dream come true so I was blown away when I was selected to present at BOG.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first heard about the BOG conference when I was studying my undergrad in Mexico at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/es/about&#34;&gt;LCG-UNAM&lt;/a&gt;. My class has a history with the conference too. Basically, part of the class was meeting to discuss what optional courses to create for our fourth year, and well, some miscommunication happened among us. This created a rift in the group and was one of my motivations for focusing on communication as well as giving back. The former lead to me being elected as class president and the latter lead to me volunteering to teach R courses later on my undergrad&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As BOG18 went underway, some of my fellow junior presenters started their talks by mentioning why CSHL was special to them. Following their cue, I wrote some notes just before my presentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-11-06-a-knot-of-threads-from-cshl-to-lcg-unam-to-aldo-barrientos-to-diversity-scholarship-opportunities_files/2018-11-06%2021.21.51.jpg&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really wanted to give a shoutout to all my LCG-UNAM classmates. I also thought of Aldo Barrientos and how it could have been him at BOG. This got me nervous, but I really wanted to do it. I also wanted this to be short and professional. You can see how it turned out for yourself&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/SRGkibDQgIc&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;aldo-barrientos&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Aldo Barrientos&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s time for me to tell you more about Aldo Barrientos, my LCG-UNAM classmate. I won’t attempt to tell you his whole story since I think that others could write a much more detailed one that myself. I hope they do and if they are made public, I’ll share them from this blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aldo came from a low income family in Mexico: I believe that his father was a construction worker&lt;a href=&#34;#fn4&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. He was smart and advanced through school successfully. He took the entry exam for LCG-UNAM like many people did in 2005. Eventually only around 10-15 percent of the applicants were admitted to this undergrad program. The school was free (25 Mexican cents per year), but it involved relocating to a new city. UNAM has some scholarship programs, but they are not enough. Aldo found a way like he always did. For example, he sold candy and juice to his classmates during lunch break. For reasons that I don’t remember, Aldo didn’t complete his undergrad in 2009 but was about to in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember Aldo as a very joyful person who was always smiling and joking with the rest of us. He had the &lt;em&gt;best&lt;/em&gt; dancing skills of anyone at my undergrad. He proved them time and time again, for example winning a dance contest at a party in my house and wearing the Pumas UNAM puma costume in our graduation party and dancing with everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-11-06-a-knot-of-threads-from-cshl-to-lcg-unam-to-aldo-barrientos-to-diversity-scholarship-opportunities_files/goyo.jpg&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://sk.pinterest.com/pin/170714642102216698/&#34;&gt;Image source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His path was cut abruptly in 2011. He was stabbed multiple times while waiting for someone. We all knew about this. It’s still unclear to me how everything happened in the following months. But I remember being told that he tried seeing a doctor before going back to his home. One day in 2011, we all started to learn about how grave his situation had turned. I didn’t know what to do&lt;a href=&#34;#fn5&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and I talked to David Romero, director (dean?) of CCG-UNAM back then. He guided me and others and we were trying to coordinate ways to help Aldo, but by the time we got to his home it was too late. I regret that we weren’t able to help Aldo earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still have some emails from 2011 when we were talking about doing something to honour him. We never did as a class, though LCG-UNAM did acknowledge him. Maybe one day we will do an event to remember him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aldo faced more challenges that myself and other classmates. Yet I believe that he would have kept solving them one by one; he would have gotten his undergrad degree and had he chosen to stay in academia, then present his research findings at conferences like BOG.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;privileged-yes-entitled-no&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Privileged yes, entitled no&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thinking about Aldo made reflect also on who has been around in my own path, who has helped me and how grateful I am to them. Undoubtedly I’ve had an easier path than others including Aldo. That is, I’ve been privileged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, even with my privileged position it has been a hard fought battle to get to where I am now. I think that a mistake others do is that they assume that they are entitled to something given their privilege instead of working for that thing. This can apply to visas and the like where you still &lt;a href=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/09/19/problems-with-an-article-from-the-baltimore-sun-covering-dr-mahoney-steel-s-immigration-issues/&#34;&gt;have to apply for them in time&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along my way I have hesitated many times what to do and have sought guidance from others. Also along my way, I’ve tried to get to know others in my surroundings. Now that I look back I realize that many people were at my position or in junior positions have kept working towards their career goals and advanced in them. So, if you can, get to know others and learn from them. They could be the future Full Professors with Tenure, future Senior Software Engineers or other titles you look up to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s an incomplete version of my timeline (&lt;a href=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/misc/timeline.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF version&lt;/a&gt;). I think that it’s pretty hard to list everyone who has helped you along the way. For example, I’m not mentioning my Ph.D. classmates from whom I learned many things. But it will give you a more detailed picture of the amount of people that have helped me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-11-06-a-knot-of-threads-from-cshl-to-lcg-unam-to-aldo-barrientos-to-diversity-scholarship-opportunities_files/timeline.png&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;invite-lcg-unam-alumni&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Invite LCG-UNAM alumni&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like I said at the beginning of my BOG18 talk, I’m not sure if I’m the first LCG-UNAM alumni to present at BOG but I know for sure that I won’t be the last one. That’s because I’m really proud of my classmates and all the great work they are doing. It’s also easy to go beyond my class to other LCG-UNAM alumni and then even go beyond and extend this to Mexican researchers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taken from my timeline, here are a few that I mentioned there (links are to their Twitter profiles):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mariaGTAC&#34;&gt;Maria Gutierrez-Arcelus&lt;/a&gt;: LCG-UNAM; Ph.D. at University of Geneva Medical School; Postdoc Harvard University&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mgschiavon&#34;&gt;Mariana Gómez-Schiavon&lt;/a&gt;: Ph.D. Duke University; postdoc UCSF&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/sur_hp&#34;&gt;Sur Herrera-Paredes&lt;/a&gt;: Ph.D. University of North Carolina; postdoc Standford&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/malacopa_genome&#34;&gt;Fernando Rabanal Mor&lt;/a&gt;: Ph.D. Gregor Mendel Institute; postdoc MPI for Developmental Biology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/caralvar88&#34;&gt;Carlos Vargas&lt;/a&gt;: Winter Genomics, MS and Ph.D. Universitat de Valencia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/RanitaRed&#34;&gt;Mariana Reyes&lt;/a&gt;: MS and Ph.D. Universitat de Valencia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kazenojigoku&#34;&gt;Atahualpa Castillo&lt;/a&gt;: Ph.D. and postdoc University of Bath&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jimena Mónzon (Ph.D. Univeristy of Bath; Oxford’s Parkinson Disease Centre Career Development Fellow)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/licloona1487&#34;&gt;Alejandra Zayas&lt;/a&gt;: Ph.D. IBT-UNAM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/AV_GonzalezS&#34;&gt;Adriana Verenisse Gonzalez Sandoval&lt;/a&gt;: Ph.D. University of Bath; postdoc Stanford&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/daniela_oaks&#34;&gt;Daniela Robles&lt;/a&gt;: Ph.D. Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute; Faculty LIIGH-UNAM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/lbolanos68&#34;&gt;Luis Bolaños&lt;/a&gt;: Ph.D. CCG-UNAM; postdoc Oregon State University&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rodrigo García: MS and Ph.D. Universitat de Valencia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Renan Escalante-Chong: Ph.D. Harvard postdoc MIT; Immuneering Corporation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gianella Garcia Hughes: Ph.D. UT Southwestern&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/garbanyo&#34;&gt;Adrian Cantú&lt;/a&gt;: LCG-UNAM; MS IBT-UNAM; INMEGEN; Ph.D. San Diego State University&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/yinayiyi&#34;&gt;Ana Georgina (Yina) Cobian&lt;/a&gt;: MS IBT-UNAM, Ph.D. San Diego State University&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/fa7gen&#34;&gt;Fernando Riveros-McKay Aguilera&lt;/a&gt;: Winter Genomics, Ph.D. Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/tatinhawk&#34;&gt;Martín Del Castillo Velasco Herrera&lt;/a&gt;: Winter Genomics, Ph.D. Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/AleMedinaRivera&#34;&gt;Alejandra Medina-Rivera&lt;/a&gt;: LCG-UNAM; Ph.D. CCG-UNAM; postdoc SickKids Toronto; Faculty LIIGH-UNAM&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/areyesq&#34;&gt;Alejandro Reyes&lt;/a&gt;: LCG-UNAM; Ph.D. EMBL; postdoc Harvard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Víctor Moreno Mayar: LCG-UNAM; Ph.D. and postdoc Natural History Museum of Denmark&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;José Reyes: LCG-UNAM, Ph.D. Harvard&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the full list of LCG-UNAM alumni, check &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/es/titulados&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/es/titulados&lt;/a&gt;. There are 257 listed as of October 25, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone has their own story of breaking barriers and overcoming challenges. All of them would love the opportunity to present their work and to compete for funds to travel to conferences and do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;It is and for example Mexican grants cannot be used for paying memberships so we cannot easily get the discounts.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Alejandra Medina-Rivera (@AleMedinaRivera) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/AleMedinaRivera/status/1052349309818232832?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;October 17, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To close off, here are some inspiring or thought provoking tweets:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&amp;quot;Along with a healthy dose of luck, the key attributes needed to produce a worthy PhD thesis are a readiness to accept failure; resilience; persistence; ...and a willingness to commit to very hard work — together with curiosity and a passion for research.&amp;quot; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/o62DODM3iZ&#34;&gt;https://t.co/o62DODM3iZ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Mariana G. Schiavon (@mgschiavon) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mgschiavon/status/1056571008662949888?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;October 28, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;When you&amp;#39;re early-stage in your career, reading stories of people who have been successful is invaluable. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;My &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/rstats?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#rstats&lt;/a&gt; hero is &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/JennyBryan?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@JennyBryan&lt;/a&gt;, and she&amp;#39;s shared her story in 2 interviews:&lt;br&gt;-&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/rOpenSci?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@rOpenSci&lt;/a&gt; profile by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kellrstats?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@kellrstats&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/bz9Jj4UJqG&#34;&gt;https://t.co/bz9Jj4UJqG&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br&gt;-&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/statschat?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@statschat&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/UFWfgIg2qa&#34;&gt;https://t.co/UFWfgIg2qa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; We are R-Ladies (@WeAreRLadies) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/WeAreRLadies/status/1055124381876260865?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;October 24, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I was told by a PhD thesis committee member that if I returned to Mexico after a postdoc I would &amp;quot;fade into mediocrity&amp;quot;. However, I did return to my home country, started my own lab, and are now well funded to investigate the genetics and genomics of cancer in Mexican patients. &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/9inVPvYkPj&#34;&gt;https://t.co/9inVPvYkPj&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Daniela Robles (@daniela_oaks) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/daniela_oaks/status/1019597807395770368?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 18, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Got a bad news myself today but then I got an AWESOME one from my mom! She got a 9/10 in her chemistry class, her last class to complete her high school!!! I’m so proud of her &amp;amp; how resilient she’s been! My brother &amp;amp; I couldn’t be happier, prouder &amp;amp; dying to hug her! &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/nevergiveup?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#nevergiveup&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; 🇲🇽 Dr. Leonardo Collado-Torres (@fellgernon) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/fellgernon/status/1001985730904764417?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;May 31, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Mexico, Day of the Dead was just last week (November 2nd) and Aldo’s birthday would have been a few weeks ago on October 27th. It was time to finally write this blog post. I hope that you take something positive from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;acknowledgements&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog post was made possible thanks to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://bioconductor.org/packages/3.9/BiocStyle&#34;&gt;BiocStyle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Oles_2018&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://github.com/Bioconductor/BiocStyle&#39;&gt;Oleś, Morgan, and Huber, 2018&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=blogdown&#34;&gt;blogdown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Xie_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&#39;&gt;Xie, Hill, and Thomas, 2017&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&#34;&gt;knitcitations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Boettiger_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&#39;&gt;Boettiger, 2017&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=sessioninfo&#34;&gt;sessioninfo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Csardi_2018&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=sessioninfo&#39;&gt;Csárdi, core, Wickham, Chang, et al., 2018&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;references&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Boettiger_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Boettiger_2017&#34;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt; C. Boettiger. &lt;em&gt;knitcitations: Citations for ‘Knitr’ Markdown Files&lt;/em&gt;. R package version 1.0.8. 2017. URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Csardi_2018&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Csardi_2018&#34;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt; G. Csárdi, R. core, H. Wickham, W. Chang, et al. &lt;em&gt;sessioninfo: R Session Information&lt;/em&gt;. R package version 1.1.1. 2018. URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=sessioninfo&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=sessioninfo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Oles_2018&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Oles_2018&#34;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt; A. Oleś, M. Morgan and W. Huber. &lt;em&gt;BiocStyle: Standard styles for vignettes and other Bioconductor documents&lt;/em&gt;. R package version 2.11.0. 2018. URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Bioconductor/BiocStyle&#34;&gt;https://github.com/Bioconductor/BiocStyle&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Xie_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Xie_2017&#34;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt; Y. Xie, A. P. Hill and A. Thomas. &lt;em&gt;blogdown: Creating Websites with R Markdown&lt;/em&gt;. ISBN 978-0815363729. Boca Raton, Florida: Chapman and Hall/CRC, 2017. URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&#34;&gt;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;reproducibility&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reproducibility&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code for the dates:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;## R code for making the dates.pdf file
## which I then imported into Adobe Illustrator for making
## the timeline.png
x &amp;lt;- paste0(1987:2018, &amp;#39;-&amp;#39;, c(paste0(&amp;#39;0&amp;#39;, 1:9), 10:12), &amp;#39;-01&amp;#39;)

plot(y = seq_len(length(x)), x = as.Date(x), las = 2, ylab = &amp;#39;&amp;#39;, xlab = &amp;#39;&amp;#39;, xaxt= &amp;#39;n&amp;#39;)
axis(1, at = as.Date(x), labels = months(as.Date(x)))


library(&amp;#39;ggplot2&amp;#39;)
library(&amp;#39;scales&amp;#39;)
df &amp;lt;- data.frame(y = 0, date = as.Date(x))


pdf(&amp;#39;dates.pdf&amp;#39;, height = 40,  useDingbats = FALSE)
ggplot(df, aes(y, date)) + 
  geom_line() + 
  scale_y_date(limits = c(as.Date(&amp;quot;1987-07-01&amp;quot;), as.Date(&amp;quot;2018-05-12&amp;quot;)), 
               breaks = date_breaks(&amp;#39;months&amp;#39;),
               date_labels = &amp;quot;%Y-%m&amp;quot;, expand=c(0,30)) +   theme(axis.text.y=element_text(angle=-180))
dev.off()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Registered S3 methods overwritten by &amp;#39;ggplot2&amp;#39;:
##   method         from 
##   [.quosures     rlang
##   c.quosures     rlang
##   print.quosures rlang&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Registered S3 method overwritten by &amp;#39;dplyr&amp;#39;:
##   method               from  
##   as.data.frame.tbl_df tibble&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## ─ Session info ───────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────
##  setting  value                                             
##  version  R Under development (unstable) (2018-11-02 r75540)
##  os       macOS Mojave 10.14.1                              
##  system   x86_64, darwin15.6.0                              
##  ui       X11                                               
##  language (EN)                                              
##  collate  en_US.UTF-8                                       
##  ctype    en_US.UTF-8                                       
##  tz       America/New_York                                  
##  date     2018-11-09                                        
## 
## ─ Packages ───────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────
##  package       * version date       lib source                            
##  assertthat      0.2.0   2017-04-11 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  backports       1.1.2   2017-12-13 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  bibtex          0.4.2   2017-06-30 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  bindr           0.1.1   2018-03-13 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  bindrcpp        0.2.2   2018-03-29 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  BiocManager     1.30.3  2018-10-10 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  BiocStyle     * 2.11.0  2018-10-30 [1] Bioconductor                      
##  blogdown        0.9     2018-10-23 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  bookdown        0.7     2018-02-18 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  cli             1.0.1   2018-09-25 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  colorout      * 1.2-0   2018-11-02 [1] Github (jalvesaq/colorout@cc5fbfa)
##  colorspace      1.3-2   2016-12-14 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  crayon          1.3.4   2017-09-16 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  digest          0.6.18  2018-10-10 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  dplyr           0.7.7   2018-10-16 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  evaluate        0.12    2018-10-09 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  ggplot2       * 3.1.0   2018-10-25 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  glue            1.3.0   2018-07-17 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  gtable          0.2.0   2016-02-26 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  htmltools       0.3.6   2017-04-28 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  httr            1.3.1   2017-08-20 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  jsonlite        1.5     2017-06-01 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  knitcitations * 1.0.8   2017-07-04 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  knitr           1.20    2018-02-20 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  lazyeval        0.2.1   2017-10-29 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  lubridate       1.7.4   2018-04-11 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  magrittr        1.5     2014-11-22 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  munsell         0.5.0   2018-06-12 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  pillar          1.3.0   2018-07-14 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  pkgconfig       2.0.2   2018-08-16 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  plyr            1.8.4   2016-06-08 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  purrr           0.2.5   2018-05-29 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  R6              2.3.0   2018-10-04 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  Rcpp            1.0.0   2018-11-07 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  RefManageR      1.2.0   2018-04-25 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  rlang           0.3.0.1 2018-10-25 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  rmarkdown       1.10    2018-06-11 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  rprojroot       1.3-2   2018-01-03 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  scales        * 1.0.0   2018-08-09 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  sessioninfo   * 1.1.1   2018-11-05 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  stringi         1.2.4   2018-07-20 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  stringr         1.3.1   2018-05-10 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  tibble          1.4.2   2018-01-22 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  tidyselect      0.2.5   2018-10-11 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  withr           2.1.2   2018-03-15 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  xfun            0.4     2018-10-23 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  xml2            1.2.0   2018-01-24 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
##  yaml            2.2.0   2018-07-25 [1] CRAN (R 3.6.0)                    
## 
## [1] /Library/Frameworks/R.framework/Versions/3.6/Resources/library&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;reactions-to-the-blog-post&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reactions to the blog post&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;My good old friend Leo sharing very interesting experiences of his path through academic life, public university system in &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/Mexico?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#Mexico&lt;/a&gt;, and remembering a very special person who taught us a ton of life lessons. &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/nHAiob30jn&#34;&gt;https://t.co/nHAiob30jn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Luis Bolaños (@lbolanos68) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/lbolanos68/status/1060038817774657536?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;November 7, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I&amp;#39;m reading this with tears in my eyes and joy in my heart. I&amp;#39;m so grateful and proud of my friend Leo. I&amp;#39;m so proud of all my classmates! Love you all! Love you Aldo &amp;lt;3 &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/ifOK9ASPmy&#34;&gt;https://t.co/ifOK9ASPmy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Mariana ReyesPrieto. (@RanitaRed) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/RanitaRed/status/1060116424415436800?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;November 7, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Beautiful and inspiring!! Thanks Leo for writing this, for honoring Aldo and being the voice of many (including myself) who feel lucky and grateful for being a LCG alumni! &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/hDyKKThj8B&#34;&gt;https://t.co/hDyKKThj8B&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; paleogenomics (@paleogenomics) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/paleogenomics/status/1060355174546505729?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;November 8, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mine was the very last one of the conference.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Which then lead to my current career. See more at my &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/fellgernon/status/1023665229882961922&#34;&gt;keynote&lt;/a&gt; for the “Latin American R/BioConductor Developers Workshop 2018”.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;My scientific talk was about the BrainSeq Phase II project by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.libd.org/&#34;&gt;Lieber Institute for Brain Development&lt;/a&gt;. It’s now available as a bioRxiv pre-print: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2018/09/26/426213&#34;&gt;426213&lt;/a&gt;. It took a while to finish this project, which contributed to my delay in making this blog post.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn4&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previous versions of my post incorrectly said that he was a farmer.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn5&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I believe that others asked me since I was or had been the class representative.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref5&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I applied to join SNI: the Mexican National Researchers registry</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/09/29/why-i-applied-to-join-sni-the-mexican-national-researchers-registry/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/09/29/why-i-applied-to-join-sni-the-mexican-national-researchers-registry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A few days ago a friend of mine told me that I was on the list of newly admitted SNI members. A few have asked me since why did I request to join it. So here’s my public reply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;es&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Woo! Ya soy &amp;quot;Investigador Nacional Nivel I&amp;quot; en el Sistema Nacional de Investigadores de CONACyT en México &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Conacyt_MX?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@Conacyt_MX&lt;/a&gt; 🎉💪🏾🇲🇽&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I&amp;#39;m a National Researcher lvl I in the Mexican National Researchers Registry ^_^ 🎆🎉&lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/hud7Z22WLY&#34;&gt;https://t.co/hud7Z22WLY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Gracias &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/malacopa_genome?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@malacopa_genome&lt;/a&gt; por el aviso! &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/NWnf90KOF1&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/NWnf90KOF1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; 🇲🇽 Dr. Leonardo Collado-Torres (@fellgernon) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/fellgernon/status/1045051193146396674?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;September 26, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;sni&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;SNI&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First let me tell you what SNI is. It stands for &lt;em&gt;Sistema Nacional de Investigadores&lt;/em&gt; which translates to National Researchers Registry. It’s a way that the Mexican government created in 1984 to recognize &lt;em&gt;high&lt;/em&gt; quality researchers and encourage them to continue to do great research, teach the next generation of researchers and promote innovation (&lt;a href=&#34;https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sistema_Nacional_de_Investigadores_(M%C3%A9xico)&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;). There are three types of members:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Candidato a Investigador Nacional&lt;/em&gt;: Candidate to National Researcher&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Investigador Nacional&lt;/em&gt;: National Researchers with 3 levels (1, 2 and 3)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Investigador Nacional Emérito&lt;/em&gt;: National Emeritus Researcher&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To become a member you have to submit documentation to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Conacyt_MX&#34;&gt;CONACyT&lt;/a&gt; showing that you have made contributions to science, technology, culture and society through scientific or technological developments, training new students, popularizing or translating science and technology, among other criteria. Once you are a member, you have to keep submitting new documents every couple of years to stay a member or advance in the ranks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;the-real-reason-behind-joining-sni&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; reason behind joining SNI&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve read a little bit that there are many critics of the SNI system. Most of the criticisms are based on how they decide what is a &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; contribution and how they judge applications. The reality is also that the process of sending the necessary documentation is cumbersome to say the least. The CONACyT website breaks often enough that it can be painful to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why do people want to join the SNI and go through all this complicated process? The main reason (I think) why people want to join the SNI is because being a member comes with a financial supplement. It’s enough that I’ve heard that it can constitute about a third of your salary. You can find headlines such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.elfinanciero.com.mx/empresas/apoyo-del-conacyt-a-investigadores-paso-de-privilegio-a-sueldo&#34;&gt;how CONACyT’s support to researchers went from a priviledge to a salary&lt;/a&gt;. This financial supplement is given to those members that work 20 hours a week on Mexican institutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given how important this boost in salary is, I can understand very well the frustrations that come with interacting with the CONACyT website: specially when the website goes down and you have to submit your application before a given deadline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;so-why-did-i-apply-to-join-sni&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;So why did I apply to join SNI?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find on CONACyT’s website an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.conacytprensa.mx/index.php/sociedad/politica-cientifica/7698-por-que-es-importante-pertenecer-al-sni&#34;&gt;interview on why it’s important to join SNI&lt;/a&gt; or go elsewhere to read a study on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://sinectica.iteso.mx/index.php/SINECTICA/article/view/155/786&#34;&gt;motivations people have for joining SNI&lt;/a&gt;. But why did I apply to join SNI given that I’m outside Mexico and won’t be getting the financial supplement?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My main motivation was protection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lets say that I return to Mexico as a researcher at UNAM or another Mexican institution. Currently there is only 1 call for new SNI members per year. If I were to return today (September 2018), I would need to wait several months for the 2019 application cycle. Then I would need to wait several months for all applications to be evaluated and would probably start receiving the financial salary boost on January 2020. That is a lot of time to wait!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, right now I don’t need the salary boost. But if I were to return then it could be a significant portion of my salary. Having all this riding on a cumbersome application (I’d be afraid of making a silly mistake in the application) and on an external evaluation would be stressful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the stakes for me were low right now. Now that I’m a SNI member if I were to return to Mexico I could start receiving that financial boost much sooner. Thus I’m also protecting myself by keeping my options open to stay abroad (in the US for me) or return to Mexico. For example, I have a verbal agreement with my boss on the length of my current job, but technically I’m an employee at will and can be fired pretty easily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also applied because I have several friends that were applying or recently applied and helped me a lot navigate the application process&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Also, you never know if the application process will change and become more complicated later on: though I hope that it will get easier!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But back to protection and security. My father has taught me that it’s our responsibility to cover our backs. Lets imagine that I have dependents. It would be irresponsible of me to miss out on the financial supplement because I didn’t send my documentation on time or because I forgot to send in the renewal documents: maybe it wouldn’t affect me, but it would affect them. Completing my application in time is under my control. What CONACyT cares about, their evaluation process, the clarity and reliability of their website are not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;beyond-sni&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Beyond SNI&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This attitude goes beyond SNI. That is why I compete when I can for awards and scholarships that I think fit me, even if its a long shot. No one will come to you and say, “hey, your work is great, now you are a SNI member” (or any award). I believe that you have to keep working and make it hard for others to say no to your applications. You have to keep trying though because you won’t get them all. That was one of my messages in my recent CDSBMexico keynote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Here are my slides for my &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/CDSBMexico?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#CDSBMexico&lt;/a&gt; remote talk tomorrow for day 1 of the &amp;quot;Latin American R/BioConductor Developers Workshop 2018&amp;quot;. 70 slides for ~20 min, I can do this! 💪🏾 Right &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jtleek?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@jtleek&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Shannon_E_Ellis?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@Shannon_E_Ellis&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/xKh2214YbM&#34;&gt;https://t.co/xKh2214YbM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/rstats?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#rstats&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/teaching?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#teaching&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Bioconductor?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@Bioconductor&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/CDSBMexico?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@CDSBMexico&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/SULAoPbHeZ&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/SULAoPbHeZ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; 🇲🇽 Dr. Leonardo Collado-Torres (@fellgernon) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/fellgernon/status/1023665229882961922?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 29, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some of my recent applications:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;You still have time to participate in this year&amp;#39;s SciLifeLab prize! I wrote a blog post about it &amp;amp; shared my unsuccessful 2017 entry &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/6y7DOP1m1a&#34;&gt;https://t.co/6y7DOP1m1a&lt;/a&gt; Got Qs? SciLifeLabPrize@aaas.org &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/sciencemagazine?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@sciencemagazine&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/academia?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#academia&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/science?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#science&lt;/a&gt; Thx &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jtleek?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@jtleek&lt;/a&gt; for the last minute recommendation letter! &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/Yfyq7j9RTc&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/Yfyq7j9RTc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; 🇲🇽 Dr. Leonardo Collado-Torres (@fellgernon) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/fellgernon/status/1009559232931401730?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 20, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Check our &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/Bioinformatics?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#Bioinformatics&lt;/a&gt; Peer Prize III entry at &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/WdggoD6KPh&#34;&gt;https://t.co/WdggoD6KPh&lt;/a&gt; highlighting recount2 &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/tK6iRfUT21&#34;&gt;https://t.co/tK6iRfUT21&lt;/a&gt; We appreciate the votes! Team submission w &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/AbhiNellore?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@AbhiNellore&lt;/a&gt; et al &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/RNAseq?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#RNAseq&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/rstats?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#rstats&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/reproducibility?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#reproducibility&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/scitwitter?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#scitwitter&lt;/a&gt; Video code &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/J0nwUcV3O4&#34;&gt;https://t.co/J0nwUcV3O4&lt;/a&gt; w ari &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/seankross?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@seankross&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; 🇲🇽 Dr. Leonardo Collado-Torres (@fellgernon) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/fellgernon/status/960590896310968320?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;February 5, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I just submitted my rstudio::conf(2019) diversity scholarship app &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/nmZY7UJsiP&#34;&gt;https://t.co/nmZY7UJsiP&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/rstudio?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@rstudio&lt;/a&gt; Text entries have a 1000 char limit!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I&amp;#39;m sharing mine &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/q3wqbSuVbW&#34;&gt;https://t.co/q3wqbSuVbW&lt;/a&gt; in case it helps other &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/LIBDrstats?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@LIBDrstats&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/CDSBMexico?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@CDSBMexico&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/rstats?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#rstats&lt;/a&gt; members at large.&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/tip?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#tip&lt;/a&gt; Always ask for help!&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; 🇲🇽 Dr. Leonardo Collado-Torres (@fellgernon) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/fellgernon/status/1032287739176267776?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;August 22, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I just submitted my application for the &amp;quot;Early Career Clinical Research Symbiont Award&amp;quot;. If I get selected, then I&amp;#39;ll be able to attend &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/PSB19?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#PSB19&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/PacSymBiocomp?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@PacSymBiocomp&lt;/a&gt;. Thx to someone who prompted me to send my application! You should submit yours too. Deadline 9/30 &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/Pv1aHySVbI&#34;&gt;https://t.co/Pv1aHySVbI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; 🇲🇽 Dr. Leonardo Collado-Torres (@fellgernon) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/fellgernon/status/1045763904964612096?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;September 28, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what happens now? I updated my CV as a friend suggested to list that I’m a SNI National Researcher Level 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;acknowledgements&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to thank my friends that helped me during the SNI application process!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;es&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Gracias &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/sur_hp?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@sur_hp&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/FSanchezQuinto?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@FSanchezQuinto&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mariagutierrez?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@mariagutierrez&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/areyesq?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@areyesq&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/malacopa_genome?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@malacopa_genome&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mgschiavon?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@mgschiavon&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/AleMedinaRivera?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@AleMedinaRivera&lt;/a&gt; por el apoyo en todo el proceso de enviar la solicitud y motivarme a enviarla!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Ahora.... me falta obtener la FIEL para firmar el doc de &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Conacyt_MX?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@Conacyt_MX&lt;/a&gt; (creo)... ugh!&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; 🇲🇽 Dr. Leonardo Collado-Torres (@fellgernon) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/fellgernon/status/1045053659967639555?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;September 26, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog post was made possible thanks to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://bioconductor.org/packages/3.8/BiocStyle&#34;&gt;BiocStyle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Oles_2018&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://github.com/Bioconductor/BiocStyle&#39;&gt;Oleś, Morgan, and Huber, 2018&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=blogdown&#34;&gt;blogdown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Xie_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&#39;&gt;Xie, Hill, and Thomas, 2017&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=sessioninfo&#34;&gt;sessioninfo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Csardi_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=sessioninfo&#39;&gt;Csárdi, core, Wickham, Chang, et al., 2017&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&#34;&gt;knitcitations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Boettiger_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&#39;&gt;Boettiger, 2017&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;references&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Boettiger_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Boettiger_2017&#34;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt; C. Boettiger. &lt;em&gt;knitcitations: Citations for ‘Knitr’ Markdown Files&lt;/em&gt;. R package version 1.0.8. 2017. URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitcitations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Csardi_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Csardi_2017&#34;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt; G. Csárdi, R. core, H. Wickham, W. Chang, et al. &lt;em&gt;sessioninfo: R Session Information&lt;/em&gt;. R package version 1.0.0. 2017. URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=sessioninfo&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=sessioninfo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Oles_2018&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Oles_2018&#34;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt; A. Oleś, M. Morgan and W. Huber. &lt;em&gt;BiocStyle: Standard styles for vignettes and other Bioconductor documents&lt;/em&gt;. R package version 2.9.6. 2018. URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Bioconductor/BiocStyle&#34;&gt;https://github.com/Bioconductor/BiocStyle&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Xie_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Xie_2017&#34;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt; Y. Xie, A. P. Hill and A. Thomas. &lt;em&gt;blogdown: Creating Websites with R Markdown&lt;/em&gt;. ISBN 978-0815363729. Boca Raton, Florida: Chapman and Hall/CRC, 2017. URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&#34;&gt;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;reproducibility&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reproducibility&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## ─ Session info ───────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────
##  setting  value                       
##  version  R version 3.5.1 (2018-07-02)
##  os       macOS High Sierra 10.13.6   
##  system   x86_64, darwin15.6.0        
##  ui       X11                         
##  language (EN)                        
##  collate  en_US.UTF-8                 
##  tz       America/New_York            
##  date     2018-09-29                  
## 
## ─ Packages ───────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────
##  package       * version date       source                            
##  backports       1.1.2   2017-12-13 cran (@1.1.2)                     
##  bibtex          0.4.2   2017-06-30 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  BiocManager     1.30.2  2018-08-24 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  BiocStyle     * 2.9.6   2018-08-19 Bioconductor                      
##  blogdown        0.8     2018-07-15 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  bookdown        0.7     2018-02-18 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  clisymbols      1.2.0   2017-05-21 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  colorout      * 1.2-0   2018-05-03 Github (jalvesaq/colorout@c42088d)
##  digest          0.6.17  2018-09-12 CRAN (R 3.5.1)                    
##  evaluate        0.11    2018-07-17 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  htmltools       0.3.6   2017-04-28 cran (@0.3.6)                     
##  httr            1.3.1   2017-08-20 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  jsonlite        1.5     2017-06-01 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  knitcitations * 1.0.8   2017-07-04 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  knitr           1.20    2018-02-20 cran (@1.20)                      
##  lubridate       1.7.4   2018-04-11 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  magrittr        1.5     2014-11-22 cran (@1.5)                       
##  plyr            1.8.4   2016-06-08 cran (@1.8.4)                     
##  R6              2.2.2   2017-06-17 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  Rcpp            0.12.18 2018-07-23 CRAN (R 3.5.1)                    
##  RefManageR      1.2.0   2018-04-25 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  rmarkdown       1.10    2018-06-11 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  rprojroot       1.3-2   2018-01-03 cran (@1.3-2)                     
##  sessioninfo   * 1.0.0   2017-06-21 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  stringi         1.2.4   2018-07-20 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  stringr         1.3.1   2018-05-10 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  withr           2.1.2   2018-03-15 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  xfun            0.3     2018-07-06 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  xml2            1.2.0   2018-01-24 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  yaml            2.2.0   2018-07-25 CRAN (R 3.5.0)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Actually, we are still trying to find out how we can sign the agreement from abroad.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SciLifeLab Prize: you still have time to participate! </title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/06/20/scilifelab-prize-you-still-have-time-to-participate/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/06/20/scilifelab-prize-you-still-have-time-to-participate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-06-20-scilifelab-prize-you-still-have-time-to-participate_files/unnamed.jpg&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have recently been getting reminder emails from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencemag.org/science-scilifelab-prize-young-scientists&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt; &amp;amp; SciLifeLab Prize for Young Scientists&lt;/a&gt;. The application deadline is July 15th, 2018!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year I submitted an entry to this competition and I enjoyed the experience, even if it was a bit rushed. The process of joining the competition is relatively straight forward:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write an essay about your Ph.D. thesis work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get a recommendation letter from your Ph.D. advisor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write a short Ph.D. thesis abstract section, list your affiliation, education, academic and professional awards and professional experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Include references.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don’t need to pay for competing! You already did the very hard part of completing your Ph.D.!!! I also like competitions like this one that invite you to think about your thesis and how to explain it. You should note that you are only eligible to participate once in this competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can read about the 4 winners from 2017 at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencemag.org/prizes/SciLifeLab/2017&#34;&gt;www.sciencemag.org/prizes/SciLifeLab/2017&lt;/a&gt; and other years too to draw some inspiration from. I didn’t win, but I’m still going to share my entry in case it’s useful to others. I’m also sharing it to keep with the theme of also sharing your failures that I talked in my &lt;a href=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/06/11/mindfulness/#.WyrJbBJKjUI&#34;&gt;mindfulness post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t know exactly why my entry was not selected (you might have some ideas on how to improve it!). But I can tell you that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I knew the deadline was coming but I wrote it the week it was due.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I didn’t have time to ask for some more specific feedback from others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I forgot that a recommendation letter was needed, so I asked at the very last minute for one by &lt;a href=&#34;http://jtleek.com/&#34;&gt;Jeff Leek&lt;/a&gt;. I don’t know what magic he did (likely skipping a few hours of sleep, sorry!!!) but he managed to send it in time. Oops!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure if I should have emphasized more the impact of my Ph.D. thesis work or what else to do. However, I do know that this exercise was useful. First, just re-reading my essay makes me smile. Also, Figure 1 shown here became a figure in the &lt;code&gt;recount-workflow&lt;/code&gt; paper &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Collado-Torres_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://f1000research.com/articles/6-1558/v1&#39;&gt;Collado-Torres, Nellore, and Jaffe, 2017&lt;/a&gt;). Furthermore, when I was notified about the &lt;a href=&#34;https://bioinformatics-peer-prize-iii.thinkable.org/&#34;&gt;Thinkable Bioinformatics Peer Prize III&lt;/a&gt; I didn’t have to think twice about joining that competition. Finally, since I wrote it in an Rmd file, it was easy to modify for this blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like I’ve said, you have nothing to lose by joining this competition. Yes, you have to invest a bit of time. But it can be helpful and morale boosting! Plus, you have a chance to win it!!! Just remember that the deadline is July 15th, 2018 (and to give your advisor enough time to write their recommendation letter for you)!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case you are curious, here are my full &lt;a href=&#34;https://gist.github.com/lcolladotor/657aaae9d16aff3ce468f44f8780a317&#34;&gt;entry files&lt;/a&gt; (the figure is here though).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Collado-Torres_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Collado-Torres_2017&#34;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt; L. Collado-Torres, A. Nellore and A. E. Jaffe. “recount workflow: Accessing over 70,000 human RNA-seq samples with Bioconductor [version 1; referees: 1 approved, 2 approved with reservations]”. In: &lt;em&gt;F1000Research&lt;/em&gt; (2017). DOI: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.12688/f1000research.12223.1&#34;&gt;10.12688/f1000research.12223.1&lt;/a&gt;. URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://f1000research.com/articles/6-1558/v1&#34;&gt;https://f1000research.com/articles/6-1558/v1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without further ado, here’s my full entry:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;usable-human-gene-expression-data-and-annotation-agnostic-methods&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Usable human gene expression data and annotation-agnostic methods&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the last decade RNA sequencing (RNA-seq) has become the predominant assay for measuring gene expression. RNA-seq allows us to measure all expressed genes, improve gene and transcript annotation, and measure expressed sequences that otherwise are excluded in microarray studies. Typical RNA-seq analysis starts with a matrix containing the number of RNA-seq reads overlapping each gene for each sample &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Love et al. 2016; Law et al. 2016)&lt;/span&gt;. To compute such a matrix, you first map the raw data to the genome with aligners such as &lt;em&gt;TopHat2&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;HISAT&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Kim et al. 2013; Kim, Langmead, and Salzberg 2015)&lt;/span&gt; and then use tools such as &lt;em&gt;Rsubread&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;HTSeq&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Y, GK, and W 2013; Anders, Pyl, and Huber 2014)&lt;/span&gt; to construct the read count matrix. After measuring enough samples, you can determine which genes are differentially expressed between two or more groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I started my graduate studies with Jeff Leek, the most commonly used methods for differential expression analysis were &lt;em&gt;DESeq&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Anders and Huber 2010)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;em&gt;edgeR&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Robinson, McCarthy, and Smyth 2010)&lt;/span&gt;. Leek and colleagues put together a set of gene count matrices in a project called &lt;em&gt;ReCount&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Frazee, Langmead, and Leek 2011)&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;em&gt;ReCount&lt;/em&gt; allowed researchers to access several datasets without having to run the whole processing pipeline. &lt;em&gt;ReCount&lt;/em&gt; then helped the development of new methods such as &lt;em&gt;DESeq2&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Love, Huber, and Anders 2014)&lt;/span&gt;. It was also Leek and colleagues that decided to look at RNA-seq data in a manner less dependent on potentially incomplete gene annotation. With the increase in size of RNA-seq projects, they thought it would be feasible to assess the differential expression signal at base pair resolution in an approach called differentially expressed regions (DER) finder &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Frazee et al. 2014)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was around then that I started to work with Andrew Jaffe, who had RNA-seq data from the human brain. Jaffe and colleagues hypothesized that the gene annotation for the human brain might be incomplete and were interested in applying the DER finder approach to their data. With them, I modified the DER finder approach to make it computationally feasible to analyze these human brain samples at base resolution &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Jaffe et al. 2015)&lt;/span&gt;. We indeed found that the human brain transcriptome was not fully annotated and identified intronic DERs that were present in other brain datasets, including from mouse, and showed these regions were enriched for genetic risk for brain disorders. Further computational improvements to the DER finder approach yielded the &lt;em&gt;derfinder&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Collado-Torres, Nellore, Frazee, et al. 2017)&lt;/span&gt; Bioconductor &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Huber et al. 2015)&lt;/span&gt; package, reducing computing time from days to hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I was working on &lt;em&gt;derfinder&lt;/em&gt;, Abhinav Nellore was developing &lt;em&gt;Rail-RNA&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Nellore, Collado-Torres, et al. 2016)&lt;/span&gt; with the goal of aligning large RNA-seq datasets. We determined that we only needed coverage data instead of alignments to use &lt;em&gt;derfinder&lt;/em&gt; and to perform gene level analyses. Coverage data files are much smaller than alignment files, which meant that we could greatly reduce our storage costs when using &lt;em&gt;Rail-RNA&lt;/em&gt; and allowed us to think as big as possible. Initially we looked at 21,504 human RNA-seq samples and explored the landscape of exon-exon junctions &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Nellore, Jaffe, et al. 2016)&lt;/span&gt;. The reads spanning exon-exon junctions provided by &lt;em&gt;Rail-RNA&lt;/em&gt; can be used for a second type of annotation-agnostic analysis as these reads provide information about exon skipping, alternative donor/acceptor sites and novel events. With a fairly conservative filter we determined that 18.6% of exon-exon junctions were missing in the annotation &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Nellore, Jaffe, et al. 2016)&lt;/span&gt;. This observation along with the fact that exon-exon junctions can be used to determine differential transcript usage gave strength to this second annotation-agnostic RNA-seq analysis method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Researchers around the world have shared their raw data via the Sequence Read Archive or via large consortiums such as the Genotype-Tissue Expression study (GTEx) and the Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA). However, it still is complicated to align and compute count matrices for these datasets. We thought that if the public data was uniformly processed that we could make this large body of human expression data more reusable. We were well positioned to carry out this project and just needed resources. Luckily, Jeff Leek, Ben Langmead and others got together and funded the implementation of &lt;em&gt;Rail-RNA&lt;/em&gt; to analyze all the human public RNA-seq data available at the time, over 70,000 samples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34; style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;
&lt;span id=&#34;fig:figure1&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-06-20-scilifelab-prize-you-still-have-time-to-participate_files/figure1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Overview of the data available in recount2. Reads aligned to the reference genome can be used to compute a base pair coverage curve, identify exon-exon junctions and compute gene and exon count matrices. The reads spanning exon-exon junctions (jx) are used to compute a third count matrix that includes un-annotated junctions (jx 3 and 4). Annotation-agnostic expressed regions can be determined from the coverage data.&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
Figure 1: Overview of the data available in recount2. Reads aligned to the reference genome can be used to compute a base pair coverage curve, identify exon-exon junctions and compute gene and exon count matrices. The reads spanning exon-exon junctions (jx) are used to compute a third count matrix that includes un-annotated junctions (jx 3 and 4). Annotation-agnostic expressed regions can be determined from the coverage data.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We computed gene count matrices for these 70,000 samples and made them available as the &lt;em&gt;recount2&lt;/em&gt; resource that can be accessed at &lt;a href=&#34;https://jhubiostatistics.shinyapps.io/recount/&#34;&gt;jhubiostatistics.shinyapps.io/recount/&lt;/a&gt; as well as through the &lt;em&gt;recount&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Collado-Torres, Nellore, Kammers, et al. 2017)&lt;/span&gt; Bioconductor package, thus representing a major improvement over &lt;em&gt;ReCount&lt;/em&gt;. To take advantage of the data as much as possible, we also released exon and exon-exon junction count matrices as well as the coverage data files required for the DER finder approach, thus enabling both annotation-agnostic methods we developed that complement traditional methods. Figure 1 illustrates the type of information that is available via &lt;em&gt;recount2&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My colleagues and I believe that &lt;em&gt;recount2&lt;/em&gt; will fuel the development of new analytical methods and greatly increase the usability of the public human gene expression data researchers have collected over the years. In the meantime, we are working hard on improving the data in &lt;em&gt;recount2&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Ellis, Collado-Torres, and Leek 2017; Wilks et al. 2017)&lt;/span&gt; and exploring how to leverage results from different RNA-seq analytical approaches &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Jaffe et al. 2017)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ph.d.thesis-abstract&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ph.D. thesis abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leonardo Collado-Torres’ thesis work is centered around the development of R software packages for analyzing RNA sequencing (RNA-seq) and ChIP sequencing (ChIP-seq) high throughput genomic data. The first chapter describes the &lt;em&gt;derfinder&lt;/em&gt; Bioconductor package which implements the DER Finder approach for identifying differentially expressed regions with RNA-seq data in an annotation-agnostic manner. The second chapter shows how &lt;em&gt;derfinder&lt;/em&gt; can be applied to ChIP-seq data to identify differentially bounded regions. The third chapter describes the &lt;em&gt;regionReport&lt;/em&gt; Bioconductor package for producing HTML or PDF reports from region-based genomic analyses, such as the &lt;em&gt;derfinder&lt;/em&gt; analyses described in the previous chapters. The last thesis project Leonardo Collado-Torres carried out was the development of the &lt;em&gt;recount2&lt;/em&gt; resource and accompanying &lt;em&gt;recount&lt;/em&gt; Bioconductor package using the &lt;em&gt;Rail-RNA&lt;/em&gt; results from processing all the public human RNA-seq data at the time, which spans over 70,000 samples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;affiliation&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Affiliation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lieber Institute for Brain Development, Johns Hopkins Medical Campus, Baltimore, Maryland, 21205, USA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;education&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Education&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2011-2016. Ph.D. in Biostatistics at Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health, Baltimore, US. Advised by Jeff Leek and Andrew Jaffe.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2005-2009. Bachelor in Genomic Sciences (LCG) at the National Autonomous University of Mexico (UNAM), Cuernavaca, MX.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2002-2005. High school at ITESM Campus Cuernavaca, Cuernavaca, MX.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;academic-and-professional-awards&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Academic and professional awards&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2011: Awarded CONACyT Mexico scholarship for PhD studies outside Mexico.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2009: &lt;em&gt;Summa Cum Laude&lt;/em&gt; for bachelor in Genomic Sciences studies at LCG-UNAM.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2005: Best high school average (&lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\sim\)&lt;/span&gt; 200 students): awarded ITESM system 90% scholarship for college studies, declined to join LCG-UNAM.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;professional-experience&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Professional experience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016-current. Data Scientist with Andrew Jaffe lab at LIBD, Baltimore. At LIBD, Dr. Collado-Torres is part of the Data Science team which goals include better understanding and characterizing genomics signatures in the human brain, including DNA methylation and gene expression. Leonardo helps mentor other team members, provides support for LIBD projects and is advancing his academic career as part of Andrew Jaffe’s lab.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2009-2011. Bioinformatician with Enrique Morett lab at IBT-UNAM, Cuernavaca, MX. Identified transcriptions start sites and transcription units in &lt;em&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Geobacter sulfurreducens&lt;/em&gt; with RNA-seq data. Developed the &lt;em&gt;BacterialTranscription&lt;/em&gt; R package.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2009-2011. Scientific executive at Winter Genomics in Cuernavaca, MX. Responsible for recruiting and hiring new personnel, overseeing and supervising bioinformaticians, training new employees, writing research reports and presenting them to colleagues, and organizing all scientific projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2007-2009. Undergraduate research assistant at Guillermo Davila’s lab at CCG-UNAM, Cuernavaca, MX. Determined bacteriophage ecological groups by developing a method based on codon distribution of all phage sequenced genomes. Joint work with Sur Herrera Paredes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2006-2007. Undergraduate research assistant at Roberto Kolter’s lab at Harvard, Boston, US. Supervisor: Elizabeth Shank. Carried out screenings to identify bacteria that activate the production of exopolysaccharide through the activation of the gene tasA in &lt;em&gt;Bacillus subtilis&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;references&#34; class=&#34;section level2 unnumbered&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;refs&#34; class=&#34;references&#34;&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-anders2010&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anders, Simon, and Wolfgang Huber. 2010. “Differential Expression Analysis for Sequence Count Data.” &lt;em&gt;Genome Biology&lt;/em&gt; 11 (10): R106. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1186/gb-2010-11-10-r106&#34;&gt;10.1186/gb-2010-11-10-r106&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-anders2014htseq&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anders, Simon, Paul Theodor Pyl, and Wolfgang Huber. 2014. “HTSeq–A Python Framework to Work with High-Throughput Sequencing Data.” &lt;em&gt;bioRxiv&lt;/em&gt;. Cold Spring Harbor Labs Journals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-collado-torres-derfinder&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Collado-Torres, Leonardo, Abhinav Nellore, Alyssa C. Frazee, Christopher Wilks, Michael I. Love, Ben Langmead, Rafael A. Irizarry, Jeffrey T. Leek, and Andrew E. Jaffe. 2017. “Flexible Expressed Region Analysis for RNA-Seq with Derfinder.” &lt;em&gt;Nucleic Acids Research&lt;/em&gt; 45 (2): e9–e9. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkw852&#34;&gt;10.1093/nar/gkw852&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-collado-torres-recount2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Collado-Torres, Leonardo, Abhinav Nellore, Kai Kammers, Shannon E. Ellis, Margaret A. Taub, Kasper D. Hansen, Andrew E. Jaffe, Ben Langmead, and Jeffrey T. Leek. 2017. “Reproducible RNA-Seq Analysis Using Recount2.” &lt;em&gt;Nature Biotechnology&lt;/em&gt; 35 (4): 319–21. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/nbt.3838&#34;&gt;10.1038/nbt.3838&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-ellis2017&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ellis, Shannon E, Leonardo Collado-Torres, and Jeffrey Leek. 2017. “Improving the Value of Public Rna-Seq Expression Data by Phenotype Prediction.” &lt;em&gt;bioRxiv&lt;/em&gt;. Cold Spring Harbor Labs Journals. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1101/145656&#34;&gt;10.1101/145656&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-frazee2014&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frazee, Alyssa C, Sarven Sabunciyan, Kasper D Hansen, Rafael A Irizarry, and Jeffrey T Leek. 2014. “Differential Expression Analysis of RNA-seq Data at Single-Base Resolution.” &lt;em&gt;Biostatistics (Oxford, England)&lt;/em&gt;, January. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1093/biostatistics/kxt053&#34;&gt;10.1093/biostatistics/kxt053&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-frazee2011&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frazee, Alyssa C., Ben Langmead, and Jeffrey T. Leek. 2011. “ReCount: A Multi-Experiment Resource of Analysis-Ready RNA-Seq Gene Count Datasets.” &lt;em&gt;BMC Bioinformatics&lt;/em&gt; 12: 449. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2105-12-449&#34;&gt;10.1186/1471-2105-12-449&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-huber2015&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Huber, Wolfgang, Vincent J Carey, Robert Gentleman, Simon Anders, Marc Carlson, Benilton S Carvalho, Hector Corrada Bravo, et al. 2015. “Orchestrating High-Throughput Genomic Analysis with Bioconductor.” &lt;em&gt;Nature Methods&lt;/em&gt; 12 (2). Nature Publishing Group: 115–21. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/nmeth.3252&#34;&gt;10.1038/nmeth.3252&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-jaffe2015&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jaffe, Andrew E., Jooheon Shin, Leonardo Collado-Torres, Jeffrey T. Leek, Ran Tao, Chao Li, Yuan Gao, et al. 2015. “Developmental Regulation of Human Cortex Transcription and Its Clinical Relevance at Single Base Resolution.” &lt;em&gt;Nature Neuroscience&lt;/em&gt; 18 (1): 154–61. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/nn.3898&#34;&gt;10.1038/nn.3898&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-jaffe2017&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jaffe, Andrew E., Richard Straub, Joo Heon Shin, Ran Tao, Yuan Gao, Leonardo Collado-Torres, Tony Kam-Thong, et al. 2017. “Developmental and genetic regulation of the human cortex transcriptome in schizophrenia.” &lt;em&gt;bioRxiv&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-kim2015&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kim, Daehwan, Ben Langmead, and Steven L. Salzberg. 2015. “HISAT: A Fast Spliced Aligner with Low Memory Requirements.” &lt;em&gt;Nature Methods&lt;/em&gt; 12 (4): 357–60. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/nmeth.3317&#34;&gt;10.1038/nmeth.3317&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-kim2013&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kim, Daehwan, Geo Pertea, Cole Trapnell, Harold Pimentel, Ryan Kelley, and Steven L Salzberg. 2013. “TopHat2: Accurate Alignment of Transcriptomes in the Presence of Insertions, Deletions and Gene Fusions.” &lt;em&gt;Genome Biology&lt;/em&gt; 14 (4): R36. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1186/gb-2013-14-4-r36&#34;&gt;10.1186/gb-2013-14-4-r36&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-Law2016a&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Law, Charity W, Monther Alhamdoosh, Shian Su, Gordon K Smyth, and Matthew E Ritchie. 2016. “RNA-seq analysis is easy as 1-2-3 with limma, Glimma and edgeR.” &lt;em&gt;F1000Research&lt;/em&gt; 5 (May): 1408. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.12688/f1000research.9005.2&#34;&gt;10.12688/f1000research.9005.2&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-love2014&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Love, Michael I, Wolfgang Huber, and Simon Anders. 2014. “Moderated Estimation of Fold Change and Dispersion for Rna-Seq Data with Deseq2.” &lt;em&gt;Genome Biology&lt;/em&gt; 15 (12). Springer: 1–21.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-Love2016&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Love, Michael I., Simon Anders, Vladislav Kim, and Wolfgang Huber. 2016. “RNA-Seq workflow: gene-level exploratory analysis and differential expression.” &lt;em&gt;F1000Research&lt;/em&gt; 4 (May): 1070. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.12688/f1000research.7035.2&#34;&gt;10.12688/f1000research.7035.2&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-rail-rna&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nellore, Abhinav, Leonardo Collado-Torres, Andrew E. Jaffe, José Alquicira-Hernández, Christopher Wilks, Jacob Pritt, James Morton, Jeffrey T. Leek, and Ben Langmead. 2016. “Rail-RNA: Scalable Analysis of RNA-Seq Splicing and Coverage.” &lt;em&gt;Bioinformatics (Oxford, England)&lt;/em&gt;, September. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btw575&#34;&gt;10.1093/bioinformatics/btw575&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-nellore2016human&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nellore, Abhinav, Andrew E. Jaffe, Jean-Philippe Fortin, José Alquicira-Hernández, Leonardo Collado-Torres, Siruo Wang, Robert A. Phillips Iii, et al. 2016. “Human Splicing Diversity and the Extent of Unannotated Splice Junctions Across Human RNA-Seq Samples on the Sequence Read Archive.” &lt;em&gt;Genome Biology&lt;/em&gt; 17 (1): 266.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-robinson2010&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Robinson, Mark D, Davis J McCarthy, and Gordon K Smyth. 2010. “edgeR: a Bioconductor Package for Differential Expression Analysis of Digital Gene Expression Data.” &lt;em&gt;Bioinformatics (Oxford, England)&lt;/em&gt; 26 (1): 139–40. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btp616&#34;&gt;10.1093/bioinformatics/btp616&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-wilks2017&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wilks, Christopher, Phani Gaddipati, Abhinav Nellore, and Benjamin Langmead. 2017. “Snaptron: querying and visualizing splicing across tens of thousands of RNA-seq samples.” &lt;em&gt;bioRxiv&lt;/em&gt;. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1101/097881&#34;&gt;10.1101/097881&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-rsubread&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Y, Liao, Smyth GK, and Shi W. 2013. “The Subread Aligner: Fast, Accurate and Scalable Read Mapping by Seed-and-Vote.” &lt;em&gt;Nucleic Acids Research&lt;/em&gt; 41 (10): e108.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mindfulness</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/06/11/mindfulness/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/06/11/mindfulness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently participated for the first time in a silent retreat (6 hrs) as part of a &lt;em&gt;Mindfulness-Based Stress Reduction&lt;/em&gt; course. I’ve really been enjoying this course and the experience of learning new ways (for me) to live better and enjoy life more. If you haven’t heard of &lt;em&gt;mindfulness&lt;/em&gt; before (like me a few months ago), &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mindfulness&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; defines it as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Mindfulness is the psychological process of bringing one&amp;#39;s attention to
experiences occurring in the present moment, which can be developed
through the practice of meditation and other training.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In academia and science, but really anywhere, we can encounter many sources of stress (some examples below). We all deal with it in different ways and this MBSR course is just one that I’m liking right now and recommend. If there’s no course near you, check out the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00C4BA3UK&#34;&gt;Full Catastrophe Living&lt;/a&gt; book that my course is based on&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these tweets are threads, so you’ll have to open them to see them: click on the blue bird on the right side of each tweet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I won an NSF grant yesterday, with three weeks to go before applying to tenure. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A thread👇&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Dr. Bryony DuPont (@BryonyDuPont) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/BryonyDuPont/status/1005618536100683777?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 10, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Just another barrier that us scientists in &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/developing?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#developing&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/countries?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#countries&lt;/a&gt; need to find ways to overcome. Not only do we have less funding, but also generating data that for other countries is routine is more expensive. &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/latin?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#latin&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/american?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#american&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/scientists?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#scientists&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/plight?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#plight&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/Hln7N4x4iM&#34;&gt;https://t.co/Hln7N4x4iM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Daniela Robles (@daniela_oaks) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/daniela_oaks/status/1004798860835938305?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 7, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Thanks for sharing this Ted! &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/tladeras?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@tladeras&lt;/a&gt; As with anything, but particularly with mental health, I think it’s important to know you are not alone and that some things we feel have names: impostor syndrome, anxiety, depression, etc. Our minds are very powerful! &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/MentalHealthMatters?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#MentalHealthMatters&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/X1UIAznV8f&#34;&gt;https://t.co/X1UIAznV8f&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; 🇲🇽 Dr. Leonardo Collado-Torres (@fellgernon) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/fellgernon/status/1004478330257707008?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 6, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the exercises on our silent retreat was &lt;em&gt;mindful eating&lt;/em&gt;. That is, eating slowly and focusing on our senses while eating food. This involved smelling the food, seeing all the colors it has, feeling all the different textures, and focusing on its taste. Plus, not talking to anyone. I had bought a lunch before the retreat (so I wouldn’t have to break the silence during it) that I normally don’t find interesting: some fruit and a chicken curry wrap from CVS. But wow, it was amazing that day! I greatly enjoyed how it tasted and all the different sensations I felt. I couldn’t believe it was the same food I had eaten other times before without much excitement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lately I’ve been processing some strong feelings related to feeling unwelcome, homesickness and loneliness. I’m doing many things that I know help me, starting with talking about them with my family. I’ve also been keeping myself busy doing some sports outside, going to events, bars, having friends over, etc. But what motivated me to write this post today is that after lunch I left really bad today. I had to go outside and try to calm myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-06-11-mindfulness_files/2018-06-11_13.25.34.jpg&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought I did, returned to work, and nah, I couldn’t do it today. So I went home, rested in my room in the dark, and I find myself finishing this post about 2 hours later. I’m not sure it’s related to the MSBR course, but I’m wondering if the mindfulness practice is also opening my mind’s ears and eyes to my inner feelings way more than normal&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I don’t think it’s bad. It’s just that it’s way harder to enjoy this process than it was eating a lunch. I’m trying to feel happy because I have feelings and I’m recognizing them. My family is also happy because they view it as a part of maturing and that I’m getting ready for taking another step in my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just some things are taking me way more time than normal. For example, it took me 2 days to process what I wanted to reply to a tweet and how to word it: it turned out well because I think we all heard each other ^^.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Thanks for the link &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/apreshill?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@apreshill&lt;/a&gt;! I agree that the blog post was aweful! You can’t blame X for the fact that X is marginalized. However, I disagree with the notion that Z can’t talk about X (challenging). I’m in favor of inclusion. Otherwise that line of thought leads to xenophobia&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; 🇲🇽 Dr. Leonardo Collado-Torres (@fellgernon) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/fellgernon/status/1006207918813958145?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 11, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also discovered that the silent retreat reminded me of vacations where I turn off my phone/email and spend a few days thinking about what’s next. I used to go to Mexico every 6 months or so during my PhD to recharge. I want to do it again, but I can’t. That lead me to my strong feelings of homesickness I had today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just to close, I’m OK. I appreciate all the support I have and I recommend others to learn about mindfulness. You might be missing out some super tasty lunches and/or an exploration trip towards your inner self.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also want to add that I know some of you might see this post as over-sharing (yes, it might be). One reply is that I think that leaders also have to show their vulnerable sides. This has been debated a lot in academic twitter accounts in the context of showing your failures too, not just your successes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;acknowledgements&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog post was made possible thanks to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=blogdown&#34;&gt;blogdown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Xie_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&#39;&gt;Xie, Hill, and Thomas, 2017&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&#34;&gt;devtools&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Wickham_2018&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&#39;&gt;Wickham, Hester, and Chang, 2018&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;references&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Wickham_2018&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Wickham_2018&#34;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt; H. Wickham, J. Hester and W. Chang. &lt;em&gt;devtools: Tools to Make Developing R Packages Easier&lt;/em&gt;. R package version 1.13.5. 2018. URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Xie_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Xie_2017&#34;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt; Y. Xie, A. P. Hill and A. Thomas. &lt;em&gt;blogdown: Creating Websites with R Markdown&lt;/em&gt;. ISBN 978-0815363729. Boca Raton, Florida: Chapman and Hall/CRC, 2017. URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&#34;&gt;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;reproducibility&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reproducibility&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Session info ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##  setting  value                       
##  version  R version 3.5.0 (2018-04-23)
##  system   x86_64, darwin15.6.0        
##  ui       X11                         
##  language (EN)                        
##  collate  en_US.UTF-8                 
##  tz       America/New_York            
##  date     2018-06-11&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Packages --------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##  package       * version date       source                            
##  backports       1.1.2   2017-12-13 cran (@1.1.2)                     
##  base          * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  bibtex          0.4.2   2017-06-30 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  BiocStyle     * 2.8.1   2018-05-17 Bioconductor                      
##  blogdown        0.6     2018-04-18 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  bookdown        0.7     2018-02-18 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  colorout      * 1.2-0   2018-05-03 Github (jalvesaq/colorout@c42088d)
##  compiler        3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  datasets      * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  devtools      * 1.13.5  2018-02-18 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  digest          0.6.15  2018-01-28 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  evaluate        0.10.1  2017-06-24 cran (@0.10.1)                    
##  graphics      * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  grDevices     * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  htmltools       0.3.6   2017-04-28 cran (@0.3.6)                     
##  httr            1.3.1   2017-08-20 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  jsonlite        1.5     2017-06-01 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  knitcitations * 1.0.8   2017-07-04 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  knitr           1.20    2018-02-20 cran (@1.20)                      
##  lubridate       1.7.4   2018-04-11 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  magrittr        1.5     2014-11-22 cran (@1.5)                       
##  memoise         1.1.0   2017-04-21 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  methods       * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  plyr            1.8.4   2016-06-08 cran (@1.8.4)                     
##  R6              2.2.2   2017-06-17 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  Rcpp            0.12.17 2018-05-18 cran (@0.12.17)                   
##  RefManageR      1.2.0   2018-04-25 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  rmarkdown       1.9     2018-03-01 cran (@1.9)                       
##  rprojroot       1.3-2   2018-01-03 cran (@1.3-2)                     
##  stats         * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  stringi         1.2.2   2018-05-02 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  stringr         1.3.1   2018-05-10 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  tools           3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  utils         * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  withr           2.1.2   2018-03-15 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  xfun            0.1     2018-01-22 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  xml2            1.2.0   2018-01-24 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  yaml            2.1.19  2018-05-01 CRAN (R 3.5.0)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Baltimore friends, I have a paper copy if you want to borrow it for a while.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;It could be a coincidence with other events in my life.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Homepage photos: which cheek you show says something?</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/08/30/Homepage-photos-which-cheek-you-show-says-something/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/08/30/Homepage-photos-which-cheek-you-show-says-something/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;John Bohannon wrote &lt;a href=&#34;http://news.sciencemag.org/sciencenow/2012/08/scientists-photos-reveal-their.html&#34;&gt;Scientists&amp;#8217; Photos Reveal Their Inner Mr. Spock&lt;/a&gt; which I found funny in a science-curious kind of way. I hadn&amp;#8217;t thought about the message you could be sending depending on which cheek you show. I had only noticed that people like to show more serious-looking photos of themselves and sometimes make it an obviously funny one. I have to say too that some of the pages from my co-workers don&amp;#8217;t even show a picture. I guess that&amp;#8217;s a more recent trend to make it more &amp;#8220;professional&amp;#8221; looking. Dunno.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to guess that dead center-looking pictures are rare. At least when you look at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psy.gla.ac.uk/staff/index.php?id=RJ002&#34;&gt;Rachael Jack&amp;#8217;s one&lt;/a&gt; it stands out. It reminds me of passport pictures. For my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu/~lcollado/index.html#.UD-xBmie5us&#34;&gt;new academic site&lt;/a&gt; I choose one that doesn&amp;#8217;t look serious, I wanted a fun one! Plus I make it obvious which country I&amp;#8217;m from ^^.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some reason this doesn&amp;#8217;t surprise me:&lt;/p&gt;
&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;while English language and literature scholars showed the left cheek and engineers showed the right, psychologists were more difficult to categorize. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is science cool?</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/08/27/Is-science-cool/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/08/27/Is-science-cool/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Adam Ruben shares his answer to whether science is cool or not. Since &amp;#8220;cool&amp;#8221; depends on the current trends, this question is set on the recent landing of Curiosity. It&amp;#8217;s the landrover that recently landed on Mars and has been sending some pictures back. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, check his answer &lt;a href=&#34;http://sciencecareers.sciencemag.org/career_magazine/previous_issues/articles/2012_08_24/caredit.a1200095&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I liked this part:&lt;/p&gt;
&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;If the Mars landing draws students to science, it won’t be because they witnessed science doing something cool. It’ll be because they witnessed science doing something human, something genuine, something legitimately appealing on its own merits. Something scientific.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img height=&#34;500&#34; src=&#34;http://www.sciencemag.org/sites/default/files/styles/article_main_large/public/images/20120824_sci_tattoo_Large2.jpg?itok=2YZjjKxZ&amp;c=51fb542122567392ab5e85ed6388a89f&#34; width=&#34;500&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Picture taken from his commentary piece.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pollination video</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/03/01/great-video-thank-you-aunt-for-sending-it-to-me/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/03/01/great-video-thank-you-aunt-for-sending-it-to-me/</guid>
      <description>&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/xHkq1edcbk4&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great video! Thank you aunt for sending it to me =)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
