<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Science on L. Collado-Torres</title>
    <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/tags/Science/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Science on L. Collado-Torres</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2011-2018 Leonardo Collado Torres under (CC) BY-NC-SA 4.0. All thoughts and opinions here are my own.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://lcolladotor.github.io/tags/Science/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>SciLifeLab Prize: you still have time to participate! </title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/06/20/scilifelab-prize-you-still-have-time-to-participate/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/06/20/scilifelab-prize-you-still-have-time-to-participate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-06-20-scilifelab-prize-you-still-have-time-to-participate_files/unnamed.jpg&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have recently been getting reminder emails from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencemag.org/science-scilifelab-prize-young-scientists&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt; &amp;amp; SciLifeLab Prize for Young Scientists&lt;/a&gt;. The application deadline is July 15th, 2018!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year I submitted an entry to this competition and I enjoyed the experience, even if it was a bit rushed. The process of joining the competition is relatively straight forward:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write an essay about your Ph.D. thesis work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get a recommendation letter from your Ph.D. advisor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write a short Ph.D. thesis abstract section, list your affiliation, education, academic and professional awards and professional experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Include references.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don’t need to pay for competing! You already did the very hard part of completing your Ph.D.!!! I also like competitions like this one that invite you to think about your thesis and how to explain it. You should note that you are only eligible to participate once in this competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can read about the 4 winners from 2017 at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencemag.org/prizes/SciLifeLab/2017&#34;&gt;www.sciencemag.org/prizes/SciLifeLab/2017&lt;/a&gt; and other years too to draw some inspiration from. I didn’t win, but I’m still going to share my entry in case it’s useful to others. I’m also sharing it to keep with the theme of also sharing your failures that I talked in my &lt;a href=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/06/11/mindfulness/#.WyrJbBJKjUI&#34;&gt;mindfulness post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t know exactly why my entry was not selected (you might have some ideas on how to improve it!). But I can tell you that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I knew the deadline was coming but I wrote it the week it was due.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I didn’t have time to ask for some more specific feedback from others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I forgot that a recommendation letter was needed, so I asked at the very last minute for one by &lt;a href=&#34;http://jtleek.com/&#34;&gt;Jeff Leek&lt;/a&gt;. I don’t know what magic he did (likely skipping a few hours of sleep, sorry!!!) but he managed to send it in time. Oops!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure if I should have emphasized more the impact of my Ph.D. thesis work or what else to do. However, I do know that this exercise was useful. First, just re-reading my essay makes me smile. Also, Figure 1 shown here became a figure in the &lt;code&gt;recount-workflow&lt;/code&gt; paper &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Collado-Torres_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://f1000research.com/articles/6-1558/v1&#39;&gt;Collado-Torres, Nellore, and Jaffe, 2017&lt;/a&gt;). Furthermore, when I was notified about the &lt;a href=&#34;https://bioinformatics-peer-prize-iii.thinkable.org/&#34;&gt;Thinkable Bioinformatics Peer Prize III&lt;/a&gt; I didn’t have to think twice about joining that competition. Finally, since I wrote it in an Rmd file, it was easy to modify for this blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like I’ve said, you have nothing to lose by joining this competition. Yes, you have to invest a bit of time. But it can be helpful and morale boosting! Plus, you have a chance to win it!!! Just remember that the deadline is July 15th, 2018 (and to give your advisor enough time to write their recommendation letter for you)!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case you are curious, here are my full &lt;a href=&#34;https://gist.github.com/lcolladotor/657aaae9d16aff3ce468f44f8780a317&#34;&gt;entry files&lt;/a&gt; (the figure is here though).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Collado-Torres_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Collado-Torres_2017&#34;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt; L. Collado-Torres, A. Nellore and A. E. Jaffe. “recount workflow: Accessing over 70,000 human RNA-seq samples with Bioconductor [version 1; referees: 1 approved, 2 approved with reservations]”. In: &lt;em&gt;F1000Research&lt;/em&gt; (2017). DOI: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.12688/f1000research.12223.1&#34;&gt;10.12688/f1000research.12223.1&lt;/a&gt;. URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://f1000research.com/articles/6-1558/v1&#34;&gt;https://f1000research.com/articles/6-1558/v1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without further ado, here’s my full entry:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;usable-human-gene-expression-data-and-annotation-agnostic-methods&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Usable human gene expression data and annotation-agnostic methods&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the last decade RNA sequencing (RNA-seq) has become the predominant assay for measuring gene expression. RNA-seq allows us to measure all expressed genes, improve gene and transcript annotation, and measure expressed sequences that otherwise are excluded in microarray studies. Typical RNA-seq analysis starts with a matrix containing the number of RNA-seq reads overlapping each gene for each sample &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Love et al. 2016; Law et al. 2016)&lt;/span&gt;. To compute such a matrix, you first map the raw data to the genome with aligners such as &lt;em&gt;TopHat2&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;HISAT&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Kim et al. 2013; Kim, Langmead, and Salzberg 2015)&lt;/span&gt; and then use tools such as &lt;em&gt;Rsubread&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;HTSeq&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Y, GK, and W 2013; Anders, Pyl, and Huber 2014)&lt;/span&gt; to construct the read count matrix. After measuring enough samples, you can determine which genes are differentially expressed between two or more groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I started my graduate studies with Jeff Leek, the most commonly used methods for differential expression analysis were &lt;em&gt;DESeq&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Anders and Huber 2010)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;em&gt;edgeR&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Robinson, McCarthy, and Smyth 2010)&lt;/span&gt;. Leek and colleagues put together a set of gene count matrices in a project called &lt;em&gt;ReCount&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Frazee, Langmead, and Leek 2011)&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;em&gt;ReCount&lt;/em&gt; allowed researchers to access several datasets without having to run the whole processing pipeline. &lt;em&gt;ReCount&lt;/em&gt; then helped the development of new methods such as &lt;em&gt;DESeq2&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Love, Huber, and Anders 2014)&lt;/span&gt;. It was also Leek and colleagues that decided to look at RNA-seq data in a manner less dependent on potentially incomplete gene annotation. With the increase in size of RNA-seq projects, they thought it would be feasible to assess the differential expression signal at base pair resolution in an approach called differentially expressed regions (DER) finder &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Frazee et al. 2014)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was around then that I started to work with Andrew Jaffe, who had RNA-seq data from the human brain. Jaffe and colleagues hypothesized that the gene annotation for the human brain might be incomplete and were interested in applying the DER finder approach to their data. With them, I modified the DER finder approach to make it computationally feasible to analyze these human brain samples at base resolution &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Jaffe et al. 2015)&lt;/span&gt;. We indeed found that the human brain transcriptome was not fully annotated and identified intronic DERs that were present in other brain datasets, including from mouse, and showed these regions were enriched for genetic risk for brain disorders. Further computational improvements to the DER finder approach yielded the &lt;em&gt;derfinder&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Collado-Torres, Nellore, Frazee, et al. 2017)&lt;/span&gt; Bioconductor &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Huber et al. 2015)&lt;/span&gt; package, reducing computing time from days to hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I was working on &lt;em&gt;derfinder&lt;/em&gt;, Abhinav Nellore was developing &lt;em&gt;Rail-RNA&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Nellore, Collado-Torres, et al. 2016)&lt;/span&gt; with the goal of aligning large RNA-seq datasets. We determined that we only needed coverage data instead of alignments to use &lt;em&gt;derfinder&lt;/em&gt; and to perform gene level analyses. Coverage data files are much smaller than alignment files, which meant that we could greatly reduce our storage costs when using &lt;em&gt;Rail-RNA&lt;/em&gt; and allowed us to think as big as possible. Initially we looked at 21,504 human RNA-seq samples and explored the landscape of exon-exon junctions &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Nellore, Jaffe, et al. 2016)&lt;/span&gt;. The reads spanning exon-exon junctions provided by &lt;em&gt;Rail-RNA&lt;/em&gt; can be used for a second type of annotation-agnostic analysis as these reads provide information about exon skipping, alternative donor/acceptor sites and novel events. With a fairly conservative filter we determined that 18.6% of exon-exon junctions were missing in the annotation &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Nellore, Jaffe, et al. 2016)&lt;/span&gt;. This observation along with the fact that exon-exon junctions can be used to determine differential transcript usage gave strength to this second annotation-agnostic RNA-seq analysis method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Researchers around the world have shared their raw data via the Sequence Read Archive or via large consortiums such as the Genotype-Tissue Expression study (GTEx) and the Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA). However, it still is complicated to align and compute count matrices for these datasets. We thought that if the public data was uniformly processed that we could make this large body of human expression data more reusable. We were well positioned to carry out this project and just needed resources. Luckily, Jeff Leek, Ben Langmead and others got together and funded the implementation of &lt;em&gt;Rail-RNA&lt;/em&gt; to analyze all the human public RNA-seq data available at the time, over 70,000 samples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34; style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;
&lt;span id=&#34;fig:figure1&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-06-20-scilifelab-prize-you-still-have-time-to-participate_files/figure1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Overview of the data available in recount2. Reads aligned to the reference genome can be used to compute a base pair coverage curve, identify exon-exon junctions and compute gene and exon count matrices. The reads spanning exon-exon junctions (jx) are used to compute a third count matrix that includes un-annotated junctions (jx 3 and 4). Annotation-agnostic expressed regions can be determined from the coverage data.&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
Figure 1: Overview of the data available in recount2. Reads aligned to the reference genome can be used to compute a base pair coverage curve, identify exon-exon junctions and compute gene and exon count matrices. The reads spanning exon-exon junctions (jx) are used to compute a third count matrix that includes un-annotated junctions (jx 3 and 4). Annotation-agnostic expressed regions can be determined from the coverage data.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We computed gene count matrices for these 70,000 samples and made them available as the &lt;em&gt;recount2&lt;/em&gt; resource that can be accessed at &lt;a href=&#34;https://jhubiostatistics.shinyapps.io/recount/&#34;&gt;jhubiostatistics.shinyapps.io/recount/&lt;/a&gt; as well as through the &lt;em&gt;recount&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Collado-Torres, Nellore, Kammers, et al. 2017)&lt;/span&gt; Bioconductor package, thus representing a major improvement over &lt;em&gt;ReCount&lt;/em&gt;. To take advantage of the data as much as possible, we also released exon and exon-exon junction count matrices as well as the coverage data files required for the DER finder approach, thus enabling both annotation-agnostic methods we developed that complement traditional methods. Figure 1 illustrates the type of information that is available via &lt;em&gt;recount2&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My colleagues and I believe that &lt;em&gt;recount2&lt;/em&gt; will fuel the development of new analytical methods and greatly increase the usability of the public human gene expression data researchers have collected over the years. In the meantime, we are working hard on improving the data in &lt;em&gt;recount2&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Ellis, Collado-Torres, and Leek 2017; Wilks et al. 2017)&lt;/span&gt; and exploring how to leverage results from different RNA-seq analytical approaches &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Jaffe et al. 2017)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ph.d.thesis-abstract&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ph.D. thesis abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leonardo Collado-Torres’ thesis work is centered around the development of R software packages for analyzing RNA sequencing (RNA-seq) and ChIP sequencing (ChIP-seq) high throughput genomic data. The first chapter describes the &lt;em&gt;derfinder&lt;/em&gt; Bioconductor package which implements the DER Finder approach for identifying differentially expressed regions with RNA-seq data in an annotation-agnostic manner. The second chapter shows how &lt;em&gt;derfinder&lt;/em&gt; can be applied to ChIP-seq data to identify differentially bounded regions. The third chapter describes the &lt;em&gt;regionReport&lt;/em&gt; Bioconductor package for producing HTML or PDF reports from region-based genomic analyses, such as the &lt;em&gt;derfinder&lt;/em&gt; analyses described in the previous chapters. The last thesis project Leonardo Collado-Torres carried out was the development of the &lt;em&gt;recount2&lt;/em&gt; resource and accompanying &lt;em&gt;recount&lt;/em&gt; Bioconductor package using the &lt;em&gt;Rail-RNA&lt;/em&gt; results from processing all the public human RNA-seq data at the time, which spans over 70,000 samples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;affiliation&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Affiliation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lieber Institute for Brain Development, Johns Hopkins Medical Campus, Baltimore, Maryland, 21205, USA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;education&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Education&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2011-2016. Ph.D. in Biostatistics at Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health, Baltimore, US. Advised by Jeff Leek and Andrew Jaffe.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2005-2009. Bachelor in Genomic Sciences (LCG) at the National Autonomous University of Mexico (UNAM), Cuernavaca, MX.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2002-2005. High school at ITESM Campus Cuernavaca, Cuernavaca, MX.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;academic-and-professional-awards&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Academic and professional awards&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2011: Awarded CONACyT Mexico scholarship for PhD studies outside Mexico.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2009: &lt;em&gt;Summa Cum Laude&lt;/em&gt; for bachelor in Genomic Sciences studies at LCG-UNAM.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2005: Best high school average (&lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\sim\)&lt;/span&gt; 200 students): awarded ITESM system 90% scholarship for college studies, declined to join LCG-UNAM.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;professional-experience&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Professional experience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016-current. Data Scientist with Andrew Jaffe lab at LIBD, Baltimore. At LIBD, Dr. Collado-Torres is part of the Data Science team which goals include better understanding and characterizing genomics signatures in the human brain, including DNA methylation and gene expression. Leonardo helps mentor other team members, provides support for LIBD projects and is advancing his academic career as part of Andrew Jaffe’s lab.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2009-2011. Bioinformatician with Enrique Morett lab at IBT-UNAM, Cuernavaca, MX. Identified transcriptions start sites and transcription units in &lt;em&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Geobacter sulfurreducens&lt;/em&gt; with RNA-seq data. Developed the &lt;em&gt;BacterialTranscription&lt;/em&gt; R package.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2009-2011. Scientific executive at Winter Genomics in Cuernavaca, MX. Responsible for recruiting and hiring new personnel, overseeing and supervising bioinformaticians, training new employees, writing research reports and presenting them to colleagues, and organizing all scientific projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2007-2009. Undergraduate research assistant at Guillermo Davila’s lab at CCG-UNAM, Cuernavaca, MX. Determined bacteriophage ecological groups by developing a method based on codon distribution of all phage sequenced genomes. Joint work with Sur Herrera Paredes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2006-2007. Undergraduate research assistant at Roberto Kolter’s lab at Harvard, Boston, US. Supervisor: Elizabeth Shank. Carried out screenings to identify bacteria that activate the production of exopolysaccharide through the activation of the gene tasA in &lt;em&gt;Bacillus subtilis&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;references&#34; class=&#34;section level2 unnumbered&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;refs&#34; class=&#34;references&#34;&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-anders2010&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anders, Simon, and Wolfgang Huber. 2010. “Differential Expression Analysis for Sequence Count Data.” &lt;em&gt;Genome Biology&lt;/em&gt; 11 (10): R106. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1186/gb-2010-11-10-r106&#34;&gt;10.1186/gb-2010-11-10-r106&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-anders2014htseq&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anders, Simon, Paul Theodor Pyl, and Wolfgang Huber. 2014. “HTSeq–A Python Framework to Work with High-Throughput Sequencing Data.” &lt;em&gt;bioRxiv&lt;/em&gt;. Cold Spring Harbor Labs Journals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-collado-torres-derfinder&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Collado-Torres, Leonardo, Abhinav Nellore, Alyssa C. Frazee, Christopher Wilks, Michael I. Love, Ben Langmead, Rafael A. Irizarry, Jeffrey T. Leek, and Andrew E. Jaffe. 2017. “Flexible Expressed Region Analysis for RNA-Seq with Derfinder.” &lt;em&gt;Nucleic Acids Research&lt;/em&gt; 45 (2): e9–e9. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkw852&#34;&gt;10.1093/nar/gkw852&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-collado-torres-recount2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Collado-Torres, Leonardo, Abhinav Nellore, Kai Kammers, Shannon E. Ellis, Margaret A. Taub, Kasper D. Hansen, Andrew E. Jaffe, Ben Langmead, and Jeffrey T. Leek. 2017. “Reproducible RNA-Seq Analysis Using Recount2.” &lt;em&gt;Nature Biotechnology&lt;/em&gt; 35 (4): 319–21. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/nbt.3838&#34;&gt;10.1038/nbt.3838&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-ellis2017&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ellis, Shannon E, Leonardo Collado-Torres, and Jeffrey Leek. 2017. “Improving the Value of Public Rna-Seq Expression Data by Phenotype Prediction.” &lt;em&gt;bioRxiv&lt;/em&gt;. Cold Spring Harbor Labs Journals. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1101/145656&#34;&gt;10.1101/145656&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-frazee2014&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frazee, Alyssa C, Sarven Sabunciyan, Kasper D Hansen, Rafael A Irizarry, and Jeffrey T Leek. 2014. “Differential Expression Analysis of RNA-seq Data at Single-Base Resolution.” &lt;em&gt;Biostatistics (Oxford, England)&lt;/em&gt;, January. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1093/biostatistics/kxt053&#34;&gt;10.1093/biostatistics/kxt053&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-frazee2011&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frazee, Alyssa C., Ben Langmead, and Jeffrey T. Leek. 2011. “ReCount: A Multi-Experiment Resource of Analysis-Ready RNA-Seq Gene Count Datasets.” &lt;em&gt;BMC Bioinformatics&lt;/em&gt; 12: 449. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2105-12-449&#34;&gt;10.1186/1471-2105-12-449&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-huber2015&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Huber, Wolfgang, Vincent J Carey, Robert Gentleman, Simon Anders, Marc Carlson, Benilton S Carvalho, Hector Corrada Bravo, et al. 2015. “Orchestrating High-Throughput Genomic Analysis with Bioconductor.” &lt;em&gt;Nature Methods&lt;/em&gt; 12 (2). Nature Publishing Group: 115–21. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/nmeth.3252&#34;&gt;10.1038/nmeth.3252&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-jaffe2015&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jaffe, Andrew E., Jooheon Shin, Leonardo Collado-Torres, Jeffrey T. Leek, Ran Tao, Chao Li, Yuan Gao, et al. 2015. “Developmental Regulation of Human Cortex Transcription and Its Clinical Relevance at Single Base Resolution.” &lt;em&gt;Nature Neuroscience&lt;/em&gt; 18 (1): 154–61. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/nn.3898&#34;&gt;10.1038/nn.3898&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-jaffe2017&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jaffe, Andrew E., Richard Straub, Joo Heon Shin, Ran Tao, Yuan Gao, Leonardo Collado-Torres, Tony Kam-Thong, et al. 2017. “Developmental and genetic regulation of the human cortex transcriptome in schizophrenia.” &lt;em&gt;bioRxiv&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-kim2015&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kim, Daehwan, Ben Langmead, and Steven L. Salzberg. 2015. “HISAT: A Fast Spliced Aligner with Low Memory Requirements.” &lt;em&gt;Nature Methods&lt;/em&gt; 12 (4): 357–60. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/nmeth.3317&#34;&gt;10.1038/nmeth.3317&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-kim2013&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kim, Daehwan, Geo Pertea, Cole Trapnell, Harold Pimentel, Ryan Kelley, and Steven L Salzberg. 2013. “TopHat2: Accurate Alignment of Transcriptomes in the Presence of Insertions, Deletions and Gene Fusions.” &lt;em&gt;Genome Biology&lt;/em&gt; 14 (4): R36. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1186/gb-2013-14-4-r36&#34;&gt;10.1186/gb-2013-14-4-r36&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-Law2016a&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Law, Charity W, Monther Alhamdoosh, Shian Su, Gordon K Smyth, and Matthew E Ritchie. 2016. “RNA-seq analysis is easy as 1-2-3 with limma, Glimma and edgeR.” &lt;em&gt;F1000Research&lt;/em&gt; 5 (May): 1408. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.12688/f1000research.9005.2&#34;&gt;10.12688/f1000research.9005.2&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-love2014&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Love, Michael I, Wolfgang Huber, and Simon Anders. 2014. “Moderated Estimation of Fold Change and Dispersion for Rna-Seq Data with Deseq2.” &lt;em&gt;Genome Biology&lt;/em&gt; 15 (12). Springer: 1–21.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-Love2016&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Love, Michael I., Simon Anders, Vladislav Kim, and Wolfgang Huber. 2016. “RNA-Seq workflow: gene-level exploratory analysis and differential expression.” &lt;em&gt;F1000Research&lt;/em&gt; 4 (May): 1070. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.12688/f1000research.7035.2&#34;&gt;10.12688/f1000research.7035.2&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-rail-rna&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nellore, Abhinav, Leonardo Collado-Torres, Andrew E. Jaffe, José Alquicira-Hernández, Christopher Wilks, Jacob Pritt, James Morton, Jeffrey T. Leek, and Ben Langmead. 2016. “Rail-RNA: Scalable Analysis of RNA-Seq Splicing and Coverage.” &lt;em&gt;Bioinformatics (Oxford, England)&lt;/em&gt;, September. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btw575&#34;&gt;10.1093/bioinformatics/btw575&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-nellore2016human&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nellore, Abhinav, Andrew E. Jaffe, Jean-Philippe Fortin, José Alquicira-Hernández, Leonardo Collado-Torres, Siruo Wang, Robert A. Phillips Iii, et al. 2016. “Human Splicing Diversity and the Extent of Unannotated Splice Junctions Across Human RNA-Seq Samples on the Sequence Read Archive.” &lt;em&gt;Genome Biology&lt;/em&gt; 17 (1): 266.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-robinson2010&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Robinson, Mark D, Davis J McCarthy, and Gordon K Smyth. 2010. “edgeR: a Bioconductor Package for Differential Expression Analysis of Digital Gene Expression Data.” &lt;em&gt;Bioinformatics (Oxford, England)&lt;/em&gt; 26 (1): 139–40. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btp616&#34;&gt;10.1093/bioinformatics/btp616&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-wilks2017&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wilks, Christopher, Phani Gaddipati, Abhinav Nellore, and Benjamin Langmead. 2017. “Snaptron: querying and visualizing splicing across tens of thousands of RNA-seq samples.” &lt;em&gt;bioRxiv&lt;/em&gt;. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1101/097881&#34;&gt;10.1101/097881&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-rsubread&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Y, Liao, Smyth GK, and Shi W. 2013. “The Subread Aligner: Fast, Accurate and Scalable Read Mapping by Seed-and-Vote.” &lt;em&gt;Nucleic Acids Research&lt;/em&gt; 41 (10): e108.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mindfulness</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/06/11/mindfulness/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/06/11/mindfulness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently participated for the first time in a silent retreat (6 hrs) as part of a &lt;em&gt;Mindfulness-Based Stress Reduction&lt;/em&gt; course. I’ve really been enjoying this course and the experience of learning new ways (for me) to live better and enjoy life more. If you haven’t heard of &lt;em&gt;mindfulness&lt;/em&gt; before (like me a few months ago), &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mindfulness&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; defines it as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Mindfulness is the psychological process of bringing one&amp;#39;s attention to
experiences occurring in the present moment, which can be developed
through the practice of meditation and other training.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In academia and science, but really anywhere, we can encounter many sources of stress (some examples below). We all deal with it in different ways and this MBSR course is just one that I’m liking right now and recommend. If there’s no course near you, check out the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00C4BA3UK&#34;&gt;Full Catastrophe Living&lt;/a&gt; book that my course is based on&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these tweets are threads, so you’ll have to open them to see them: click on the blue bird on the right side of each tweet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I won an NSF grant yesterday, with three weeks to go before applying to tenure. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A thread👇&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Dr. Bryony DuPont (@BryonyDuPont) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/BryonyDuPont/status/1005618536100683777?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 10, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Just another barrier that us scientists in &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/developing?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#developing&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/countries?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#countries&lt;/a&gt; need to find ways to overcome. Not only do we have less funding, but also generating data that for other countries is routine is more expensive. &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/latin?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#latin&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/american?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#american&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/scientists?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#scientists&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/plight?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#plight&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/Hln7N4x4iM&#34;&gt;https://t.co/Hln7N4x4iM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Daniela Robles (@daniela_oaks) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/daniela_oaks/status/1004798860835938305?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 7, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Thanks for sharing this Ted! &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/tladeras?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@tladeras&lt;/a&gt; As with anything, but particularly with mental health, I think it’s important to know you are not alone and that some things we feel have names: impostor syndrome, anxiety, depression, etc. Our minds are very powerful! &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/MentalHealthMatters?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#MentalHealthMatters&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/X1UIAznV8f&#34;&gt;https://t.co/X1UIAznV8f&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; L. Collado-Torres (@fellgernon) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/fellgernon/status/1004478330257707008?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 6, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the exercises on our silent retreat was &lt;em&gt;mindful eating&lt;/em&gt;. That is, eating slowly and focusing on our senses while eating food. This involved smelling the food, seeing all the colors it has, feeling all the different textures, and focusing on its taste. Plus, not talking to anyone. I had bought a lunch before the retreat (so I wouldn’t have to break the silence during it) that I normally don’t find interesting: some fruit and a chicken curry wrap from CVS. But wow, it was amazing that day! I greatly enjoyed how it tasted and all the different sensations I felt. I couldn’t believe it was the same food I had eaten other times before without much excitement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lately I’ve been processing some strong feelings related to feeling unwelcome, homesickness and loneliness. I’m doing many things that I know help me, starting with talking about them with my family. I’ve also been keeping myself busy doing some sports outside, going to events, bars, having friends over, etc. But what motivated me to write this post today is that after lunch I left really bad today. I had to go outside and try to calm myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://lcolladotor.github.io/post/2018-06-11-mindfulness_files/2018-06-11_13.25.34.jpg&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought I did, returned to work, and nah, I couldn’t do it today. So I went home, rested in my room in the dark, and I find myself finishing this post about 2 hours later. I’m not sure it’s related to the MSBR course, but I’m wondering if the mindfulness practice is also opening my mind’s ears and eyes to my inner feelings way more than normal&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I don’t think it’s bad. It’s just that it’s way harder to enjoy this process than it was eating a lunch. I’m trying to feel happy because I have feelings and I’m recognizing them. My family is also happy because they view it as a part of maturing and that I’m getting ready for taking another step in my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just some things are taking me way more time than normal. For example, it took me 2 days to process what I wanted to reply to a tweet and how to word it: it turned out well because I think we all heard each other ^^.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Thanks for the link &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/apreshill?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@apreshill&lt;/a&gt;! I agree that the blog post was aweful! You can’t blame X for the fact that X is marginalized. However, I disagree with the notion that Z can’t talk about X (challenging). I’m in favor of inclusion. Otherwise that line of thought leads to xenophobia&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; L. Collado-Torres (@fellgernon) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/fellgernon/status/1006207918813958145?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 11, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also discovered that the silent retreat reminded me of vacations where I turn off my phone/email and spend a few days thinking about what’s next. I used to go to Mexico every 6 months or so during my PhD to recharge. I want to do it again, but I can’t. That lead me to my strong feelings of homesickness I had today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just to close, I’m OK. I appreciate all the support I have and I recommend others to learn about mindfulness. You might be missing out some super tasty lunches and/or an exploration trip towards your inner self.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also want to add that I know some of you might see this post as over-sharing (yes, it might be). One reply is that I think that leaders also have to show their vulnerable sides. This has been debated a lot in academic twitter accounts in the context of showing your failures too, not just your successes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;acknowledgements&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog post was made possible thanks to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=blogdown&#34;&gt;blogdown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Xie_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&#39;&gt;Xie, Hill, and Thomas, 2017&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&#34;&gt;devtools&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a id=&#39;cite-Wickham_2018&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(&lt;a href=&#39;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&#39;&gt;Wickham, Hester, and Chang, 2018&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;references&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Wickham_2018&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Wickham_2018&#34;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt; H. Wickham, J. Hester and W. Chang. &lt;em&gt;devtools: Tools to Make Developing R Packages Easier&lt;/em&gt;. R package version 1.13.5. 2018. URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id=&#39;bib-Xie_2017&#39;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cite-Xie_2017&#34;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;cite&gt; Y. Xie, A. P. Hill and A. Thomas. &lt;em&gt;blogdown: Creating Websites with R Markdown&lt;/em&gt;. ISBN 978-0815363729. Boca Raton, Florida: Chapman and Hall/CRC, 2017. URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&#34;&gt;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;reproducibility&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reproducibility&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Session info ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##  setting  value                       
##  version  R version 3.5.0 (2018-04-23)
##  system   x86_64, darwin15.6.0        
##  ui       X11                         
##  language (EN)                        
##  collate  en_US.UTF-8                 
##  tz       America/New_York            
##  date     2018-06-11&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Packages --------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##  package       * version date       source                            
##  backports       1.1.2   2017-12-13 cran (@1.1.2)                     
##  base          * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  bibtex          0.4.2   2017-06-30 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  BiocStyle     * 2.8.1   2018-05-17 Bioconductor                      
##  blogdown        0.6     2018-04-18 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  bookdown        0.7     2018-02-18 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  colorout      * 1.2-0   2018-05-03 Github (jalvesaq/colorout@c42088d)
##  compiler        3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  datasets      * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  devtools      * 1.13.5  2018-02-18 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  digest          0.6.15  2018-01-28 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  evaluate        0.10.1  2017-06-24 cran (@0.10.1)                    
##  graphics      * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  grDevices     * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  htmltools       0.3.6   2017-04-28 cran (@0.3.6)                     
##  httr            1.3.1   2017-08-20 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  jsonlite        1.5     2017-06-01 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  knitcitations * 1.0.8   2017-07-04 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  knitr           1.20    2018-02-20 cran (@1.20)                      
##  lubridate       1.7.4   2018-04-11 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  magrittr        1.5     2014-11-22 cran (@1.5)                       
##  memoise         1.1.0   2017-04-21 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  methods       * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  plyr            1.8.4   2016-06-08 cran (@1.8.4)                     
##  R6              2.2.2   2017-06-17 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  Rcpp            0.12.17 2018-05-18 cran (@0.12.17)                   
##  RefManageR      1.2.0   2018-04-25 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  rmarkdown       1.9     2018-03-01 cran (@1.9)                       
##  rprojroot       1.3-2   2018-01-03 cran (@1.3-2)                     
##  stats         * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  stringi         1.2.2   2018-05-02 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  stringr         1.3.1   2018-05-10 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  tools           3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  utils         * 3.5.0   2018-04-24 local                             
##  withr           2.1.2   2018-03-15 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  xfun            0.1     2018-01-22 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  xml2            1.2.0   2018-01-24 CRAN (R 3.5.0)                    
##  yaml            2.1.19  2018-05-01 CRAN (R 3.5.0)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Baltimore friends, I have a paper copy if you want to borrow it for a while.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;It could be a coincidence with other events in my life.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Homepage photos: which cheek you show says something?</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/08/30/Homepage-photos-which-cheek-you-show-says-something/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/08/30/Homepage-photos-which-cheek-you-show-says-something/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;John Bohannon wrote &lt;a href=&#34;http://news.sciencemag.org/sciencenow/2012/08/scientists-photos-reveal-their.html&#34;&gt;Scientists&amp;#8217; Photos Reveal Their Inner Mr. Spock&lt;/a&gt; which I found funny in a science-curious kind of way. I hadn&amp;#8217;t thought about the message you could be sending depending on which cheek you show. I had only noticed that people like to show more serious-looking photos of themselves and sometimes make it an obviously funny one. I have to say too that some of the pages from my co-workers don&amp;#8217;t even show a picture. I guess that&amp;#8217;s a more recent trend to make it more &amp;#8220;professional&amp;#8221; looking. Dunno.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to guess that dead center-looking pictures are rare. At least when you look at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psy.gla.ac.uk/staff/index.php?id=RJ002&#34;&gt;Rachael Jack&amp;#8217;s one&lt;/a&gt; it stands out. It reminds me of passport pictures. For my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu/~lcollado/index.html#.UD-xBmie5us&#34;&gt;new academic site&lt;/a&gt; I choose one that doesn&amp;#8217;t look serious, I wanted a fun one! Plus I make it obvious which country I&amp;#8217;m from ^^.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some reason this doesn&amp;#8217;t surprise me:&lt;/p&gt;
&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;while English language and literature scholars showed the left cheek and engineers showed the right, psychologists were more difficult to categorize. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is science cool?</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/08/27/Is-science-cool/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/08/27/Is-science-cool/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Adam Ruben shares his answer to whether science is cool or not. Since &amp;#8220;cool&amp;#8221; depends on the current trends, this question is set on the recent landing of Curiosity. It&amp;#8217;s the landrover that recently landed on Mars and has been sending some pictures back. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, check his answer &lt;a href=&#34;http://sciencecareers.sciencemag.org/career_magazine/previous_issues/articles/2012_08_24/caredit.a1200095&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I liked this part:&lt;/p&gt;
&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;If the Mars landing draws students to science, it won’t be because they witnessed science doing something cool. It’ll be because they witnessed science doing something human, something genuine, something legitimately appealing on its own merits. Something scientific.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img height=&#34;500&#34; src=&#34;http://www.sciencemag.org/sites/default/files/styles/article_main_large/public/images/20120824_sci_tattoo_Large2.jpg?itok=2YZjjKxZ&amp;c=51fb542122567392ab5e85ed6388a89f&#34; width=&#34;500&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Picture taken from his commentary piece.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pollination video</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/03/01/great-video-thank-you-aunt-for-sending-it-to-me/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/03/01/great-video-thank-you-aunt-for-sending-it-to-me/</guid>
      <description>&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/xHkq1edcbk4&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great video! Thank you aunt for sending it to me =)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
