<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Coursera on L. Collado-Torres</title>
    <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/tags/Coursera/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Coursera on L. Collado-Torres</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2011-2018 Leonardo Collado Torres under (CC) BY-NC-SA</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://lcolladotor.github.io/tags/Coursera/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;I am a writer&#34; exercise</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/21/I-am-a-writer-exercise/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/21/I-am-a-writer-exercise/</guid>
      <description>I do not have a clear memory of when I started to write or in which language it was. My first written words might have been in English since I lived in Boston (USA) three years during my early childhood. By age five I was back in Mexico and that is where I am sure I wrote my first full homeworks. During elementary school, I changed languages once more—this time to French.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>And so begins English Composition I</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/21/And-so-begins-English-Composition-I/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/21/And-so-begins-English-Composition-I/</guid>
      <description>This week started the English Composition I: Achieving Expertise course (Comer, 2013) that I have been looking forward to.
I am not sure yet how long I will last, but I hope to enjoy it as much as I can. Plus, it should help me with my posting and other writing areas. While I last in the course, I plan to publish my writings in the blog too. So you will hopefully see me be more active here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Online Bioinformatics Curriculum</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/10/07/an-online-bioinformatics-curriculum/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/10/07/an-online-bioinformatics-curriculum/</guid>
      <description>Last week I talked about online courses in my JHSPH-Biostat through Coursera post. Now I&amp;#8217;m back to comment on An Online Bioinformatics Curriculum by David B. Searls. Sur Herrera pointed out this paper to me, and I have to say that if you are considering learning bioinformatics online it will be very useful to you. David Searls first goes through a history recap of online (free) courses. Notably, in the last year Coursera and other startups offered their first courses.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>JHSPH-Biostat through Coursera</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/10/01/JHSPH-Biostat-through-Coursera/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/10/01/JHSPH-Biostat-through-Coursera/</guid>
      <description>Have you heard of online education? If you are in the US or Mexico I&amp;#8217;m sure that you have seen some ads about online universities. Well, that&amp;#8217;s not the type of education I&amp;#8217;m talking about. I&amp;#8217;m talking about free high-quality education. For some years, the top option has been the Open Courseware (OCW) organized under the Open Courseware Consortium (OCWC). Back in 2009 I was pushed my undergrad (LCG-UNAM) to design and teach OCW-compliant courses.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>