<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Git on L. Collado-Torres</title>
    <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/tags/Git/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Git on L. Collado-Torres</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2011-2018 Leonardo Collado Torres under (CC) BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://lcolladotor.github.io/tags/Git/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Sharing my work for &#34;Advanced Methods III&#34;</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/02/13/Sharing-my-work-for-Advanced-Methods-III/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/02/13/Sharing-my-work-for-Advanced-Methods-III/</guid>
      <description>This semester I&amp;#8217;m taking the live version of the Data Analysis class by Jeff Leek. His more popular version of the course is available through Coursera. One of the things that Jeff promotes is reproducibility and sharing code. I share that tendency and thus created a Git repository for my homework and code for the class: lcollado753. I&amp;#8217;m hosting it with GitHub to try it out since I started with Mercurial via Bitbucket.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bitbucket revamped</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/10/09/Bitbucket-revamped/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/10/09/Bitbucket-revamped/</guid>
      <description>Bitbucket announced their new &amp;#8220;look&amp;#8221; today. The goal is to make it more team friendly but I guess that they also wanted to make it look fresh.
For example, the overview page now has a quick summary:
 That can be useful coupled with the simpler navigation tabs. But I think that the best of the new tools is the ability to comment at a given commit at any line change.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing Git while making your academic webpage</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/09/24/Introducing-Git-while-making-your-academic-webpage/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/09/24/Introducing-Git-while-making-your-academic-webpage/</guid>
      <description>Last week I gave a presentation during our computing club on how to use git (a version control system). I used as a motivating example the first steps of creating your own academic webpage. The goal was to make it interesting to both new students (who might have been more interested on the webpage part) and older students (for whom version control should be a must). The slides and all the material is publicly available through the following Bitbucket repository: https://bitbucket.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Version control: need to learn Git</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/09/05/i-consider-myself-a-fan-of-using-version-control/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/09/05/i-consider-myself-a-fan-of-using-version-control/</guid>
      <description>I consider myself a fan of using version control for bioinformatics/biostatistics (or any text based, like code) project. Yet my knowledge of version control systems is quite limited. I&amp;#8217;ve used Mercurial for some time, but I haven&amp;#8217;t ventured much beyond the basic commands and some GUIs for merging.
I don&amp;#8217;t recall how it all went, but I remember reading that Subversion (SVN) was much better than CVS. Also, the Bioconductor project uses SVN.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>