<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Nfl on L. Collado-Torres</title>
    <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/tags/nfl/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Nfl on L. Collado-Torres</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2011-2018 Leonardo Collado Torres under (CC) BY-NC-SA</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://lcolladotor.github.io/tags/nfl/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Do analytics really tell the whole story?&#34;</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/31/Do-analytics-really-tell-the-whole-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/31/Do-analytics-really-tell-the-whole-story/</guid>
      <description>&amp;#8220;Do analytics really tell the whole story?&#34; by Vic Ketchman explores how analytics is used nowadays in the NFL draft. The entry point is the &#34;Moneyball&#34; movie and Ketchman&amp;#8217;s piece is mainly a digested interview to Tony Villiotti from draftmetrics.com
According to him:
 What is analytics? It’s the accumulation of meaningful patterns in data, for the purpose of using that data to predict future results.
 I&amp;#8217;m not a fan of the wording used, but well, the point they make is that they use data to predict the future.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predicting who will win a NFL match at half time</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/23/Predicting-who-will-win-a-NFL-match-at-half-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/23/Predicting-who-will-win-a-NFL-match-at-half-time/</guid>
      <description>It was great to have a little break, Spring break, although the weather didn&amp;#8217;t feel like spring at all! During the early part of the break I worked on my final project for Jeff Leek&amp;#8217;s data analysis class, which we call 140.753 here. Continuing my previous posts on the topic, this time I&amp;#8217;ll share the results of my final project.
At the beginning of the course, we had to submit a project plan (more like a proposal) and in mine I announced my interest to look into some sports data.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>