<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Graphics on L. Collado-Torres</title>
    <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/tags/graphics/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Graphics on L. Collado-Torres</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2011-2017 Leonardo Collado Torres under (CC) BY-NC-SA</copyright>
    <atom:link href="/tags/graphics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Why aren&#39;t all of our graphs interactive?</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/10/08/why-arent-all-of-our-graphs-interactive</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/10/08/why-arent-all-of-our-graphs-interactive</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During the last pre-happy hour seminar, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kbroman/&#34;&gt;Karl Broman&lt;/a&gt; talked about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kbroman/presentations/DynamicGraphs/&#34;&gt;Why aren&amp;#8217;t all of our graphs interactive?&lt;/a&gt; I didn&amp;#8217;t know, but a few years ago Karl worked in the department and clearly promoted beer-drinking and is &lt;em&gt;the heart of the department. &lt;/em&gt;I&amp;#8217;m a fan of our pre-happy hour seminars since you have a get to listen to good/fun talks over a beer or two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I&amp;#8217;m also a fan of reproducible research and useful graphics. I do most of this by using &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.statistik.lmu.de/~leisch/Sweave/&#34;&gt;Sweave&lt;/a&gt; (for reproducibility) in LaTeX documents and with the R packages &lt;a href=&#34;http://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/lattice/index.html&#34;&gt;lattice&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/car/index.html&#34;&gt;car&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/plotrix/index.html&#34;&gt;plotrix&lt;/a&gt;, and some &lt;a href=&#34;http://ggplot2.org/&#34;&gt;ggplot2&lt;/a&gt; (I should use it more). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Karl made &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kbroman/presentations/DynamicGraphs/&#34;&gt;his presentation&lt;/a&gt; using html (definitely check it out!) and inserted pretty interactive graphics. His talk got me really interested and I definitely need to pick up a few tools. For example, asciidoc or R Markdown can be useful for making html documents with R code. Specially if you want to write a report and you don&amp;#8217;t want to deal with Sweave/Latex when making plots (can be a pain to know where they&amp;#8217;ll show up). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the interactive side, D3 (and other tools Karl listed) can be useful to learn. But I might put this on a hold for some time. Maybe I&amp;#8217;ll wait and see what others in the deparment are developing for R-D3 and embedding interactive plots in pdf files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t think that it will be long before interactive plots make it to the journals. Specially for their web versions. Though, I still think that if you are showing a 3D plot, as the author you will have to give a few default views where you can clearly see something that you want to talk about instead of having the reader find that sweet spot. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One problem that I don&amp;#8217;t think has been solved yet is reproducible research on a cluster. Karl and others mentioned &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gnu.org/software/make/manual/make.html&#34;&gt;make&lt;/a&gt; as well as having if/else clauses where you either show the output or a cleaned up version of the code that you used to generate the output. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, there are many tools and tips I can learn from Karl. And I&amp;#8217;m sure that I&amp;#8217;m not the only one! Hopefully he&amp;#8217;ll give tips on where to start (nothing is more tedious than reading UNIX man-files).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
