<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Paper Comments on L. Collado-Torres</title>
    <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/tags/paper-comments/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Paper Comments on L. Collado-Torres</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2011-2018 Leonardo Collado Torres under (CC) BY-NC-SA</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://lcolladotor.github.io/tags/paper-comments/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Great commentary on sequestration&#39;s impact on research! National media should talk about this and YOU should read it!!!</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/28/great-commentary-on-sequestrations-impact-on-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/28/great-commentary-on-sequestrations-impact-on-research/</guid>
      <description>Today Jeffrey T. Leek and Steven L. Salzberg published a paper commentary in Genome Biology today titled “Sequestration: inadvertently killing biomedical research to score political points” (Leek &amp;amp; Salzberg, 2013) which I think is a must read for anyone. Seriously!
I do not mean anyone involved in research, or all scientists. I mean, this commentary should be in the national media. Why?
Well, let me approach the technical side first. You might think that anything that appears in a scientific journal—despite any efforts to make it accessible to the general public—will rely on words whose meaning is mostly only understood by scientists.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Commenting scientific papers</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/11/Commenting-scientific-papers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/11/Commenting-scientific-papers/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;#8217;ve been thinking about commenting papers in blog posts. I did a few some long time ago, but now I&amp;#8217;m thinking of doing this activity more systematically. There are several reasons why I&amp;#8217;m thinking of doing this, say for 1 paper a week. It has the obvious advantage of forcing me to read a paper in depth per week. At the same time, I want to learn more from others. See what I like in other papers and maybe avoid some mistakes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>P-values and Statistics phylosophy</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/01/30/P-values-and-Statistics-phylosophy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/01/30/P-values-and-Statistics-phylosophy/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;#8217;m in the process of catching up with all the posts from SimplyStatistics that I didn&amp;#8217;t read during the break. Doing so I found a very interesting post on p-values (more below)
simplystatistics:
 This post written by Jeff Leek and Rafa Irizarry.
 The p-value is the most widely-known statistic. P-values are reported in a large majority of scientific publications that measure and report data. R.A. Fisher is widely credited with inventing the p-value.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beware of mis-assembled genomes: still valid today!</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/01/26/Beware-of-mis-assembled-genomes-still-valid-today/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/01/26/Beware-of-mis-assembled-genomes-still-valid-today/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;#8217;ve been recently impressed by Steven Salzberg talk as you might have noticed, and browing his home page I stumbled upon his opinion piece (also by James Yorke): Beware of mis-assembled genomes.
It&amp;#8217;s a short note published in 2005, but damn, can anyone deny that it fits perfectly for today&amp;#8217;s state of the art in the de novo genome assembly field? I bet no one will. For instance, it&amp;#8217;s a solid statement to say:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Extensive comments and review about the recent bake-off of de novo genome assemblers &#34;GAGE&#34;</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/01/25/extensive-comments-and-review-about-the-recent-bake-off/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/01/25/extensive-comments-and-review-about-the-recent-bake-off/</guid>
      <description>During this week&amp;#8217;s Genomics seminar at the Genome Cafe in the Biostats department, Steven Salzberg gave a talk on his team new published paper: GAGE: A critical evaluation of genome assemblies and assembly algorithms. I worked on a few assembly projects during my time at Winter Genomics, but that was not the main reason why I was immediately submerged into his talk. I think that it was due to his bold comments since comparing genome assemblers is a, hmm&amp;#8230;, delicate issue.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Commenting: Genomics in 2011</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/01/23/Commenting-Genomics-in-2011/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/01/23/Commenting-Genomics-in-2011/</guid>
      <description>Today is my first day of classes and Kasper couldn&amp;#8217;t have had a better timing to share the link to Genomics in 2011: challenges and opportunities. There, the Editorial Board members of Genome Biology gave their opinion on: important 2011 papers, influential people for their careers, advice to young scientists, top challenges in their field, and unlimited money projects. I felt identified several times and as:
 I think one of the most important skills in research is the ability to communicate ideas.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>