<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Network on L. Collado-Torres</title>
    <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/tags/Network/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Network on L. Collado-Torres</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2011-2018 Leonardo Collado Torres under (CC) BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://lcolladotor.github.io/tags/Network/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>rMaps Mexico map</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2014/02/26/excited-by-willingness-to-help-get-things-done/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2014/02/26/excited-by-willingness-to-help-get-things-done/</guid>
      <description>It&#39;s exciting when great people help each other get things done This is a simple networking story, which might not be surprising to some but I was happily surprised by it. This is how the story goes:
Two weeks ago rMaps (Vaidyanathan, 2014) was released. After making a blog post about it I thought about using it to make a map of the homicide rate in Mexico over the recent years.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning about social networks through an interactive presentation</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/09/28/learning-about-social-networks-through-an-interactive/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/09/28/learning-about-social-networks-through-an-interactive/</guid>
      <description>During this week&amp;#8217;s journal club meeting Hilary Parker (homepage, blog) led the session on &amp;#8220;Identifying influential and susceptible members of social networks&amp;#8221;. Were there some speakers or why did she &amp;#8220;lead the session&amp;#8221;? By this I mean that Hilary tried a very different (and interesting) format this time. Instead of giving a talk, not a formal one like at seminars, she prepared a short presentation (publicly available here) that begins showing a 20 minute video.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quid @Biostat-JHSPH</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/09/28/Quid-Biostat-JHSPH/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/09/28/Quid-Biostat-JHSPH/</guid>
      <description>Just like most scientific departments, we have a seminar (weekly over here) where very bright people come to us to talk about their work. Being a Biostatistics department, we mostly get faculty from other Biostatistics departments from universities to talk to us. This week was quite different. Amy Heineike from Quid gave us a talk describing their product, which fits perfectly in what is now called &amp;#8220;data science&amp;#8221;. You can see Amy at the end of the table in the picture below.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>