<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Paper Comments on L. Collado-Torres</title>
    <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/categories/paper-comments/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Paper Comments on L. Collado-Torres</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2011-2017 Leonardo Collado Torres under (CC) BY-NC-SA</copyright>
    <atom:link href="/categories/paper-comments/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Great commentary on sequestration&#39;s impact on research! National media should talk about this and YOU should read it!!!</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/28/great-commentary-on-sequestrations-impact-on-research</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/28/great-commentary-on-sequestrations-impact-on-research</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu/%7Ejleek/&#34;&gt;Jeffrey T. Leek&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steven_Salzberg&#34;&gt;Steven L. Salzberg&lt;/a&gt; published a paper commentary in Genome Biology today titled “&lt;a href=&#34;http://genomebiology.com/2013/14/3/109&#34;&gt;Sequestration: inadvertently killing biomedical research to score political points&lt;/a&gt;” (&lt;span class=&#34;showtooltip&#34; title=&#34;Leek J and Salzberg S (2013). Sequestration: Inadvertently  Killing Biomedical Research to Score Political Points. _Genome  Biology_, *14*. ISSN 1465-6906,   http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/gb-2013-14-3-109.&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/gb-2013-14-3-109&#34;&gt;Leek &amp;amp; Salzberg, 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;) which I think is a &lt;strong&gt;must read for anyone&lt;/strong&gt;. Seriously!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do not mean &lt;em&gt;anyone involved in research&lt;/em&gt;, or all scientists. I mean, this commentary should be in the &lt;strong&gt;national media&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Why&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, let me approach the technical side first. You might think that anything that appears in a scientific journal—despite any efforts to make it accessible to the general public—will rely on words whose meaning is mostly only understood by scientists. That is not the case in this commentary: it is a dual letter meant to be read by those in Congress, but it is also an educational commentary for the general public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main reason why &lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt; should be reading this commentary is that the consequences of the &amp;#8216;sequester&amp;#8217; are going to affect &lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt;. So if you are interested in your future and the well-being of those who you care for, then you should read it. And if you don&amp;#8217;t know what the sequester is and how it will impact research, well, that&amp;#8217;s another reason why you should read this commentary. Plus you might want to look at this (serious) comic from &lt;code&gt;PhD comics&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;span class=&#34;showtooltip&#34; title=&#34;Cham J (2013). U.S. Budget Sequestration Explained.   http://www.phdcomics.com/comics.php?f=1561.&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.phdcomics.com/comics.php?f=1561&#34;&gt;© Cham, 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;) to get an overall idea. Note that it was published before sequestration hit in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;PhD comic on the sequester&#34; src=&#34;http://www.phdcomics.com/comics/archive/phd021513s.gif&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going back to the commentary piece by Leek and Salzberg, I can imagine someone refuting like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hey, but I don&amp;#8217;t live in the United States so it doesn&amp;#8217;t affect me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is true in a sense because you will likely be affected by your own country&amp;#8217;s policies more directly, and specially in policy topics that have short term impact. Nevertheless, any breakthrough made by U.S.-based research for the most part (aka, when politics doesn&amp;#8217;t get in the way) will reach you. After all, Leek and Salzberg cite (&lt;span class=&#34;showtooltip&#34; title=&#34;(2013). The Sequester Is Going to Devastate U.S. Science Research  for Decades.   http://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2013/03/the-sequester-is-going-to-devastate-us-science-research-for-decades/273925/  [Online. last-accessed: 2013-03-28 03:33:46].   http://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2013/03/the-sequester-is-going-to-devastate-us-science-research-for-decades/273925/.&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2013/03/the-sequester-is-going-to-devastate-us-science-research-for-decades/273925/&#34;&gt;Alivisatos et al in The Atlantic, 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;) where the following statement is made:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nobel Prize-winning economist Robert Solow has &lt;a href=&#34;http://magazine.amstat.org/blog/2011/03/01/econgrowthmar11/&#34;&gt;calculated&lt;/a&gt; that over the past half century, more than half of the growth in our nation&amp;#8217;s GDP has been rooted in scientific discoveries – the kinds of fundamental, mission-driven research that we do at the labs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The claim that it affects other countries is just a generalization of the previous result and what I would consider some common sense. If this is not enough to attract your interest, then you should take a look at Salzberg&amp;#8217;s previous comment “&lt;a href=&#34;http://genome.fieldofscience.com/2013/03/a-breakthrough-cure-for-acute-leukemia.html&#34;&gt;A breakthrough cure for acute leukemia?&lt;/a&gt;” that is a showcase example of successful biomedical research funded by the same institutions being hit by sequestration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope to have convinced you to read Leek and Salzberg&amp;#8217;s commentary by now. So let me talk a little bit about the things that I liked the most.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of all, I like the tone they used because this is not a silly matter and while it may sound as alarming as &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Boy_Who_Cried_Wolf&#34;&gt;the boy who cried wolf&lt;/a&gt;, the reality is that the wolf does exist and will visit you. So while no visible effects have been seen from the sequester this month, that doesn&amp;#8217;t mean that you can just ignore this problem. It is like when you throw a stone in calm water: just a few small ripples are seen at the beginning, but they reach far away. In other words, it will take some time to actually feel the negative effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, I consider Leek and Salzberg&amp;#8217;s work a &lt;strong&gt;wake up call&lt;/strong&gt; to politicians and &lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt;. Either &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; the researcher, but most importantly, &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; the citizen who cares about the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some, specially those who are major supporters of military programs, might disagree with the whole comparison of the F-35 plane which has an estimated cost of $400 billion to the National Institutes of Health (NIH) annual budget of around $31 billion (&lt;span class=&#34;showtooltip&#34; title=&#34;Leek J and Salzberg S (2013). Sequestration: Inadvertently  Killing Biomedical Research to Score Political Points. _Genome  Biology_, *14*. ISSN 1465-6906,   http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/gb-2013-14-3-109.&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/gb-2013-14-3-109&#34;&gt;Leek &amp;amp; Salzberg, 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;). But to me this is just incredible!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strike&gt;To end my comments, I have to say that I am surprised that Leek and Salzberg&amp;#8217;s commentary is behind a paywall. I thought that it would be an open-access piece. After all research articles in Genome Biology are open-access, but this is a commentary so it is not considered a research article. To their credit, Genome Biology does offer 30-day free trial subscriptions. But I am afraid that Leek and Salzberg will lose many readers due to this reason. Hopefully, &lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt; will feel motivated enough to go through the whole trial subscription process, or maybe Genome Biology will make an exception for this commentary.&lt;/strike&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;**Update: Genome Biology changed Leek &amp;amp; Salzberg&amp;#8217;s commentary so &lt;span&gt;as of March 28th &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;it is now open-access (I wrote the post late on the 27th).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, are you not incredulous to see this situation happen? Shouldn&amp;#8217;t the debate be about spending more money in research now that what was spent in the past? The whole sequestration topic is alarming, but the fact that the budget for research hasn&amp;#8217;t increased in years is &lt;strong&gt;shocking&lt;/strong&gt;. Oh wait, you are giving Mexico a chance to catch up to the mighty U.S. in research!!! The whole talk in Mexico about catching up with Brazil or India should be about the U.S. now! (Sadly, Mexico has a lot of catching up to do…)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Citations made with &lt;code&gt;knitcitations&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;span class=&#34;showtooltip&#34; title=&#34;Boettiger C (2013). _knitcitations: Citations for knitr markdown  files_. R package version 0.4-4,   https://github.com/cboettig/knitcitations.&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cboettig/knitcitations&#34;&gt;Boettiger, 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;) and the post was written in the Rmd format powered by &lt;code&gt;knitr&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;span class=&#34;showtooltip&#34; title=&#34;Xie Y (2013). _knitr: A general-purpose package for dynamic report  generation in R_. R package version 1.1,   http://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitr.&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitr&#34;&gt;Xie, 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;(2013) The Sequester Is Going to Devastate U.S. Science Research for Decades. &lt;em&gt;The Atlantic&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2013/03/the-sequester-is-going-to-devastate-us-science-research-for-decades/273925/&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2013/03/the-sequester-is-going-to-devastate-us-science-research-for-decades/273925/&#34;&gt;http://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2013/03/the-sequester-is-going-to-devastate-us-science-research-for-decades/273925/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Carl Boettiger, knitcitations: Citations for knitr markdown files. &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cboettig/knitcitations&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cboettig/knitcitations&#34;&gt;https://github.com/cboettig/knitcitations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yihui Xie, (2013) knitr: A general-purpose package for dynamic report generation in R. &lt;a href=&#34;http://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitr&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitr&#34;&gt;http://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jorge Cham, U.S. Budget Sequestration Explained. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.phdcomics.com/comics.php?f=1561&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.phdcomics.com/comics.php?f=1561&#34;&gt;http://www.phdcomics.com/comics.php?f=1561&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jeffrey T Leek, Steven L Salzberg, (2013) Sequestration: Inadvertently Killing Biomedical Research to Score Political Points. &lt;em&gt;Genome Biology&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;14&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/gb-2013-14-3-109&#34;&gt;10.1186/gb-2013-14-3-109&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Commenting scientific papers</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/11/Commenting-scientific-papers</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2013/03/11/Commenting-scientific-papers</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been thinking about commenting papers in blog posts. I did a &lt;a href=&#34;http://fellgernon.tumblr.com/tagged/Paper%20comments#.UT534NHF0W8&#34;&gt;few some long time ago&lt;/a&gt;, but now I&amp;#8217;m thinking of doing this activity more systematically. There are several reasons why I&amp;#8217;m thinking of doing this, say for 1 paper a week. It has the obvious advantage of forcing me to read a paper in depth per week. At the same time, I want to learn more from others. See what I like in other papers and maybe avoid some mistakes. There are two main lines of papers that I would be posting about. Anything that is somewhat close to my research (genomics, RNA-seq, biostatistics, bioconductor, visualization) and anything done by my undergrad peers from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lcg.unam.mx/&#34;&gt;LCG-UNAM&lt;/a&gt;. I don&amp;#8217;t think that there is a compilation of papers from LCG students despite many of us doing research all over the globe —Mexico, US, Canada, Denmark, France, England, Germany, Switzerland, Austria, Australia to name a few countries. Maybe compiling a list of papers with contributions from LCG students is a task for &lt;a href=&#34;http://masciencia.org/&#34;&gt;Más Ciencia por México&lt;/a&gt; which seeks to promote science in Mexico. But I would be happy to learn what others are doing and in a way keep in touch academically. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another reason in favor is that blogging helps me practice my English. And writing helps me organize my ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, the question remains, if you systematically comment papers, what would you comment on?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that I should state my opinion of the paper in different areas. Kind of like doing a review. First, try to summarize the paper. Next, was the scientific objective clear? They did answer the main question? Then, given the nature of my Ph.D. program, &lt;span&gt;I think that I should try to comment on any statistics used in the papers. This certainly includes the plots and reproducibility. If they included tools (software), I could take a quick look at it. Then, I can end with stating the main things I liked. Maybe I could come up with some scoring mechanism to rate the paper.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;You can think of other aspects to talk about of a paper. For example, in what way did it help it&amp;#8217;s field? But, I don&amp;#8217;t think that I can answer this for many papers outside my research area. It would all be speculation. I guess that I could use Google Scholar to see who cited the paper and maybe comment on it&amp;#8217;s impact that way. For the LCG papers, I could point out how the LCG students contributed. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;Or maybe I could take the more educational route. But that&amp;#8217;s very time consuming as I can see from &lt;a href=&#34;http://cienciaexplicada.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;La Ciencia explicada&lt;/a&gt;&#39;s highly detailed posts.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;Anyhow, if I have something clear in mind is how I would implement it. I&amp;#8217;m thinking of making a GitHub repository and writing my comments using Rmd and knitr. Then posting them here using Markdown. It should be easy to then have a template post and fill in the gaps after reading the paper.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;The risk of using a template is that the comments will start to look boring. That&amp;#8217;s why I might add a more free section, or change things up a bit.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;If you have any ideas, let me know!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>P-values and Statistics phylosophy</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/01/30/P-values-and-Statistics-phylosophy</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/01/30/P-values-and-Statistics-phylosophy</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m in the process of catching up with all the posts from &lt;a href=&#34;http://simplystatistics.tumblr.com&#34;&gt;SimplyStatistics&lt;/a&gt; that I didn&amp;#8217;t read during the break. Doing so I found a very interesting post on p-values (more below)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;tumblr_blog&#34; href=&#34;http://simplystatistics.tumblr.com/post/15402808730/p-values-and-hypothesis-testing-get-a-bad-rap-but-we&#34;&gt;simplystatistics&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post written by Jeff Leek and Rafa Irizarry.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&gt; &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/P-value&#34;&gt;p-value&lt;/a&gt; is the most widely-known statistic. P-values are reported in a large majority of scientific publications that measure and report data. &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ronald_Fisher&#34;&gt;R.A. Fisher&lt;/a&gt; is widely credited with inventing the p-value. If he was cited every time a p-value was reported his paper would have, at the very least, 3 &lt;strong&gt;million&lt;/strong&gt; citations* - making it the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jbc.org/content/280/28/e25.full#&#34;&gt;most highly cited paper&lt;/a&gt; of all time. &lt;/p&gt;
&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://simplystatistics.tumblr.com/post/15402808730/p-values-and-hypothesis-testing-get-a-bad-rap-but-we&#34;&gt;Read More&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s like &lt;strong&gt;the p-value is a necessary evil&lt;/strong&gt;. The post is indeed a great read, but what caught my attention was the following statement:&lt;/p&gt;
&gt; &lt;p&gt;The advent of new measurement technology has shifted much of science from hypothesis driven to discovery driven making the existing multiple testing machinery useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m taking a class with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu/~crohde/personal/&#34;&gt;Chuck Rohde&lt;/a&gt; on probability with a strong philosophical component. That lead me to ask him recently how he would try to convince a biologist that he should believe/trust statistics. To explain myself a bit more, I asked the question as I&amp;#8217;ve been in environments where people follow their intuition on what is significant or not and disregard whatever statistics says on the same data. So in the past I&amp;#8217;ve been in discussion where I&amp;#8217;m the one trying to convince others that statistics say something is not significantly different. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t think that I communicated my question correctly as Rohde&amp;#8217;s answer is that whenever he says a +- on count data we (as statisticians) are not doing something right! He also reflected on the past as at some time people were quite into mathematical biology, a field that has either died out or transformed into new fields (systems biology comes to mind). Will the same happen to genomics? *Sound of a coin flipping in the air* I don&amp;#8217;t have a clue!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a sense, the post at &lt;a href=&#34;http://simplystatistics.tumblr.com&#34;&gt;SimplyStatistics&lt;/a&gt; approaches the same issue I was trying to ask Rohde:&lt;/p&gt;
&gt; &lt;p&gt;Why not explain to our collaborator that the observation they thought was so convincing can easily happen by chance in a setting that is uninteresting. [&amp;#8230;] In general, we find p-value to be superior to our collaborators intuition of what patterns are statistically interesting and which ones are not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To end the post, I invite you to read the paper &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18692458&#34;&gt;A Brief History of the Hypothesis&lt;/a&gt; by David Glass and Ned Hall from back in 2008. It&amp;#8217;s one of my all time favorites. I&amp;#8217;ve read it a few times and while my memory distorts what they really wrote, in my mind it&amp;#8217;s a great summary with a message: it&amp;#8217;s time to abandon hypothesis-driven science and continue with question-driven science involving building models from data and not from our hypothesis. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a few quotes from their paper:&lt;/p&gt;
&gt; &lt;p&gt;We propose that building hypotheses should be abandoned in favor of posing a straightforward question of a system and then receiving an answer, using that answer to model reality, and then testing the reproducibility and predictive power of the model, modifying it as necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They end their paper with:&lt;/p&gt;
&gt; &lt;p&gt;Thus, although a hypothesis might have been thought to be necessary in the past, it no longer seems to be so. It is better to see science as a quest for good questions to try to answer, rather than a quest for bold hypotheses to try to refute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you agree?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beware of mis-assembled genomes: still valid today!</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/01/26/Beware-of-mis-assembled-genomes-still-valid-today</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/01/26/Beware-of-mis-assembled-genomes-still-valid-today</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been recently impressed by Steven Salzberg talk as &lt;a href=&#34;http://fellgernon.tumblr.com/post/16468048496/extensive-comments-and-review-about-the-recent-bake-off#.TyAz0OPOzIw&#34;&gt;you might have noticed&lt;/a&gt;, and browing &lt;a href=&#34;http://bioinformatics.igm.jhmi.edu/salzberg/&#34;&gt;his home page&lt;/a&gt; I stumbled upon his opinion piece (also by James Yorke): &lt;a href=&#34;http://cbcb.umd.edu/papers/Mis-assembledGenomesReprint.pdf&#34;&gt;Beware of mis-assembled genomes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s a short note published in 2005, but damn, can anyone deny that it fits perfectly for today&amp;#8217;s state of the art in the de &lt;em&gt;novo&lt;/em&gt; genome assembly field? I bet no one will. For instance, it&amp;#8217;s a solid statement to say:&lt;/p&gt;
&gt; The source of most mis-assemblies is, as it has always been, repeats.
&lt;p&gt;He didn&amp;#8217;t add a &amp;#8220;will always be&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;will be for at least 7 years more&amp;#8221; now that we are in 2012, but it feels like this will be the case until we can get accurate (and cheap) reads that span even the longest repeat. Well, maybe we don&amp;#8217;t need such huge reads as people have been able to find large genome duplications. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And as I said in my &lt;a href=&#34;http://fellgernon.tumblr.com/post/16468048496/extensive-comments-and-review-about-the-recent-bake-off#.TyAz0OPOzIw&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;#8217;m still surprised by how careless the human genome assembly was carried out as they didn&amp;#8217;t track their own steps. I was hoping that wasn&amp;#8217;t the case, but clearly it is:&lt;/p&gt;
&gt; Indeed, many of the original assemblies of parts of the human genome were done in the mid- and late-1990s, and are now lost.

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m also impressed by how accurate Steven and James&amp;#8217; prediction was when they forsaw that people were going to be misled in judging assembly quality by contigs size without taking into account mis-assemblies. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They also called upon the bioinformatics community to take action in evaluating genome assemblies. Due to the amount of data nowadays, it feels like a inhuman (well, incluster as infeasible by high power clusters :P, well, incomputable is the correct term) task. But with some funding, I bet Salzberg and colleagues could find a way to do so. At least partially. Yet, as with anything, you need motivation, and I&amp;#8217;m note sure they are motivated to clean up the mess. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Extensive comments and review about the recent bake-off of de novo genome assemblers &#34;GAGE&#34;</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/01/25/extensive-comments-and-review-about-the-recent-bake-off</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/01/25/extensive-comments-and-review-about-the-recent-bake-off</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During this week&amp;#8217;s Genomics seminar at the Genome Cafe in the Biostats department, &lt;a href=&#34;http://scholar.google.com/citations?user=sUVeH-4AAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34;&gt;Steven Salzberg&lt;/a&gt; gave a talk on his team new published paper: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22147368&#34;&gt;GAGE: A critical evaluation of genome assemblies and assembly algorithms.&lt;/a&gt; I worked on a few assembly projects during my time at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wintergenomics.com/&#34;&gt;Winter Genomics&lt;/a&gt;, but that was not the main reason why I was immediately submerged into his talk. I think that it was due to his bold comments since comparing genome assemblers is a, hmm&amp;#8230;, delicate issue. I really like the confidence he has on his work and the way he projects it when he talks. It might be too preachy for some, but I like it. Plus it helps that I completely agreed on two key points that differentiate GAGE from it&amp;#8217;s competitors: &lt;a href=&#34;http://cnag.bsc.es/&#34;&gt;dnGASP&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://assemblathon.org/&#34;&gt;Assemblathon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, GAGE uses real data sets instead of simulated ones. I know that some might argue that a given data set can have specific properties that are not general or that it&amp;#8217;s biased to a certain assembler. It also feels a bit funny, because I started out assembling simulated data too. It certainly had its uses as I learnt a lot. But once you encounter a real data set you learn how complicated things can be, and it can be quite messy as no one gives you perfectly clean data. I haven&amp;#8217;t read much about GAGE&amp;#8217;s competitors, but regardless of how they simulate their data, I completely agree with Steven that GAGE has the advantage by using four real data sets. Plus, they were quite sensible when choosing the four data sets as they are Illumina data (the most common) with frequently used read sizes and library types. Note that even the bacterial genome have more than one replicon. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second key point is that the GAGE team made public all the data and assembly &lt;em&gt;recipes&lt;/em&gt; available through their &lt;a href=&#34;http://gage.cbcb.umd.edu/&#34;&gt;official site&lt;/a&gt; (which has a great summary in from of a FAQ explaining the project and key differences). They have certainly made an effort to guarantee the reproducibility of their results, which is hard to do and hasn&amp;#8217;t been done before. It&amp;#8217;s a sad feeling that it took so long for someone to focus on reproducibility. So it feels wrong that they have to stress out how unique this feature is on their paper, but they definitely had to. Hm&amp;#8230; can anyone reproduce the human genome assembly? I&amp;#8217;m not talking about someone reading the paper and doing it on their institution computers, but someone from the author team. I hope the changelog is saved at least in some kind of repository.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another important difference between GAGE and say Assemblaton, is that the for GAGE an in-house team ran the assemblers instead of asking the authors of each program to fine tune their results. If you had asked me a year ago, I would surely had supported the idea of asking the authors to run their programs. After all, even if you read all the documentation it&amp;#8217;s the authors who know the best tricks on how to use their assemblers (or should be very good users). Yet, I can see the point that in reality it&amp;#8217;s not the authors who run their code for each application. It&amp;#8217;s a person or team of bioinformaticians (or a biologist struggling to death with UNIX) that has read the manual &amp;amp; papers (hopefully) from a few tools and decided which is his favorite one. During this process they probably ran a few of the assemblers with a small parameter scan and compared the results. The GAGE pipeline is very similar and hence feels much real. They obviously did this process in a more rigorous way and made sure the conditions allowed comparing the assemblers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the steps common to all of their &lt;em&gt;recipes&lt;/em&gt; was to run &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21114842&#34;&gt;Quake: quality-aware detection and correction of sequencing errors.&lt;/a&gt; I didn&amp;#8217;t know about this specific tool before, but I did know about the idea. Basically, you plot the distribution of the k-mers multiplicity from your data and do something to those that are possible errors (those k-mers that are unique or have very low multiplicity compared to the expected value); most commonly you try to correct them and if you can&amp;#8217;t, you discard them. That&amp;#8217;s a very broad explanation and I&amp;#8217;m sure that interested readers will download the original paper. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, the point is that they cleaned the data sets prior to using any assembler. I couldn&amp;#8217;t agree more to the sentence:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High-quality data can produce dramatic differences in the results&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Running some kind of preprocessing cleaning tool should help, but you can&amp;#8217;t do miracles with crappy data. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is getting huge, so I&amp;#8217;ll jump to some points I&amp;#8217;d like to highlight though it&amp;#8217;ll still be very long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I&amp;#8217;m amazed by the simple concept that is &amp;#8220;N50 corrected&amp;#8221;. It does look complicated to calculate, but the idea of splitting contigs when an error (at least a 5 bp indel) is found (they have Sanger-sequence reference genomes for 3 of them) before calculating the N50 size is just great. It&amp;#8217;s simple and very effective. By using this statistic and comparing it to the original N50 size you can clearly detect &lt;em&gt;aggressive&lt;/em&gt; assemblers that don&amp;#8217;t mind adding errors vs highly conservative ones. Then, comparing &amp;#8220;N50 corrected&amp;#8221; vs the number of errors (as in figure 6) is VERY informative. I just love that figure!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result is a bit frustrating because the winner is ALLPATHS-LG. Don&amp;#8217;t get me wrong, I think that they are doing great work (they introduced new statistics for comparing assemblies, they are exploiting library preparation more than the rest, etc) but it&amp;#8217;s simply hard to come by a data set that meets ALLPATHS-LG&amp;#8217; requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, no matter which assembler you use, your result is going to contain lots of errors. There is no way around it, it&amp;#8217;s a fact! Hm&amp;#8230; unless you want tiny contigs (very conservative assemblers) which aren&amp;#8217;t really useful. I think that it&amp;#8217;ll be important to stress this out to consumers of the technology instead of fueling their wild dreams of high-quality finished (not draft) de novo assemblies. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, de &lt;em&gt;novo&lt;/em&gt; genome assembly (specially for large genomes) is still a complicated endeavor. You shouldn&amp;#8217;t take it lightly!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you might have noticed, I found this paper (and the talk) to be very stimulating and interesting. And as I forgot to do so during the talk, &lt;strong&gt;thank you Salzberg et al. for taking a huge step in the right direction&lt;/strong&gt;. It&amp;#8217;ll surely help those working on the field and that at some point asked themselves:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What will an assembly based on short reads look like?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which assembly software will produce the best results?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What parameters should be used when running the software?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A couple more notes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;It&amp;#8217;s sad, but &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ebi.ac.uk/~zerbino/velvet/&#34;&gt;Velvet&lt;/a&gt; didn&amp;#8217;t perform as well as I hoped. I had been convinced for a while that it is one of the best assemblers out there. Plus I&amp;#8217;m surprised that it couldn&amp;#8217;t run on a 256&amp;#160;GB machine for the bumble bee data set.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take a look at the E-size statistic on the methods section of the paper. It&amp;#8217;s interesting that it correlates well with N50 size. At times, I haven&amp;#8217;t been too eager to select a best assembly on N50 size as it might not be one of the longest assemblies and I felt like I was wasting data. But it is a very reasonable summary statistic for such a hard problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;#8217;m still curious on whether gap-closers like &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez/20388197?dopt=Abstract&amp;amp;holding=f1000,f1000m,isrctn&#34;&gt;IMAGE: Iterative Mapping and Assembly for Gap Elimination&lt;/a&gt; (I don&amp;#8217;t know why they didn&amp;#8217;t include the name on their paper title &amp;gt;.&amp;lt;) correctly increase scaffold/contig length by &lt;a href=&#34;http://genomebiology.com/2010/11/4/R41/figure/F1&#34;&gt;re-assembling local &lt;em&gt;border&lt;/em&gt; paired-reads&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check the websites of the competitors. GAGE looks more complete to me and I&amp;#8217;m quite surprised dnGASP doesn&amp;#8217;t include links to the other sites! The &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/#!/gagecompetition&#34;&gt;GAGE twitter&lt;/a&gt; might be a bit too much (plus it seems abandoned).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/news/2011/110323/full/471425a.html&#34;&gt;Here is a news commentary &lt;/a&gt;which talks about the three competitors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I found it funny when Salzberg declared a winner in the talk, but it&amp;#8217;s surely takes some guts to do so and I agree that it had to be done after such a rigorous comparison (or &amp;#8220;bake-off&amp;#8221; ^_^).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From the advice section in Genomics 2011 (&lt;a href=&#34;http://fellgernon.tumblr.com/post/16368703139/commenting-genomics-in-2011#.Tx922ePOzIw&#34;&gt;check my long post about it&lt;/a&gt;), &amp;#8220;Published is better than perfect&amp;#8221;. Results from a bake-off like GAGE are going to change quickly since new updates are released quickly, but they are very helpful!!!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Commenting: Genomics in 2011</title>
      <link>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/01/23/Commenting-Genomics-in-2011</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lcolladotor.github.io/2012/01/23/Commenting-Genomics-in-2011</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today is my first day of classes and &lt;a href=&#34;http://scholar.google.com/citations?hl=en&amp;amp;user=8XOPyM4AAAAJ&amp;amp;oi=sra&#34;&gt;Kasper&lt;/a&gt; couldn&amp;#8217;t have had a better timing to share the link to &lt;a href=&#34;http://genomebiology.com/2011/12/12/137&#34;&gt;Genomics in 2011: challenges and opportunities&lt;/a&gt;. There, the Editorial Board members of Genome Biology gave their opinion on: important 2011 papers, influential people for their careers, advice to young scientists, top challenges in their field, and unlimited money projects. I felt identified several times and as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think one of the most important skills in research is the ability to communicate ideas. [&amp;#8230;] practicing both writing skills and oral presentation skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;here I am sharing my view on the paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall the paper is a good read and I enjoyed most of it, so I highly recommend reading it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The top papers section is quite broad and it felt to me like a huge abstract on many papers. Now I want to read the paper on &amp;#8220;phenologs&amp;#8221;, a concept that seems very simple and natural, and has helped understand a bit more what genes do (functional genomics).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The parts about influential people and unlimited money projects are not so interesting. I felt that it was too personal and I didn&amp;#8217;t feel that it related to me much. Regardless, I&amp;#8217;d like to highlight some parts of the text:&lt;/p&gt;
&gt; * [&amp;#8230;] showed me the fun of methodology development in computational biology
&gt; * [&amp;#8230;] emphasized establishing a solid foundation in computer science and statistics but also developed our skills to identify relevant and impactful biological questions
&gt; * His humble upbringing, ability to admit when he was wrong, and persistence for what was right has continued to inspire me.
&lt;p&gt;The advice section was very appealing to me and I felt reassured as some of the advice I gave even younger scientists (&lt;a href=&#34;http://fellgernon.tumblr.com/post/13739343319/introducing-biostatistics-to-first-year-lcg-students#.Tx3PlmPOz_g&#34;&gt;check my talk to LCG students&lt;/a&gt;) popped up. I surely learnt a few things too =)&lt;/p&gt;
&gt; * Surrounding yourself with people who are smarter than you also helps you raise your game.
&gt; * Published is better than perfect.
&gt; * Importance of communication
&gt; * you need to appreciate the biology as much as, if not more than, the statistical method or computer science
&gt; * The success of our field is ultimately measured by the impact we can have on our understanding of biology
&gt; * I would say it&amp;#8217;s the ability to understand both the experimental and the computational sciences. [&amp;#8230;] I would learn the key principles in computational biology or at the very least the linguistics, and vice versa.

&lt;p&gt;I hadn&amp;#8217;t taken consciousness of the fact that the amount of computing you can do (per dollar) is doubling every year while the size of genomic databases is going up by a factor of 10. I knew something was off and that we are getting more data, but I didn&amp;#8217;t know the ratio. Plus, I have to agree with the comment that cloud computing is not going to be the solution though I&amp;#8217;m not sure if:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only solution is to discover fundamentally better algorithms for processing these databases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, we need better algorithms, but I think that it&amp;#8217;s fair to ask for cleaner and higher-quality data. This doesn&amp;#8217;t mean that the data format has to be simpler, as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Far too often, enough biological details are abstracted away so that the solution loses its biological relevance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sad, but true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do agree with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another challenge is to educate people about genomics and to tone down the natural hype of the genomics field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as with any discipline, it&amp;#8217;s not easy to explain your field to a random person and it&amp;#8217;s a harder job when someone exaggerates a set of results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The argument that RO1 NIH grants are not built for young genomics scientists is interesting and I do hope that it changes soon. Though I don&amp;#8217;t have a clue as to how the following is going to happen:&lt;/p&gt;
&gt; the last challenge is to transform the academic review system in our institutions&lt;/p&gt;
&gt; Understanding the systems-level ecological rules governing microbial community structure&lt;
&lt;p&gt;surely opened my eyes as it was one of my main interests a few years ago (and stills interests me ^^).&lt;/p&gt;
&gt; streamlining methods for turning next-generation data into actionable biology
&lt;p&gt;sounds very fancy!! It&amp;#8217;s as fancy, and important, as developing new ways to visualize networks that take into account time instead of viewing all the possibilities at once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To finish off the post, I agree completely with:&lt;/p&gt;
&gt;I believe the biggest bottleneck is the bioinformatics and the shortage of researchers in the field. There needs to be a big investment to address this shortage. 
&lt;p&gt;Note that I think that there are lots of bioinformatics-converts: people who recently joined the field to fill in the gap in their lab. As:&lt;/p&gt;
&gt;In my opinion, too many computational biology researchers are working in isolation on marginally relevant problems or making incremental improvements in areas that have already been well-populated by methods that are already adequate. 
&lt;p&gt;So, yes, we need more bioinformaticians as most labs have high-throughput experiments (with only one experiment you already need a bioinformatician), but I do hope that a good proportion of them are trained to develop methods and focus on important problems and new areas instead of marginally relevant ones on &amp;#8220;old&amp;#8221; areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s why I&amp;#8217;m studying a PhD in Biostatistics!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
