<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Statistics | L. Collado-Torres</title>
    <link>/tags/statistics/</link>
      <atom:link href=http://lcolladotor.github.io/tags/statistics/index.xml rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Statistics</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2011-2020 Leonardo Collado Torres under (CC) BY-NC-SA 4.0. All thoughts and opinions here are my own. Icon is the [R logo](https://www.r-project.org/logo/) modified</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>Statistics</title>
      <link>/tags/statistics/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>International Year of Statistics: coming up soon!</title>
      <link>/2012/08/16/international-year-of-statistics-coming-up-soon/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2012/08/16/international-year-of-statistics-coming-up-soon/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Did you know that next year will be the International Year of Statistics? Well, you probably didn&amp;#8217;t! There is a &lt;a href=&#34;http://statistics2013.org/index.cfm&#34;&gt;site&lt;/a&gt; organizing the activities and listing the institutions that morally support the celebration. I&amp;#8217;m happy to see my current work place listed there but at the same time concerned that the National Autonomous University of Mexico is not in it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe it&amp;#8217;s not that surprising since there is no big Statistics department at UNAM. Googling I found a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dpye.iimas.unam.mx/&#34;&gt;Department of Probability and Statistics&lt;/a&gt; listing 14 faculty members and it seems that it was last updated in 2007. Not looking good! There is a more &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dcb.unam.mx/CoordinacionesAcademicas/CienciasAplicadas/ProbabilidadEstadistica/index_eng.html&#34;&gt;recent site&lt;/a&gt; listing 3 staff members and it seems to be geared towards helping students. I did find a graduate program on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iimas.unam.mx/iimas/pagina/es/110/posgrado-en-ciencias-matematicas-y-de-la-especializacion-en-estadistica-aplicadaes&#34;&gt;Mathematical Sciences specializing in Applied Statistics&lt;/a&gt; and a short diploma course on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.educontinua.fciencias.unam.mx/SiteNuevo/Cursos/DiplEstadProb/2012/Intro.php&#34;&gt;Probability and Statistics&lt;/a&gt;. I think that most statisticians at UNAM work in institutes without Statistics in the name. I hope that there are plenty more out there!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several other Mexican institutions listed (just look at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://statistics2013.org/participants.cfm&#34;&gt;participants list&lt;/a&gt; and search &amp;#8220;Mexico&amp;#8221; in your browser). Looking at the list highlights how vastly spread is the field. By that I mean that there are plenty of organizations across the world that teach it, and use it. I&amp;#8217;m also happy to see that most of the activities (which are almost exclusively conferences) are not in the US. I&amp;#8217;m sure that by 2013 there will be plenty more activities listed and hopefully some public outreach events.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>P-values and Statistics phylosophy</title>
      <link>/2012/01/30/p-values-and-statistics-phylosophy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2012/01/30/p-values-and-statistics-phylosophy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m in the process of catching up with all the posts from &lt;a href=&#34;http://simplystatistics.tumblr.com&#34;&gt;SimplyStatistics&lt;/a&gt; that I didn&amp;#8217;t read during the break. Doing so I found a very interesting post on p-values (more below)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;tumblr_blog&#34; href=&#34;http://simplystatistics.tumblr.com/post/15402808730/p-values-and-hypothesis-testing-get-a-bad-rap-but-we&#34;&gt;simplystatistics&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post written by Jeff Leek and Rafa Irizarry.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&gt; &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/P-value&#34;&gt;p-value&lt;/a&gt; is the most widely-known statistic. P-values are reported in a large majority of scientific publications that measure and report data. &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ronald_Fisher&#34;&gt;R.A. Fisher&lt;/a&gt; is widely credited with inventing the p-value. If he was cited every time a p-value was reported his paper would have, at the very least, 3 &lt;strong&gt;million&lt;/strong&gt; citations* - making it the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jbc.org/content/280/28/e25.full#&#34;&gt;most highly cited paper&lt;/a&gt; of all time. &lt;/p&gt;
&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://simplystatistics.tumblr.com/post/15402808730/p-values-and-hypothesis-testing-get-a-bad-rap-but-we&#34;&gt;Read More&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s like &lt;strong&gt;the p-value is a necessary evil&lt;/strong&gt;. The post is indeed a great read, but what caught my attention was the following statement:&lt;/p&gt;
&gt; &lt;p&gt;The advent of new measurement technology has shifted much of science from hypothesis driven to discovery driven making the existing multiple testing machinery useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m taking a class with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu/~crohde/personal/&#34;&gt;Chuck Rohde&lt;/a&gt; on probability with a strong philosophical component. That lead me to ask him recently how he would try to convince a biologist that he should believe/trust statistics. To explain myself a bit more, I asked the question as I&amp;#8217;ve been in environments where people follow their intuition on what is significant or not and disregard whatever statistics says on the same data. So in the past I&amp;#8217;ve been in discussion where I&amp;#8217;m the one trying to convince others that statistics say something is not significantly different. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t think that I communicated my question correctly as Rohde&amp;#8217;s answer is that whenever he says a +- on count data we (as statisticians) are not doing something right! He also reflected on the past as at some time people were quite into mathematical biology, a field that has either died out or transformed into new fields (systems biology comes to mind). Will the same happen to genomics? *Sound of a coin flipping in the air* I don&amp;#8217;t have a clue!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a sense, the post at &lt;a href=&#34;http://simplystatistics.tumblr.com&#34;&gt;SimplyStatistics&lt;/a&gt; approaches the same issue I was trying to ask Rohde:&lt;/p&gt;
&gt; &lt;p&gt;Why not explain to our collaborator that the observation they thought was so convincing can easily happen by chance in a setting that is uninteresting. [&amp;#8230;] In general, we find p-value to be superior to our collaborators intuition of what patterns are statistically interesting and which ones are not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To end the post, I invite you to read the paper &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18692458&#34;&gt;A Brief History of the Hypothesis&lt;/a&gt; by David Glass and Ned Hall from back in 2008. It&amp;#8217;s one of my all time favorites. I&amp;#8217;ve read it a few times and while my memory distorts what they really wrote, in my mind it&amp;#8217;s a great summary with a message: it&amp;#8217;s time to abandon hypothesis-driven science and continue with question-driven science involving building models from data and not from our hypothesis. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a few quotes from their paper:&lt;/p&gt;
&gt; &lt;p&gt;We propose that building hypotheses should be abandoned in favor of posing a straightforward question of a system and then receiving an answer, using that answer to model reality, and then testing the reproducibility and predictive power of the model, modifying it as necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They end their paper with:&lt;/p&gt;
&gt; &lt;p&gt;Thus, although a hypothesis might have been thought to be necessary in the past, it no longer seems to be so. It is better to see science as a quest for good questions to try to answer, rather than a quest for bold hypotheses to try to refute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you agree?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
