<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Knitr on L. Collado-Torres</title>
    <link>/tags/knitr/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Knitr on L. Collado-Torres</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2011-2018 Leonardo Collado Torres under (CC) BY-NC-SA 4.0</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/knitr/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating awesome reports for multiple audiences using knitrBootstrap</title>
      <link>/2013/12/10/knitrBootstrap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/12/10/knitrBootstrap/</guid>
      <description>As a biostatistics student, I use R very frequently when analyzing data. At the same time, I interact with other researchers, some who know how to use R (R crowd) and some who don&#39;t (yet!): no-R crowd. This means that I have to be able to communicate my results to two crowds. It is important that I can quickly provide the code in case that the R savvy want to look at it: maybe they find a bug and report it ^^.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using plyr and doMC for quick and easy apply-family functions</title>
      <link>/2013/04/26/using-plyr-and-domc-for-quick-and-easy-apply-family/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/04/26/using-plyr-and-domc-for-quick-and-easy-apply-family/</guid>
      <description>A few weeks back I dedicated a short amount of time to actually read what plyr (Wickham, 2011) is about and I was surprised. The whole idea behind plyr is very simple: expand the apply() family to do things easy. plyr has many functions whose name ends with ply which is short of apply. Then, the functions are identified by two letters before ply which are abbreviations for the input (first letter) and output (second one).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adding youtube videos in pdfs, html reports and html presentations</title>
      <link>/2012/12/05/adding-youtube-videos-in-pdfs-html-reports/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/12/05/adding-youtube-videos-in-pdfs-html-reports/</guid>
      <description>I got a question today on how to add a video to a beamer pdf presentation. Well, I had never done it, but I got curious enough to google around for a bit and here is the end product.
One way of doing it is using the media9 tex package. For this to work you need to have the latest version of texlive (or miktex). Then, it&amp;#8217;s quite straight forward to include the video.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to R and Biostatistics (2012 version): presentation</title>
      <link>/2012/11/12/Introduction-to-R-and-Biostatistics-2012-version/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/11/12/Introduction-to-R-and-Biostatistics-2012-version/</guid>
      <description>To follow my Introducing R and Biostatistics to first year LCG students (2012 version) post, you can now find the presentation online from my site either in presentation format, in a single webpage format, or the raw Rmd file. To prove the point that publishing to RPubs is super easy, you can also find the single webpage format over there. I also like how you can comment and share in RPubs.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>